<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An harborovve for faithfull and trevve subiectes agaynst the late blowne blaste, concerninge the gouernme[n]t of vvemen. wherin be confuted all such reasons as a straunger of late made in that behalfe, with a breife exhortation to obedience. Anno. M.D.lix.</title>
            <author>Aylmer, John, 1521-1594.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1559</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1005</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100367</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836209</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836209</idno>
            <idno type="VID">466</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 194:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An harborovve for faithfull and trevve subiectes agaynst the late blowne blaste, concerninge the gouernme[n]t of vvemen. wherin be confuted all such reasons as a straunger of late made in that behalfe, with a breife exhortation to obedience. Anno. M.D.lix.</title>
                  <author>Aylmer, John, 1521-1594.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[136] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.[i.e. London, printed by John Day],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Strasborowe :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The. 26. of Aprill [1559]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Aylmer.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Knox, John.  The first blast of the trumpet against the monstruous regiment of women.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; actual publication information from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-R⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An harborovv for faithfull subiectes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Knox, John, ca. 1514-1572. --  First blast of the trumpet against the monstruous regiment of women.</term>
               <term>Women heads of state --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:466:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:466:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN HARBOROVVE FOR FAITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL AND TREVVE SVBIECTES, agaynſt the late blowne Blaſte, concerninge the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of VVemen. wherin be confuted all ſuch reaſons as a ſtraunger of late made in that behalfe, with a breife exhortation to OBEDIENCE.</p>
            <p>Anno. M.D.lix.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROVERBES. 32.</bibl>
               <p>Many daughters there be, that gather riches to gether: but thou goeſt aboue them all. As for fauour it is deceitfull, and bewtie is a vaine thing: but A vvoman that feareth the Lord: ſhe is vvorthie to be prayſed. Geue her of the fruit of her handes, and let her ovvne vvorkes prayſe her in the gate ⁂</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ At Straſborowe the .26. of Aprill. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:466:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:466:2"/>
            <head>To the right honorable and his ſinguler good Lordes, Francis Earle of Bedford one of the Quenes Maieſties priuie Counſell, and the Lord Robert Duddeley, maſter of her highnes horſſe, and knight of the honorable order of the Garter. Thauth our wiſſheth many quiet dayes, the continuall feare of God, and earneſt zeale in Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes quarrell</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE moſte noble and excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t philoſopher Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tark reporteth (moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) that bulles fleſhe corrupted and rotten, be ingendred Bees, of horſe fleſh Harnets, and of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſerpentes. VVhereby not only appeareth the great diuerſity of natures in the diuerſities of kindes, but alſo (whiche is no ſmall wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der) how of that which is moſte made of, and eſtemed, is bred the worſt and vileſt corruption, of that, which in oure cies is the beautifulleſt worke of nature, ſpringeth forth the fouleſt frute, that is, or can be found in nature. No creature in this world is counted more excellente than man: and no monſtre in ſighte more ouglie, and in nature more hurtfull than a ſerpent, ſo that we ſee that of the faireſt, cometh the fouleſt, of the beſt loued, the moſt hated, of the moſt holſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the moſt venimous, and to be ſhort, of the ſineſt in our cies, the filthieſt in oure iudgement. Vvherby God geueth vs to vnderſtand, that miſcheuous matter lieth oft hidden in fair veſſels, and no litle ill, where we think to find moſt good. If
<pb facs="tcp:466:3"/>this poiſoned venim, be in the bodye of man, to engender ſerpents: ſhall we thinke that the minde is pure? No certen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For though it bringeth not fourth (being corrupted and rotten with error) ſerpents, adders, and ſnakes: yet be the buds of that tree, either as ill, or muche vvorſe. For like as a man inhabiting a ſtinking, filthye, and vnholſome houſe, ſituate in a corrupt and vnclean aire, can not be but ſubiect to that contagion: ſo theſe mindes of ours, beinge lodged in ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure an harborowe, muſte neades be defiled with the filthe. VVherfore the Apoſtle crieth oute, qui in carne ſunt, deo placere non poſſunt, ſo long as we remain in this fleſhe, we can not pleaſe God. The cauſe of this corrupcion, no chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is ſo vnſkilful, but he knoweth it to be the dotage of our firſte parentes, conucied into the vaines of their mindes firſt, and their bodies nexte by the venimous breath, of that ſubtil ſerpent our auncient ennemy. VVhome, while they harkned vnto, they became ſo charmed and bewitched: that they forgate them ſelues, forſoke God, and became of hys deare ſonnes, his extreme enemies, of his obediente and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſeruaunts, his wilful and obſtinate rebels, and confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats with his ſworne ennemye the deuill. Here we finde the cauſe, and we daily fele theffect, in that we be in al things by nature repining at the wil of God, ready to follow the will of the fleſh, winſing and kicking againſt godlines and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, and on the other ſide, euer huntinge for fleſhlines and lies. Out of this corrupted puddle of mas hart, or rather out of this forge and ſhop of Sathan, where ſinne is wroughte and ſhapen: breaketh forth amonge the reaſte of monſters, (which it bringeth out) the horrible hydras of errors, ſects a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hereſies wherwith the world hath fence the beginning, and to thending ſhalbe poiſoned and infected. Hereof ſpra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the curious contencions and ſoundry ſectes of Ethnike Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, as Academians, Peripatetica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Stoikes, Epicures, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niks, and all that rabble. Here budded or rather flowed furth
<pb facs="tcp:466:3"/>the horrible and moſt hurtful hereſies, hatched by the deuel, in the neſt of mans mind, and vttered by the to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and pen of buſy bodies, ſealed vp to ſerue Satan in this kind of miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Such wer in our ancettors dais, the Nycolaitans, the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, Arrians, Macedonians, Pelagians, Eutychians, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomians, Neſtorians and ſuch other. And in theſe our latter daies, the old feſtred ſores newly broken out, as the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes, the freewillers, or rather frowardewillers, the iuſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. &amp;c, and others that be new, as Adiaphoriſtes, Oſeriani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, Maroraniſtes, Papiſts, with infinit other ſwarms of gods enemies, by whom our aduerſari Satan ſeketh to diſturb the true vnitie of Chriſtes church, to choke the good corn of late ſown in gods field, and to dim that excellent lighte, whiche according to his ſecreate counſell and decree, he determined ſhuld ſhine to the vnſpeakeable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of his elect, in theſe our dais. Among theſe vgglie monſters and brodes of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils brotherhead, hath of late krept out (I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not tel whether by wil or ignorance) certen <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which haue called into queſtion among vs ſuch thinges, as good ſubiectes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neuer doubted of, whether it wer lawful for women, in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heritours of kingdoms, to gouern and guid the ſame, or no. Although this error may appeare, not to touch ſo neare the ſoule and ſaluacion of man, as ſome of the fornamed do: yet conſidering that the quiet of common weales is the nurſe of religion and bulwark of good and faithful men: and that the apoſtle pronounceth againſt the rebellious vtter damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: VVe can not think it to be a trifle to diſturbe the common ordres of pollicies, to ſondre the mindes of ſubiectes, by new inuented contrauerſies, and briefly to make men to muſe, of that they neuer before miſtruſted. Vvherfor chaunſing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a boke, about a yere paſt, intitled the firſt blaſt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teining new broched doctrine to diſproue the regiment of women: After I had red it, I wiſhed that ſome notable learned man, wold haue anſwered it, that, like as thoſe which be ſtonge of
<pb facs="tcp:466:4"/>Scorpians vſe to fetch remeady of the ſame: ſo this cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wounded, or rather a little ſcratted with ſom ſhewe and appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of learning: might be again healed with ſuche plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as through the truthe of the matter, true lerning mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth. And for as much as I hoped of this at ſom mens ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds and hard of one, which is now gon to God, that he had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it vpon him: I ment not my ſelf for a time to medle with it, leaſt that a good cauſe by il handling, ſhuld in the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſom ſeme the worſe. But whan the length of time taught me that he that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, it was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuch as could haue throughly don it, made no haſt to it: I thoughte it better ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by my ſclendre handling of it to ſhew mi good wil, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the common ſilence to ſeme to winke at it. And ſo much the rather I toke it in hand: becauſe if no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld do it: all our ſide ſhuld ſeme to bear with it, which I knowe to be ſo far of: that none that I know (I ſpeake of the learned) be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gilty in this poynt, than that by ther declaration they haue not ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues giltles. I know the credit, the old prouerb hath, qui tacet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tire videtur, he that winketh at a matter, ſemeth to think the ſame. And therfore as it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that ſom on the behalf of al, ſhuld vtter the minds of the reſt, ſo ment I, though more boldly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wiſely, yet not ſo raſhly as neceſſarily, nor as I truſt more rudely the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, to let the world vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that this infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not blown in by the blaſt to al mens breaſts, yea I dare be bold to ſaye that al the beſt learned be of the ſame iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t herein that this my ſimple treatiſe ſhall vtter me to be of. So that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our ſworn enemies the papiſts ſhal haue any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to belie vs, nor our half frends which are indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be leue any thing of vs, hereafter to miſtruſt vs, nor the highe powers the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in this point to feare vs. we haue lerned a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d taught, we loue and like, we honor and eſteme true obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the high miniſtres of God, and on the contrarye we can no ſkil of ſeditious diſturbers of wel ſatled policies, of raſhe vnbrideled brekers of holſome and godlye lawes. Thus me thinke I may ſaye in the name of al, becauſe I know the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary opinion to be in fewe or none. VVherfore let our ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies
<pb facs="tcp:466:4"/>leaue of thus to charge vs, in that we deſerue not, &amp; our frindes to miſtruſt vs, in that they certainlye knowe not, or els they ſhall be reproued of loude lying, and theſe of to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frendly miſiudging. Nolite ante tempus iudicare, iudge not before the time, for haſty iudgement ſeldom hitteth the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. Now whan I had finiſhed this ſimple anſwere: I coulde find none to whom I might commend theſe firſte frutes of my labors, more mete, or worthier then your honors, bothe for that you be no les carefull for the quiet of the ſtate, the ſafety of our ſoueraign, and the welth of the whole realme, than for your own life a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d preſeruacion, but alſo, that it hath pleaſed the geuer of all good giftes, to endue you with a ſin gulare fauoure and deſire to aduaunce and promote the true doctrin of Chriſtes croſſe, which of late thorow the power of darknes, the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of antichriſtes and Sathans garde, hath not onli ben obſcured, but clene defaced a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was like ſtil to be if God inſpired not the hart of our Engliſh Helena, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuch as be about her, to ſeke out a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d dig vp his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes cros out of the do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghil of the deuils doctrin, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to rear vp again in the eies of her ſubiects, to the vnſpekeable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of al Chriſtes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thaduerſaries. In the doing wher of no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> douteth, but that you both with a few other haue and wilbe erneſt, harty, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d faithful laborers. And as this heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gift a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d godly zele is comon to you both: ſo hath almighty God ſuffred you both to taſt of the bitter cup of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d aduerſitie, (though thone more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thother: yet both ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently) therby teaching you plainly by practiſe that which is hardlye gotten by ſcience, that he is hable to throwe downe and ſet vp, to wounde and to cure, to marre and to make, to kyll, and to reuiue, and ſhortlye to do all that he lyſteth wythoute vs, and we nothing neither to him, our ſelues, nor other without him. Afflictio dat intellectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith Dauid. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bringeth vnderſtanding, both howe vnhable we be to crepe out, and how ready he is to deliuer. In this ſchole haue you both ben exerciſed and haue atteined to like knowledge to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ad not vnlike zeale to maintain, Chriſt naked
<pb facs="tcp:466:5"/>on his croſſe, the true doctrine of ſaluacion, wherof he hathe now made you ſhieldes of defence. Seing he hath thus ioig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you in theſe poyntes and others: I thoughte good wyth your fauors, to match you in the defence of this litle work, which I haue for none other reſpect at this time ſet out, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtop the mouthes of ſome to lauaſe in language, and to quiet the mindes of other ſome, which for lack of ſkil, haue begone to ſtagger. That it maye pleaſe you to graunte your good wil herein, craue not I, but your countrye, not youre country, but the truth, not the truth, but God (whoſe choiſe and decree is heare defended) your readines to receiue that is offred, and your authoritie to ſhield that is written. Take vpon you therfore the defence of this pore treatiſe, which is the defence of them, by whome we be defended all. Manye graue and ſore ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſures I am ſure it muſt abide: but my truſt is that ſuch as ſhall ſinde fault, wil either reprehend charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly or ſet out a better ſpedelye. Thus am I bolde to trouble your Lordſhippes both with my long letter, and my ſimple trauail, truſting that you wil take in good part that is heare offred you of one that honoureth your vertues, oweth you his ſeruice, and dailye prayeth to God for you. VVho graunt you both to be conſtant in his truthe, to continue in his feare, and to increaſe in muche honour to his glory, and your countries commoditie. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:466:5"/>
            <head>FAITHFVLL SVBIECTES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>IKE as ſicke or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bodies cannot abyde any great panges or fittes, or old cracked ſhippes anye great vvaues or vvindes: ſo diſtur bed and may med common vvealthes are ſone ouertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and caſt vnder foote, by ſoden and ſtraung mutations. Seing therfor that by frovvning fortune, and Gods vvrath, for thoffences of thinabitantes, Englande is of late both in honour and poſſeſſions, not a lytle may med, Yea, takinge a fall through the negligence of the Nurce halfe made a creple: It is neceſſary for al good men, &amp; the dutie of all faithfull Subiectes, to haue an eye to it, that it runne not vpon the rockes, and make ſhipp vvrake. And as in great Cities, great hede is geuen, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Citezins, nor malice of euil vvillers, it be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed by fyre, or hurt by any other caſualtie: So in common vvelthes muſt it be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that no fyre brandes of Sedicion be caſt into the houſes of mens hartes, to impayre thobedience of good Subiectes, to kindle the harts of the frovvard, and to deſtroy honeſt, godly, and comly order. For mans nature being ſuch, as it can hardly be brought to ſtupe, and eaſely ſtirred vp to diſturbe: All occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions muſt be cut of, vvherby the euyll may be enco raged to caſt of the yocke of obedience, and the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple brought into doubt vvhat thei ought to folovv. Happening therfore not longe agone to rede a lytle
<pb facs="tcp:466:6"/>booke ſtrangely vvritten by a Straunger, to proue that the rule of VVomen is out of Rule, and not in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vvelth tollerable: And vvaying at the firſt vvhat harme might come of it, and felyng at the laſt that it hath not a lytle vvounded the conſcience of ſome ſymple, and almoſt cracked the dutie of true Obedience: I thought it more then neceſſary to lay before mens eyes the vntruth of the argument, the vvekenes of the proufes, and the abſurditie of the vvhole. In the ſiftyng vvherof, I mynd to vſe ſuche modeſtie: that it ſhall appere to all indifferent men, that I ſeke to defend the cauſe, and not to deface the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Seing this errour roſe not of malice but of zele: and by loking more to the preſent crueltie, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvas vſed: then to the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience that after might follovv. VVherin ſurely his doyng is ſomvvhat to be pardoned: conſideryng the grief that like a good member of that bodie vvhich then ſuffered, he ſelte to his great ſorovv and trouble. For lvke as the eye being ful of teares, is the more vnable to ſe: So is the mind full of ſorovv much the les hable to iudge. As vve ſe in Euripides Polymneſtor being for his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of Polidorꝰ extremeli puniſhed of Hecuba a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d other vveme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (vvho pricked out his eyes vvith pins) cryeth out not only agayn them that hurt hym,<note place="margin">Eurip. in Hecu.</note> but agaynſt the vvhole ſexe that neuer came nere him. And in Hippolitꝰ vvho for the faut of his Stepdame Phedra,<note place="margin">Idem in Hipp.</note> curſſeth the vvhole kynd. So this Authour ſeyng the tormentes of Martyres, the murdrynge of goodmen, Thimpriſſonment of Innocentes, The ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cking of the gyltles, The baniſhyng of Chriſt, The
<pb facs="tcp:466:6"/>receiuing of Antechriſte, the ſpoyling of ſubiectes, The mayntenaunce of ſtraungers, The mouing of vvarres, The loſſe of Englandes honour, the purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of hatred, vvhere vve had loue, the procuring of trouble vvhere vve had peax, The ſpending of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vvhere it vvas nedeles, and to be ſhort all out of ioynt: He could not but miſlike that regiment from vvhence ſuch frutes did ſpring. Only in this he vvas not to be excuſed (onles he alledge ignoraunce) that he ſvvarued from the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the particuler queſtion to the generall, as though all the gouernment of the vvhole Sexe vvere againſt nature, Reaſon, Right, and Lavve: becauſe that the preſent ſtate then through the faulte of the perſone, and not of the Sexe, vvas vnnaturall, vnreaſonable, vniuſt, and vnlavvful. If he had kept him in that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon: he could haue ſaid nothing to muche, nor in ſuche vvyſe, as could haue offended any indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent man. And this againe vvould haue been conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: that if the queſtion vvere to be handled, yet vvas it not mete to bring it into doubt at that time, vvhen it could not, nor yet can be, redreſſed (vvere it neuer ſo euill,) vvithout manifeſt and violent vvro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be in place. For if it vver vnlavvful (as he vvill haue it) that that Sexe ſhould gouerne: yet is it not vnlavvfull that they ſhould enherit, as hereafter vve ſhal proue. And in this point their enheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is ſo lynked vvith the empyre: that you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not pluck from them thone vvithout robbing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thother. This doubt might better haue been moued vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sceptre vvas or ſhalbe in the hand of the male. And
<pb facs="tcp:466:7"/>ſo if it vvere founde euill (as I am perſvvaded it ſhal neuer be) it might vvithout the vvronging of any be reformed. But novve being ſtably ſhed by lavve, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by cuſtome, and ratefied by common co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of all the orders in the Realme: It can be no equitie to take it from them, nor any colour of honeſtie or godlines to moue any plea againſt them. If nature hath geuen it them by birth: hovve dare vve pulle it from them by violence? if God haue called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to it either to ſaue or to ſpille: vvhy ſhould vve repine at that vvhich is Gods vvyland order? ar vve vyſer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he in beſtovving it: or ſo bolde to alter that he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhould come of it? if he hable vvomen: ſhal vve vnhable them?<note place="margin">Vve may not vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de god</note> if he ment not they ſhould miniſtre: he could haue prouided other, Therfore the ſafeſt vvaye is, to let him do his vvill, vvhiche can do beſt, vvhiche can ſee plainly that vvil follovve it, vvhere vve blyndly geſſe and do but grope at it.<note place="margin">Proue. 6.</note> Per me Reges regunt ſaith vviſdome in the perſon of God, by him reigne they and not by vs. It is his appoyntment and not ours, for though vve ſomtyme haue the election to chuſe or refuſe this perſon or that (as it is in ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvelthes) yet becauſe vve be not our ovvn but his: nor haue our hartes in our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to ordein vvhat vve liſte, but muſt as vvaxe yelde to his vvurkinge: Therfore it is more agreable to dutie, and a greate deale leſſe icopardic, to honour his choiſe, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to preferre our ovvn. Placeth he a vvoman vveake in nature, feable in bodie, ſofte in courage, vnſkilfull in practiſe, not terrible to the enemy, no Shilde to the ſtynde, vvel, Virtus mea (ſaith he) In infirmitate pficitur.
<pb facs="tcp:466:7"/>My ſtrengthe is moſte perfight vvhen you be moſte vveake, if he ioyne to his ſtrengthe:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.</note> ſhe can not be vveake. If he put to his hande ſhe can not be ſeable, if he be vvith her vvho can ſtande againſt her? Thou ſhalt not take vvith the any great povver (ſaith he to Gedeon) leſt you thinke to ouercome your enemies by your ovvn ſtrength, and provves,<note place="margin">Iud. 17.</note> and not by my vvurking and might. It is as eaſy for him to ſaue by ſevve as by many, by vveake as by ſtrong, by a vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man as by a man.<note place="margin">Iud. 5.</note> Yea his moſte vvo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull vvorkes are alvvayes vvrought in oure moſte vveakenes, as infinite examples and teſtimonies do ſhevve. Yet meane I not to barre pollicie: vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvithout breatch of Gods ordinaunce it may haue place,<note place="margin">Pollicie gods gift.</note> for pollycie is Gods gifte eyther geuen man immediatly of God, or gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſtudy, experience, and practiſe, or vvo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne by quickneſſe of vvit. But vvhen God chuſeth him ſelfe by ſending to aking, vvhoſe ſucceſſion is ruled by enheritaunce and lyneall diſcent, no heires male: It is a plain argument, that for ſome ſecret purpoſe he myndeth the female ſhould reigne and gouerne,<note place="margin">God vvor keth in vveaknes.</note> if vve conſider the vvorkes of God: vve ſhall fynde throughout the vvhole ſcripture: that vvhere vvas leaſt helpe of man or any vvorldly meanes: there vvrought he greateſt vvonders and brought thinges to a moſte happy ende.<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> In the making and framing of the heauen the earth and all that in them is contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, vvho put to his hande to helpe? vvhat felovve had he to ſo excellent a vvorke? did he it not himſelf vvithout any tovvardnes of matter, any helpe of any meanes, either of aungels or man? And that moſte
<pb facs="tcp:466:8"/>bevvtifull and excellent image of him ſelfe man, did he not ſhape him ſelfe of a moſte vnmete matter, a pece of earth, a thing of naught, hovve ſo euer Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene foliſhly derideth it,<note place="margin">Galen de vſu partiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> ſaying that nature choſe the meteſt matter for euery vvoorke? Preſeruid he not mankinde, and the ſtate of al other lyuing creatures, by one ſhippe? vvherin if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvil ſearch by reaſon and not by Gods omnipotencie,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.8.</note> hovve one veſſell coulde holde ſo many couples of beaſtes, foules, vvormes. &amp;c. And if it could: hovv ſo many ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, diuers, and contrary natures ſhould agree together pynned vp in one corner: it ſhall appere not only vvonderfull but alſo inpoſſible. VVhat helpe vvas in a ſorte of pore men, compaſſed aboute vvith ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, mountaynes,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> and ſeas: to make the vvater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to nature to leaue his courſe, and as it vvere vvith a certain choiſe and iudgement to giue paſſage and ſafetie to the ſtreſſed, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion and deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the proude prince and his company?<note place="margin">Num. 20. Exod. 17. Pſalm. 77.15.104.</note> he forſed the harde rocke to yelde vvater, as a moſte ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful vvel, at the tycke of a vvande. He ſaued his people by the hande of a vvoman poore Deborah. He aduaunced them and ouerthrevve the enemies by a poore ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde and his ſling.<note place="margin">Iud. 5.</note> He cut of the head of the proude captayne Olophernes by the hande of avveake vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.<note place="margin">Sam. 17.</note> It vvas,<note place="margin">Iudith. 13.</note> in reaſon a poore helpe to Sampſons ſtrengthe,<note place="margin">Iud. 16.</note> a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of heares grovving vpon his hed, or an Aſſes iavve bone in his hande, to deſtroye ſo many enemies and bring the people to libertie.<note place="margin">Iud. 15.</note> The breaking of .300. earthen pottes,<note place="margin">Iud. 20.</note> vvas a ſclender pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycie to make ſo many Myriades to flee and one to
<pb facs="tcp:466:8"/>kille another. And to come to the greateſt of al: it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the eye of the vvorlde, and the vviſdome of the fleſhe, very vnlyke: that a poore abiect co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for a traytour hanged among thefes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a croſſe moſte vylie,<note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> gronyng and morning at the panges of death: ſhould robbe Sathan of his kyngdom, reſtore man to the fauour of God, vvynne the victory of death, and make a conqueſt of hel and ſynne. This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in it ſelfe and not taught by the ſpirite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardly: made the Ievves to counte it madnes and the Greekes mere foliſhnes.<note place="margin">1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> VVhat ſhoulde I ſaye of the meanes, vvhereby as by conduites this vvater of liyfe, this doctrine of Gods ſonne, vvas caried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the vvhole vvorlde, againſt all reaſon and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycie, by idiotes to confounde the learned, by ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite all the vviſdome of the vvorlde, by fyſſhers, the fyne Philoſophers, the proude Phariſes, the myghty princes and monarkes of the earth. And to come to our dayes vvhen the lyght of this Goſpell vvas put out,<note place="margin">Luther.</note> and Antechriſt ruled and reueled in the temple of God (vvhich is mens hartes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) armed and garded vvith the povver of Emperours,<note place="margin">Sledanus.</note> Kynges, Prynces, and Lavves: beyond all mens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, contrary to hope, a poore frier, one man, at that time not the beſt learned, through the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hande of God according to his vnſearcheable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree vvas able not vvith ſvvoorde and armour, not vvith bandes of men and povver, not vvith fauour of princes and prelates, not vvith any helpe of man, or fauour of the vvorlde: to ſet vp the croſſe of Chriſt, to pull dovvne the chaire of Antechriſte, to reſtore
<pb facs="tcp:466:9"/>Gods vvorde, to banyſhe the deuels Sophiſtrie, to make of darknes lyght, of lyes truthe, of playne fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhnes, trevve vviſdome, and as it vvere an other Helena to finde out the croſſe of Chriſt hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the dungeon of deueliſhe doctrine,<note place="margin">Eccle. hiſt. li. 10. ca. 7.</note> couered vvith the rotten bones of Romy ſhe Martirs, ſynfull Sayntes, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terſaited Confeſſores. And as vve began vvith the matter of vvomen ſo to returne thither againe vvith the example of a vvoman.<note place="margin">Quene Anne the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of reuiuig the goſpel King He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> VVas not Quene Anne the mother of this bleſſed vvoman, the chief, firſt, and only cauſe of bany ſhing the beaſt of Rome, vvith all his beggerly baggage? vvas there euer in Englande a greater feate vvrought by any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: then this vvas by a vvoman? I take not from kyng Henry the due praiſe of broching it, nor from that lambe of God king Edvvard, the finiſhing and perfighting of that vvas begon,<note place="margin">Kyng Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard.</note> though I giue hir, hir due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion. I knovv that that bleſſid martir of God Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas Cranmer Byſhop of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terbury,<note place="margin">The Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry.</note> did much tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in it, and furthered it: but if God had not gyuen Quene Anne fauour in the ſight of the kynge, as he gaue to Heſter in the ſight of Nabucadnezar: Hama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and his company, The Cardinall, VVyncheſter, More, Rocheſt. and other vvold ſone haue triſed vp Mardocheus vvith al the reſt that leaned to that ſide. VVherfore though many deſerued muche praiſe for the helping forvvarde of it: yet the croppe and roote vvas the Quene,<note place="margin">God vvor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth oft by contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries.</note> vvhiche God had endevved vvith vviſdome that ſhe coulde, and gyuen hir the minde that ſhe vvould do it. Seing then that in al ages God hath vvroughte his moſte vvonderfull vvorkes, by
<pb facs="tcp:466:9"/>moſte baſe meanes: and ſhevved his ſtrengthe by vveakenes, his vviſdome by folyſhnes, and his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding greatnes by mans exceding feblenes: VVhat doubt vve of his povver, vvhen vve lacke pollycie, or miſtruſt his helpe vvhiche hath vvrought ſuche vvounders? VVho is placed aboue him ſaieth Iob:<note place="margin">Iob. 36.</note> to teach him vvhat he ſhuld do? Or vvho can ſay to him, thou haſt not don iuſtly? He ſendeth a vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by birth, vve may not refuſe hir by violence. He ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſſheth hir by lavve, vve may not remoue hir by vvronge. He maketh hir a head, vve may not make hir a hande or foote. Nunquid contendere cum deo eſt eruditio (ſaieth Iob) is it vvyſdome to comptrolle Gods doynges, or to breake that he hath made,<note place="margin">Iob. 39.</note> or to pulle dovvne that he hath ſet vp? If vve vveye our ovvne vviſdome vvhat foliſhnes it is, and conſidre our ovvne pollycie hovve feable it is, vve ſhall ſone leaue this quarell and yelde our ſelues to his vvill. The children of Iſraels pollycie vvas to haue a king,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.</note> a iolie fellovve to rule them vvith pompe as other nacions had, and not a poore Prophet for that vvas to baſe. I doubte not, they had theſe conſideracions that our polytikes haue. He muſt be a man of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage that the forren enemy may feare him, to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine that vve haue, and recouer that vve loſte, to be vvith his ſouldiars abroade, and ſitte vvith his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell at home: But vvhat folovved this their godlie pollycie? Marry, non reiecerunt te ſed me dicit dominus. They vvould not haue the Prophet apoynted them by God, as theſe men vvill not haue a vvoman or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned by nature. Therfore they had akyng at their
<pb facs="tcp:466:10"/>ovvne aſking to their owne vndoinge. If an Ape ſhould take vpon him to comptrolle a man,<note place="margin">Man gods ape.</note> he wold not ſuffer it, thoughe it can ſomwhat countrefayte mens doing: No more wyll God be taughte or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by man, though he haue a ſhadowe of his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude. But leſt this author ſhould thinke that I make to longe a flory ſhe before I come to hande ſtrokes with him, as an euil fenced ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that can make a better bragge of his cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, then when nede is, vſe it: I mynde before I ſaye any more of this matter, to buckle with him in his argumentes, and to trie what blowes he gyueth. VVherin if I followe not the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that he kepith leafe by leafe, and reaſon by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which I auoyde, becauſe he followeth no methode: Yet I truſte ſo to hyt the pithe of it, that all ſuche as be indifferent ſhall thynke him fully aunſwered, and he him ſelfe with the boulting out of the truthe not offendid. For I haue that opinion of the mans hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and godlynes: that he will not diſdayne to heare better reaſons, nor be loth to be taught in any thing he miſſeth:<note place="margin">Man may ſone erre.</note> Knowyng that no mans iudgement is ſo ſounde, no mans wytte ſo ripe, nor no mans learning ſo perfight: but he may ſumty me miſſe the quiſſy on and fall into errour. For as it is Gods peculyar pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie neuer to erre: ſo it is a botche in mans nature ſeldome to hyt the treuth, as we ſee in all the ſectes of Philoſophers,<note place="margin">Both phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes erre.</note> Stoickes, Academikes, Paripate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, Epicures, and all other, which lackyng neither wytte, learning, nor diligence, yet came as nere the trouthe as darkenes to light, and errour to truthe.
<pb facs="tcp:466:10"/>Yea not onely they: but many auncient Fathers, (yea I myght ſaye all) not being vtterly withoute Gods ſpirite: Yet were not alwayes without their errours as Auguſtine who humbly confeſſeth it. Hierom, Ambroſe, and Origene, with the reſt who can not denye it Hominis eſt (ſayeth Cicero) errare labi, falli &amp; decipi. No man can warraunt hym ſelfe,<note place="margin">Cic. in off.</note> but that he ſhall ſome tyme ſwerue, and thinke he ſeeth when in deede he is blynde. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is man therfore I doubte not wyll paciently heare, what may truly be ſayd againſt hym, Specially ſeinge that this at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte is not ſo muche to reproue hym, as to proue the matter, and to ſatiſfie tender myndes, whiche by probable reaſons are ſoone wounded, and onles they heare the countrary not ſo ſoone healed. I ſhal in this treatiſe paſſe ouer al bie matters as of VVyat, the Duke of Suffolke, the tyranny of ſuche as then gouerned, the decaye of the Realme, and all ſuche other appendixes whiche were rather ornamentes to decke then reaſons to proue the cauſe: and will only turne the argumentes out of their cloutes and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them as they be in them ſelues,<note place="margin">A ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> and not as they be ſet out with colours. For like as a man that would bye an houſe, wyll not ſoo muche weye the gaye Payntinge, as the ſuer buyldynge: So who wyll iudge of any matter truely: muſt laye it before his eyes nakedly.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The argumentes as I remember, bee theſe,<note place="margin">The argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes.</note> not many in nomber, but handſomlye amplified. Fyrſt that what ſo euer is agaynſte nature the ſame in a
<pb facs="tcp:466:11"/>common vvealth is not tollerable, but the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is againſt nature. Ergo it is not tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable.</p>
            <p n="2">The ſecond, vvhat ſo euer is forbidden by ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not lavvfull. But a vvoman to rule is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by ſcripture. Ergo it is not lavvfull.</p>
            <p n="3">The third, if a vvoman may not ſpeke in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: muche leſſe ſhe may rule. But ſhe may not ſpeake in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ergo ſhe may not rule.</p>
            <p n="4">The fourth, vvhat the ciuil lavve forbiddeth, that is not lavvfull: but the rule of a vvoman the Ciuill lavv forbiddeth, ergo it is not lavvfull.</p>
            <p n="5">The fift, ſeing therfolovveth more inconuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the rule of vvome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then of mens gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not to be borne in a common vvelth.</p>
            <p n="6">The laſt, the Doctors and Canoniſtes forbidde it, ergo it can not be good. Theſe (as I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber) be the Proppes that hold vp this matter, or rather the pik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>axes to vnder mynde the ſtate. This is the cannon ſhot to batter the vvalles of them perial ſeate, and to beate the crovvne of the true heires head.<note place="margin">The blaſt vvas blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vven out of ſeaſon.</note> It is a ſore enterpriſe to alter ſo auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t an order, and to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge lavves of ſuche antiquite, ſpecially at ſuche tyme as the realme is full of trouble, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s myndes othervviſe diſquieted, and the forren enemies gaping for occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to inuade and ouerrenne vs: Zalencus counſell vvas,<note place="margin">Zalencus lavve.</note> that vvho ſo euer vvould attempt to perſvvade the people to breake olde lavves and make nevve: ſhould ſtande vvith his necke in the halter, that if he proued it not neceſſarie: he might be knit vp by and by. And if he could proue them: he ſhould be ſett at
<pb facs="tcp:466:11"/>libertie. And the Garamants in like maner apoynted it death, to alter anye one of thoſe lavves,<note place="margin">The Gara mantes.</note> that vvere made. This they apoynted in their commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvelths becauſe they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidred that the breach of good lavvs, vvas the breakeneck of the countrey. And ſhall vve thinke it a light matter to alter a ſtate, to plucke the chief magiſtrate out of her throne, and geue ſcope to light heades, to deſcant vpon their dutie, according to their phanſie? I vvolde haue vviſſ hed that it had bene vndone, or novv it is done: that the doer vvold for the quyetinge of vveake myndes acknovvledge his error. But vvhether he dothe or no, I doubt not by that time vvee haue vnfolded hys argumentes, ſeene throughe his vvhole ſhoppe, and peruſed hys vvares, the good ſubiects ſhal both think them not ſaleable, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be ſatiſſied, and the mouths of buſy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſtopped. And as this is don vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, and not to curry fauor: ſo I pray God to geue it foi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen in the harts of true ſubiects. VVel, novv to the firſt argument:<note place="margin">To the firſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> You ſay in your minor that the rule of a vvoman is againſt nature, becauſe the vvoman is by nature vveake, vnſkilful, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſubiect to the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c VVell, befoore I anſvveare to theſe, vve muſte ſe vvhat is ment by this vvorde nature,<note place="margin">VVhat is nature.</note> hovve farre it ſtretcheth, hovv it muſt be taken in this propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then hovv the rule of a vvoman maye agree or not agree vvith it. Nature is nothing els but a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral diſpoſition ingraft of God in all creatures, for the preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the vvhol, and of euer ikind, or as Seneca ſaith.<note place="margin">Sen. de be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nef.</note> Quid aliud eſt natura <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>quam</ex>
               </expan> deus et diuina ratio toti mundo vniuerſiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> eius partibus inferta. Nature is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge
<pb facs="tcp:466:12"/>els but God him ſelfe, or a diuine order ſpred throughout the whole world, and ingrafte in euerye part of it, as in all fire to be hot, all water moiſte, all heauy things to moue downward, al light things vp ward. The ſonne and the moone to run their courſe, motu circulari. &amp;c. whiche are ſo ſet orders in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of euery creature: as it muſt nedes follow that natural diſpoſition, onles it pleſeth the creator (who is the Lord of all) to alter thoſe properties which he hath geuen them by nature, as when he made of the mouing water a ſtanding wall, and the fire ſo to loſe his operacion: that it conſumed not the bodies of the three yonge menne that were caſte into it, and ſuche like,<note place="margin">Ex. 14. Dani. 3.</note> all whiche deedes bee wonders and miracles, and not the vvorke, but the impedimente of nature. Now if this hathe ſo beene ingrafted in the nature of al menne, that no woman ſhoulde gouerne, but all women ſhoulde bee ſubiectes: then vvere there no more to be ſaide, the matter were ended. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſee by many examples, that by the wholle conſent of nacyons, by the ordinaunce of God, and order of lawe, wemen haue reigned and thoſe not a fewe, and as it was thoughte not againſte nature: Therefore it canne not bee ſaide, that by a generall diſpoſition of nature, it hathe bene, and is denyed them to rule. But let vs here conſider, whether it be in a woman againſte nature to rule, as it is in a ſtone to moue vpwarde, or in the fire not to conſume. In the ſtone or in the fire is no manner of aptneſſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the one to go vpward, or the other to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and not deſtroy; and neither can be done in ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:466:12"/>withoute violence and outwarde force: But in a woman is witte, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, and as Ariſtotle ſaith the ſame vertues that be in a man,<note place="margin">3. Polit.</note> ſauinge that they differ. Secundum maius et minus, that is, moore in the man then in the woman. There is the ſame ſhape, the ſame language, and ſometime more giftes in them,<note place="margin">Artemiſia Iuſt. li. 2.</note> then in the man, as was in Artemiſia (as Iuſtine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth) more prowes and witte to rule the armie, then in the great Monarke Xerxes. Only we can pul from them that they be not ſtrong of body, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſo couragious in minde, graunte that it is ſo: muſt they therfore be vtterly vnmete to rule: nay if you ſaide vnmeter, then men: we woulde not muche wraſtle with you. For as Ariſtotle ſaithe the mannes rule is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is more mete to rule. But to reaſon thus wemen be not ſo mete as men, Ergo, it is againſt nature: is an euill conſequent. King Edwarde for his yeares and tenderneſſe of age was not ſo mete to rule, as was his father Kinge Henrye: yet was it not againſte nature, onles you pronounce of him as Storie bothe vnlearnedlye and impudentlye ſayde Ve terrae illi cuius puer rex eſt.<note place="margin">Storie.</note> Vnhappye is the realme that hathe a childe to their Kinge, as thoughe thys worde child were not there a Metaphor, but take an elder. Cambiſes was not ſo mete to rule as his father. Cyrus: for he vvas a dronkard a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d cruel. Ergo his rule was vnnaturall. It is a fallax a vitio conſequentis. If it wer vnnatural for a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to rule, becauſe ſhe lacketh a mannes ſtrengthe. Then olde Kinges whyche bee moſt mete to rule for witte and experience, becauſe they lack ſtrength, ſhuld be vnmete for the feblenes
<pb facs="tcp:466:13"/>of the bodi. Yea ſay you, God hath apoynted her to be ſubiect to her huſband. Ad virum erit conuerſio tua, therfore ſhe maye not be the heade.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3.</note> I graunte that, ſo farre as perteineth to the bandes of mariage, and the office of a vvife, ſhe muſte be a ſubiecte: but as a Magiſtrate ſhe maye be her huſbands head. For the Scripture ſaithe not. Thine eye muſt be to the man, but ad virum tuum to thy huſbande. Neither ovveth euerye vvoman obedience to euery man, but to her ovvne huſbande. VVel, if ſhe be her huſbandes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte ſhe can bee no ruler. That follovveth not, for the childe is the fathers ſubiecte, and the Father the childes ruler, and as Ariſtotle ſaithe (vvhome you ſo muche vrge) his rule is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is kynglike ouer his childe. But the huſbandes is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is ciuill, then if the childe by nature a ſubiect, maye be by lavve a heade, yea the heade of his father, and his father his ſubiecte: VVhie may not the vvoman be the huſbandes inferiour in matters of vvedlock, and his head in the guiding of the common vvelth. Lyuie reporteth hovve Quintus fabius Max: cominge from Rome to his Sonne in the vvarre,<note place="margin">Liu. li. 4.3 dec.</note> came riding thoroughe all the Sergeants and officers, vviche for the reuerence they bare to him, boothe for his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure and age, and that he vvas the conſuls father: gaue him roome, tyll at the laſte his Sonne the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſull bad thofficer ſtaye him, vvhereat the olde man alighted, and doinge his dutie to his ſonne, ſay de: I ment to try ſonne, vvhether you knevv vvhat belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the maieſti of your office, vvherbi vveſe that the father, vvhich by nature vvas the ſonnes hed, is
<pb facs="tcp:466:13"/>novv by order of polly cie his ſubiectt, and yet is not this rule in the ſonne vnnaturall.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiect.</note> But you vvill ſaye there is an aptnes in the ſonne to rule, but the vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is ordeined to obey, and cleane exempt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie. That I denye.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſvver.</note> For both nature and Gods vvorde giueth hir a kynd of ſuperioritie by expreſſe vvordes, not only ouer beaſts, and al creaturs ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vvith Adam:<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> but alſo ouer men and reaſonable creatures.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.</note> Saynt Paule ſpeaking of yong vvy dovves ſaith let them mary, tende their buſines, and rule the hous <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. No man I am ſure, vvill deny but that the gouernment in the houſe is a kynde of ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorite and that ouer men: Onles you vvyll as the Buoi dyd, that the men ſhall rule the men, and the vviues the vvomen, or you vvill apoynte them ſuch famylies as ſhall haue no men in them. If then they may gouerne men in the houſe by ſaynt Paules com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſion, and an houſhold is a lytle common vvelth, as Socrates in Xenophon ſaith. Then I can not ſee hovve you can debarre them of all rule,<note place="margin">Xenopho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dict. &amp; fact.</note> or conclude that to be heads of men is againſt nature. VVhiche if you graunt, is inough for the diſprouing of your minor. If you put to and ſaie in a common vvelthe: yet it vvil not ſcrue, for the profe of that is, by cauſe (ſay you) ſhe is the mans ſubiect. I haue ſhevved hovve, in that ſhe is his vvyſe, not in that ſhe is a vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For as you ſee, ſhe may be ſome mans head as in hir houſhold. But vvhyle you take this vvord nature to largely, you deceiue yourſelf vvy ttingly. thinking that becauſe it is not ſo conuenient, ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, or mete, therfore it is vnnaturall. But that is
<pb facs="tcp:466:14"/>to large a Scope.<note place="margin">Againſt nature di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</note> VVherfore that we maye vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande howe farre you ſtretche this woorde nature. I wyll axe you whether you take it, as it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, for the mooſte parte: or all together <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is vniuerſall. If you take it as it is in the order of nature, for the moſte parte: As it is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall for an olde man to haue whyte heeres in his age, or for a woman to brynge forthe one childe at a burden: and then reaſon, it is agaynſt nature for an olde man to haue black heres, or a gainſt nature for a vvoman to bringe furth twoo children or three at a burden: no man would allowe your reaſonyng. For though the one be accordynge to nature, as it is for the moſte parte: yet is not the other, that happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſome tyme, vtterly againſte nature. In lyke maner, thoughe it bee for the mooſte parte ſeene, that men and not vvomen doo rule common wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes: Yet when it happeneth ſomme tyme by the ordinaunce of God, and courſe of enheritaunce, that they beare rule: it is not to bee concluded, that it repungneth againſt nature: no more then the old mans black heeres, or the vvomans two twynnes. So that you ſee, that in this acception of nature, their rule can not be againſt nature. On the other ſyde, if you take it in a generalite, as when ſo euer the ſtoone moueth vpvvarde, it is violent, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte nature: or vvhen ſo euer the fyer conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not the matter that is put to it: then are you further vvyde. For it chaunſeth not ſeldome but ofte, not in one countrey, but in manye, not emong the barbarous, but in the chefeſt Empires, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies,
<pb facs="tcp:466:14"/>and not only in them, but in the common vvealth of the Ievves, more then ones or tvvyſe, that vvomen beinge inheritours, haue ruled after their parentes, vvyues after their huſbandes: and Syſters after their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as I ſhal at large declare. But before I come to that poynte, I muſte vvade a lytle further vvith hym in his argument of nature. VVherfore, I reaſon againſt him thus:<note place="margin">To preſer ue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vvealths is not agaiſt nature.</note> vvhat ſo euer preſerueth commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvealthes, and deſtroyeth them not: is not againſte nature, but the rule of vvomen hath preſe rued common vvealthes, ergo, it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt nature. The maior is playne, for it is mooſte naturall to preſerue and maynteine the ſociete of men, ſeing man and cities, vvhiche conſiſte vpon the companie of menne, be the chiefeſt vvoorke of God by nature, for all other thynges, bee prepared for that, as the chiefe ende: That menne lyuinge toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a cyuill companye, maye peaceablie, and quietly honour GOD the author, and preſeruer of that ſocietie: So that there is no doubte of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior. For the minor, vvhiche is that the rule of vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men preſerueth common vvealthes, it muſte be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by hiſtories. VVhiche I truſte to make ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that not only the matter ſhalbe out of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie: But alſo that men of indifferent iudgement ſhall ſee playnlie, that this man fell chiefly into this errour, either by cauſe he red not, or conferred not thauncient hiſtories, vvhiche record this matter: I ſhall therefore not onely oute of the Hiſtories of the people of GOD the Ievves, but alſo oute
<pb facs="tcp:466:15"/>of the Ethnikes and Chriſtian Stories proue, that in alages, in many cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis, and vnder euery monarck, wemen haue not only ruled,<note place="margin">Many cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treis haue bene vvel gouerned by vvome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> but happely and vvell: yea (whiche is a great matter) cmong thoſe that in that ſexe bare rule, you ſhal fynde none or very few, in vvhoſe reigne their countrey vvas the vvorſe for their gouernment, but muche the better. VVhere of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, hovv many miſfortunes, ouerthrovves, chaunges, and tranſlations of monarchies, haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened vnder the regiment of men: it is harde to nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and impoſſible to declare. But hereby I meane not either to preferre or matche this ſexes gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vvith the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. (For I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it in dede the more conuenient) only my meaning is to ſhevv that ſuch kynde of regiment, is not ſo heinous, and intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or in any vvyſe euel, as this man maketh it. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borah ſhal marche in the firſt ranke and haue the firſt place both for thantiquite of the tyme,<note place="margin">Deborah.</note> the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſtory, and the happy ſucceſſe of hir reigne. Deborah (ſaieth the ſcripture) iudged the people of Iſraell,<note place="margin">Iud. 5.</note> and the people reſorteth vnto hir, ſhe dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered them out of thraldome, and ſet them at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. In this vvomans doinges is playnlie ſet out that ſhe both gouerned in peace and in vvar, and ſo did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſequently al that any ruler by ciuil authorite might, or is vvont to do. She iudged ſaith the ſcripture and ſhe ſent Barake to the vvarre, vvho beinge of leſſe courage or leſſe zeale then ſhe vvas, refuſed to goo onles ſhe vvent vvith him. And vvhen they came to encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter vvith their enemies, if ſhe had not bene: both Barake, and al his ſouldiors, lyke vvite lyuered
<pb facs="tcp:466:15"/>warriars had geuen backe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd marred all. This wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of ſome of the Hebrues to be Barakes wife, and yet ſent ſhe him to the warre, gaue him his commiſſion and made him the generall, whereby a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that to be true, which we ſaide before: that a woman as a wife muſt be at commauudement, but a woman as a magiſtrate may lawfullye commaunde, but this exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple the blaſt bloweth awai as a peculier example, and extraordynarie, becauſe wee finde no more the like in the Scripture, but that is no ſound reaſon, it is but once in the Bible: Ergo it is no ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent example? we rede not in the ſcripture more then once or twiſe that a childe reigned, therfore ſhall it followe that a childes reigne is not by that exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtabliſhed? VVe find not in the ſcipture that the Apoſtles were baptized, and yet we thinck they wer. VVe rede but once in the ſcripture, that Peter chec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked a Magiſtrate, and yet ſome there be that dare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, and wryte bokes of it, that it is not only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to checke, but to kil an euil Magiſtrate. But that you may ſee that wemen reigned in Iudah ofter, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at one time, though it be not conteigned in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: I ſhall proue out of Ioſephus a Iew born, wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Iewiſh hiſtory, that diuers beſide this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, gouerned. Iohannes, ruler of the Iewes. 470. yeares, after the captiuitie of Babilon, at his deathe left his wife Quene and gouernes, who ruled as it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth rightwel, vntil thambition of her ſonne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his fathers order, troubled her gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: for at the laſt as a wicked graft,<note place="margin">Ioſep. li. 1. de capt.</note> he conſpired againſt her, and pined her in priſon vnto death.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:466:16"/>
            <p>Not long after,<note place="margin">Ioſeph li. pri. Egeſip. lib pri. cap. 12</note> Ariſtobulus beinge ruler of Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye at his deathe, lefte his wyfe Quene, to gouerne in his place: vnder whoſe gouernment, the lande was in quyet. And after, ſhe crowned Alexander her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes brother, (whome Ariſtobulus hadde impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned) and gaue ouer her title to him. VVhereby it do the appeare, that ſhe did not onlye gouerne, but hadde alſo authoritie to place a Kinge. This Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander, dyinge lefte Alexandra his wife,<note place="margin">Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra.</note> Quene of the Countrey: who vſed ſuche mercye and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie towarde her people, that ſhe kept them in peax, and wanne their good wyll, whiche her huſbande throughe his crueltie, rigoure, and vnmercifulneſſe, hadde vtterlye loſte. She is muche commended in the ſtories, for her good and pollitike gouernment, not onlye in kepinge that was lefte her, but alſo for encreaſinge it, vntill the churche menne, the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and Prieſtes abuſinge her pitye, and deuoute mynde, gatte authoritie to empry ſon, murder, and kill whome they liſted. Not muche vnlike in thys poynte to the late Quene Mary, who bearinge, and wearing,<note place="margin">Quene Mary.</note> a womans hart, coulde not (I thincke) haue vſed ſuche rigoure and extremitie, in impry ſoning, baniſhinge, rackinge, hanginge, dravving, hedding, burninge, fleſinge, and fleainge withal manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie, not ſparinge her owne bloude, no not her natural ſiſter: Onles ſhe had bene ſo bewitched, and endoted by her Cardinall, Biſhoppes, and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, of whome, ſome be gone before her, to taſte of thoſe rewardes whiche ſhe and they by ſuche extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie deſerued: And thoſe that remaine muſte fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovve,
<pb facs="tcp:466:16"/>onles they vvaſhe avvaye the ſpottes of bloude that hange vppon their Rachets, vvith fluds of teares of repentaunce. Oh they may thanck God,<note place="margin">The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates haue time of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentance.</note> that they haue this time to brethe them, and bethink them of their naughtie, and helliſhe crueltie, and to call daily, and hovverly, for pardon, and forgeuenes, for let them thincke that if they be not punyſhed in this life: nor repent: God accompteth their dedes ſo vile, and the faultes ſo heynous: that no temporall paines be inough, for ſuche offences, and therfore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth them to eternall damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Oh hovvld and vvail you prieſts and prelats, not for the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger you ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in, of loſing your biſhopriks a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d benefices,<note place="margin">Note you Prelates.</note> your po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p and your pride: your dignities a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d honors, your riches and vvelth: but for that hel hathe opened hys mouth vvide, and gapeth to ſvvallovve you, for the ſhedding of ſo much innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t blud, for the murdring of ſo many martirs, and ſpoiling Chriſtes church, of ſo many gliſtering, and glorious orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of al men for learning, and diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended of none for their liuinge. But to returne to my ſtorye,<note place="margin">The Quene de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued by her chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che men.</note> this Quene Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dra vvas ſo inuegled of the church me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that (as Ioſephus ſaith) ſhe ruled other, and the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies her. It is an eaſy matter for them that be of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout mindes, and godly diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to be broughte into error by thoſe, vvhom they think to be godly. And therfor that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvelth is hapy (ſaith Plato) vvhoſe gouerner is a philoſopher, or a Philoſopher their gouerner, vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> princes be lerned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes:<note place="margin">Learnyng in pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> thei ſhal not hang alone vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mouths of the prelates, but iudge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes hovv true it is they teache, that
<pb facs="tcp:466:17"/>they may ſaye with the Samaritanes: woman, we do not beleue it, becauſe thou ſay eſt it, but becauſe we haue ſene our ſelues.<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note> VVhat ſhoulde we ſaye of the Quene of Saba, whome Chriſt with his own mouth commendeth for her deſire to heare Salomons wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and calleth her by the name of Quene.<note place="margin">1. Reg. 10. Luc. 11.</note> If ſhe had vnlawfully, and againſt nature vſurped that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: ſurely he would as well haue founde faulte with her vnlawful rule, as he commended her dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t trauail. But Chriſt knowing the boundes of hys of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, wold not meddle with externe pollycies, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of realms,<note place="margin">Luc. 12.</note> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d depriuing of true inheritors: No, when he was deſired to be arbiter betwixte two bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern he axed not how the pleaſtode, but who made him an officer. Diuines (me thinke) ſhoulde by this example not geue them ſelues to much the bridle,<note place="margin">Spirituall me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld not medle vvith po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies.</note> and to large a Scope, to meddle to farre with matters of pollicie, as this is, wherupon depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth either the welfare or ilfare of the whole realm. If thoſe. ii. offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I meane Eccleſiaſtical and Ciuil, be ſo iumbled together, as it may be lawful for both parties to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in both functions: there can be no quiet, nor any wel ordered common welth. But becauſe this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment requireth a long treatiſe, I leaue it and go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde with my matter. I paſſe ouer here the ſiſter of Antigonus and Salome,<note place="margin">The ſiſter of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonus. Salome.</note> the ſiſter of Herode, of the which one was Quene of Hircania, and tho ther ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by Auguſtus Ceſar to rule ouer Iammam, Azotum, Phaſalidem, and Aſtaloniam, and the ſame regiments ſhe after left to Iulia Tiberius mothera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Auguſtus wife.<note place="margin">Ioſeph. 1. li. ca 13.</note> Theſe are euidente argumentes that
<pb facs="tcp:466:17"/>whyle the Romaynes, at that tyme the Monarkes of the worlde, did ſo beſtowe kyngdomes vpon wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they thought it not to be againſt nature, for that ſexe to gouerne. Many other exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of ſuch regimentes there be in the hiſtories of the Iewes, which I might alledge for this matter, if I thought not theſe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, but that it may appeare, that not only it was in vſe, and practiſe in that nacion, to bee ruled by that ſexe, but alſo emong the gentiles, which were rather ledde by the lawe of nature, then hedged in with gods pollycie: I will ſhortly runne ouer, ſome of their prophane hiſtories. Beroſus, a Babilonian borne,<note place="margin">Lib. 5.</note> and for the truthe of his ſtorie preferred before all the Grekes, and worthely (for he followed no fables, as they commonly dyd, but the recordes of the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies) ſaith, that Noah whiche was called Ianus (for iain ſignifieth wyne, whiche he inuented) made his daughter Crana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quene and gouernes of Italy,<note place="margin">Crana No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ahs dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter.</note> which thing being true (as it is moſte lyke) howe dare men ſaye that their regiment is againſt nature. VVhiche that worthy father, whome God thought amyddes his vnſpeakeable wrath, againſt the whole world, not only to ſaue and preſerue, but alſo to make hym the author of the newe worlde: did not only ſuffer, as a thinge tollerable, but apoynted as an order moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. If we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempne his dede: we muſt alſo conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Gods choiſe, who could not fynde, or pick oute a worthier or wvſer man, to be the reſtorer of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind, then hym: that ſhould ſo ſhamefully erre, as they ſaye againſt nature. In the monarche of the Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,<note place="margin">Hero. li. 1.</note> were very notable Semiramis, and Nicocris,
<pb facs="tcp:466:18"/>both for their vviſdome and ſelicite in gouerning, &amp; alſo for the notable monuments they leſt behind the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Semiramis,<note place="margin">Semira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.</note> after the death of hir huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Ninus, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leaſt the late conqueſtes and countreis vvoulde not be kept in avve by hir ſonne, yet yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of yeares, vnſkilfull in gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and not of courage mough to play the king: in the perſone of her ſonne, for the tyme of his nonage ruled ſo (as Beroſus ſaith of hir) that ſhe paſſe in ſeates of vvarre, in triumphes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes, and vvelthe, all that vvere then lyuinge, or before hir. She buylded Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia, ſhe inuaded India, vvhether neuer king nor Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour came.<note place="margin">Iuſt. lib. 1.</note> but Alexander the great. Thother Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocris (as Herod. reporteth) vviſer then the former,<note place="margin">Hero. li. 1.</note> deſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did hir empire agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the Medes, who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſought the monarchie of the vvorlde. She vvrought ſuche a vvonder in the great flud Euphrates, as al men, then vvere amaſed at it, and yet, thinke it almoſte incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for ſhe made it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to all mens expectacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to leave thold courſe, and to folow hir deuiſe to, &amp; fro, to ſerue the citie moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modiouſly. So that ſhe did not only paſſe all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in wyt: but ouerca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts with povver. VVhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe died, ſhe cauſed to be ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in hir ſepulchre theſe vvordes. If any king of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon ſtande innede of treaſure, let him ſearche my tombe.<note place="margin">Nicocris byl in hir tombe.</note> But not onles he be in nede. This ſepulchre was neuer touched, til Darius wan Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vvho dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vp hir graue, fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nothing but a vvriting to thꝭ effect. If thou weert not an vnſaciable rauenour, thou vvouldeſt not ſcrape for riches emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g dead mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. I thinke that ſome fault vvilbe found in theſe, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:466:18"/>ſpecially in Simiramis, by cauſe ſhe attyred hir ſelfe lyke hir ſonne: and that ſhalbe thought a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> For it is the maner of the world to blot out many good and honeſt dedes, with obiecting of one euil. But that can not hurt my matter, nor helpe his. For ſo that I wyn at his hand that theſe wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and kept their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis in as good order, or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then any men did: it is a great likelihod, that this ſexe is not ſo vnapt to rule, as he maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Maſagits reigned Thomirꝭ<note place="margin">Thomiris</note> a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch fame for hir wiſdom, and power:<note place="margin">Hero. li. 1.</note> that Cirꝰ that noble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian and firſt monarche after the Medes, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to hir for mariage, to whome ſhe made anſwer,<note place="margin">Thomiris aunſvver.</note> that ſhe knew his meaning was to mary hir kingdome, and not hir: which anſwer, if Quene Mary had gyuen to Philip: Calles, Hams, and Guiſnes, had not bene loſt, nor thꝭ good lady hir ſiſter, and our ſouereigne, ſo lefte in the breers, beſett about on euery ſyde almoſte, with mightie enemies, empouery ſhed, and robbed of hir common treaſure, and hir ſubiectes ſo fleſed, that they muſt ſcrape nere the boones that vvill get any more. This Thomiris vvith this anſvvere kyndled Cirus vvrath ſo muche:<note place="margin">Kinges ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not beare repulſes.</note> that (no remedy) he muſte vppon hir and haue hir by force, vvhome he could not gett by fayre meanes. And hadde at the firſt ſo good lucke againſt hir: that he kylled hir ſonne, and the moſte parte of his armie. But this noble Quene, let it not long go vnreue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the field hir ſelf, and pitching a battell againſt him: ouercame hym that hadde before ouercome all other, cutte of his head and thruſt it into a veſſelful of bloud ſaying:
<pb facs="tcp:466:19"/>drinke thy fill, vvhiche haſt euer ſo thirſted bloud. In this ſtory, by the vvay is to be noted, that if kings be vvovvers and no ſpeders: there can be ſmall hope that they vvill be faithfull friendes after. For greate men, can not beare great repulſes, ſpecially vvhen their povver is ſuch as they can vvhen they vvill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge it. And a mynde, or harte, vvhere loue hath dvvelt, if it begynne ones to hate: is lyke a ſponge vvhiche ſucketh vp as muche vvater of malice, as it had before hony. Mother vnto this greate monarke Cirus vvas Mandane,<note place="margin">Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dane.</note> doughter vnto Aſtiages king of Media: who hauing no more children but hir, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he drempt that out of his doughters vvombe, ſprong a tree vvhich ſhadovved all Aſia: thought by deſtroing hir child begotten of Cambiſes a Perſian,<note place="margin">Hero. li. 1.</note> he ſhould auoide the deſtenie. And therfore aſſone as the child vvas borne, deliuered it, to one Harpagus a truſty ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his,<note place="margin">Iuſt. lib. 1.</note> to be made avvay, and deſtroyed. But Harpagus, forcaſting lyke a vvyſe polytike ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovve, that if he killed the childe: the mother enhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting after hir father, vvould be on his bones for it, and call him to accompte: founde the meanes that it vvas ſaued. This mans forſight, vvas not muche vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ke the polly cie of ſome by ſſhops in Englande,<note place="margin">Harpagi in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> in the late quenes dayes, vvho being more vvyſe, and leſſe furious then the reſt: though they ſerued at an ynche in their calling, in ambaſſages, to fetche in the holy father, to miniſter vngracious counſell, and do all that vvas commaunded: yet vvould they not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, to be any of the broylers of the milde martirs, or the common hang men, as the reſt vvare, leaſt the
<pb facs="tcp:466:19"/>day might come, that Mandane, might axe accompt of theſe Harpagi, for her children and ſeruantes, but the reſt as deſperate dicks, went forward in their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines,<note place="margin">Deſperate dickes, good Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in England.</note> ſpared none, dred no pearill, looked no further then their fote, but with to the and naile cried downe with the ſide, hang ſome, racke ſome, beheade ſome, baniſh ſome, broile ſome, fetch them vp with num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of harneſſed men, into the Tower wyth them, ſpare neither kithe, nor kin, ſiſter nor other, it made no matter, ſo they might ſhew them ſelfes obedient ſubiects to the Quene, and diſobedient traytors vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and the realme.<note place="margin">Harpagi ſignifyeth raueners.</note> Theſe were Harpagi in dede and furi, but not in wit and forſight. Now to mi pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if it hadde not bene an order in Media that the daughter ſhuld ſuccede the father: yea in the whole Monarchie of Aſia: what needed Harpagus to haue miſtruſted Mandanes reuenge. So that it is more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euident, that women might not only enherite after their fathers, in prouinces, and ſmall kingdoms: but in great Monarchies, and Empires, which ſhuld not haue bene ſo permitted in all places: if it had bene ſo much againſt godes forbid. If I ſhuld here tarye in the ſetting oute of Artemiſias noble courage,<note place="margin">Artemiſia</note> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wiſdom, and felicitie in Gouernment, of whom Herod maketh mencion: I ſhould eaſely finde,<note place="margin">Hero. li. 8</note> how to begin: but hardly, how to end, wherfore I ſay onli of her, as Herod. Iuſt. and all other writers do:<note place="margin">Iuſt. li. 2.</note> that ſhe was more mete to haue gouerned that heuge ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Xerxes, which for the greatnes dranke dry all the riuers it came to, then he him ſelf was. For when he inuaded Grecia, and by the ſubtiltie of Themiſto
<pb facs="tcp:466:20"/>cles was diſcomfited at Salamine, and like a coward was glad to take his feete: She not onlye encouraged her ſouldiours, ſo as they paſſed al other in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict: but alſo gaue the king ſuch counſel, as if he had followed it: all Gretia had ſmarted for it: and he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly haue bene the conqueroure. But he like a braynſick beaſt, thinking as many do, that it had ben a ſhame, to be well counſeled or ruled by a woman: had rather follow his owne fanſy, to his vtter vndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:<note place="margin">In cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell looke not to the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, but to the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> then her wiſdom to ſaue his country and army. And therfor he went home not like a king, but like a cockeſcome, not like a conqueror, but like a coward, not like a man, but like a mouſe, in a fiſhers boote, with one or two with him: whiche broughte oute ſo many as it is almoſte at theſe daies incredible. If he could haue bene as wiſe, as God mighte haue made him: or as the counſel of Bethulia at the comming in of Olophernes were: he had bene the greateſt that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was vpon the earth.<note place="margin">Iudith. cap. 8.</note> Theſe Bethulians when thei were beſieged of Olophernes: wer conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t all the hole Senate to come to Iudithes houſe, a meane widowe, but a wiſe, and godly woman, and to heare her, folow her cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d obey her. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they wer al at their wits end, ready to geue ouer the city like milk ſops, and venture religion, wife, and children, goodes and liues, in thenemies ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds: She indued with gods ſpirit and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, found the way through wit, prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the help of God, not only to deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but to reuenge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only to ſaue their pols, but to cut of thenemies. wher was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſaying, which is ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vrged: a woman may not open her lips in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?
<pb facs="tcp:466:20"/>A woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be no iudge? ſhe opened her mouth, and vttered her wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when they al wer gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled, and not only that, but toke the ſworde in her tender hand, and did executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like a magiſtrate vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gods enemi. But of that place of Paul I ſhal ſpeak of at a nother time at large, I may not tary in the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of al the prophane hiſtories, which ſcrue to this purpoſe, leaſt I ſhuld ſeme to write an hiſtory, and not a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vvherfor the reader being inſtructed with theſe ſhal not nede but only to be put in minde of the reſt that remain.<note place="margin">Iſis. Beroſ. li. 5</note> Iſis (after the death of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Oſiris) reigned ouer al Egipt with ſo much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the welth of the realm: that ſhe was after her death co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a goddeſſe. For as Tullie ſaith,<note place="margin">Cic. de na. deorum.</note> the foliſh antiquitie, honored me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as gods after their deathes, which either exceded in power, or wer great by birth, or had done ſome notable pleaſure to their country. Lauinia after the death of Aeneas reigned in Latio: Dido in Carthage:<note place="margin">Liui. li. 1. det 1. Beroſ. li. 5, polyb. Iuſt. li. 14.</note> Oli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pias (Pirrhꝰ daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) in Epire: Aramea, in Scithia, Cleopatra, in Egipt in the time of Auguſtꝰ: and a Quene in Illiria, who durſt venture to withſtand the Romains, when they wer greateſt. Olimpias (after the death of great Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander) in Macedonia: a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d infinit more, which thei that be expert in hiſtories, know. It is a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, that men vnſkilled in the diuerſities of times, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hiſtoris, dare thus ventre in ſo great matters: which, becauſe they be ſomwhat obſcure in the Bible, therfor they think can no where els be found. Not much vnlyke the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort of Germains, which trauailinge no further then they may ſe the ſmoke of the ſtouf: think that
<pb facs="tcp:466:21"/>in their country is the paradiſe of the world, and that in it is al things and in all other nothing, and like to a certen. Sir Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſaid, by my prieſthode if the Trinitie were not in my portaſe, I wold not beleue it. I make not this compariſon, as though I thought not the Bible to be a paradiſe. wherin are to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all the beſt hearbes and frutes that be: but meaninge that all antiquitie of time, all hiſtories and monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, canne not be conteined in ſo lyttle rometh. VVherfore,<note place="margin">The kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Inſtories is a greate peece of learninge.</note> if men wil decide weightie matters, ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vppon antiquitie: they muſt not only counſell with the Bible, but excerciſe them ſelfe in aunciente ſtories. And therefore, Philippe Melanthon (one of the Princes of learning, at this day) trauaileth more in theſe his laſt yeares, in the reading, gathering, and ſetting furth of hiſtories: then of any other kinde of learninge, and not withoute reaſon. For hiſtories (ſaith Tullie) be the witnes of times,<note place="margin">Cic. de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. li. 2.</note> the candle of truthe, the life of memory, the Ladye of life, and the regeſtre of antiquitie. VVherfor, let no man diſdain hiſtories, or find fault with vs, though we trauaile in hiſtories about this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſy, for nothinge better openeth it, nothing more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmeth it, nor nothing ſoner bringeth out of doubte, that is nowe broughte into queſtion. Nowe thou ſeeſt (good Reader) howe this matter ſtode among the Iewes, and gentils, how neither of them debarred the heires female, of their right, and title of enheritance, when ſo euer it fell to their lot to ſuccede their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as though it had ben vnlawful, vngodly, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnnatural for that ſexe to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern. There remaineth, that we run ouer a fewe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes
<pb facs="tcp:466:21"/>in like maner among the chriſtians: leaſt the contrary ſide might haue their refuge and ſtartinge hole there. VVherfore, diſday ne not to heare a fewe more, and ſo wil I end with this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.<note place="margin">Regiſt. an nali. mag.</note> Theodora (otherwiſe called Helena) reigned after the death of Leo Themperour, in Conſtantinople ouer all Aſia, as lady and Empreſſe, and ſauing that ſhe was ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticious, and wilfull (thorough the lewde perſwaſions of hir clatteringe Clargie, in the defence of Images) there was no great, faulte to be founde in hir gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In this poynt in dede ſhe was more then mad. For ſhe digged vp the bones of Conſtantinus hir fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in lawe and burned them for an heretike. As the late quene did doctor Buſars and others.<note place="margin">Bulling de orig. erro.</note> I can not tel whether ſhe did it with the lyke ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnite, or more ſpite, then this was done in Englande. But it is lyke that ſhe had hir by ſſhops, and ioly Clargie to ſet it forwarde. I rede not that there was any Cardinall of counſel in it, as was of late (by report) in the deuiſing to burne king Henry theights bones. If the ſpiritual ſpiders ment it without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion: it was to ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: if they had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion ſuerly it was to vnnatural. But Prince and Prelates deale it betwixt them: But for the matter ſhe gouerned by the conſent bothe of the ſpiritualtie, and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poraltie, and as it was thought laufully, vvhiche is inough for my purpoſe. For if it vvere thought lauful for a vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be an empreſſe, to vvhome belonged the managinge of the greateſt parte of the vvorlde: It can not be then vnlaufull for a vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to rule one litle realme: and as for hir faults vvhat ſo euer they vvere, that can not vvype avvaye
<pb facs="tcp:466:22"/>hir right:<note place="margin">Quintus Curtius. Herod. Sabell.</note> no more then the crueltie in Nero, and Do mitian, drunkennes in Alexander, and Cambiſes, &amp; other faultes in other rulers, made them vnlavvfull gouernours. Elias ſaide to Achab, it is thou, and thy fathers hous, that troubleth al Iſraell:<note place="margin">1. Reg. 8.</note> but he inferred not therfore that he was an vnlawful kyng. Saul was reiected of God for his wickednes:<note place="margin">1. Sam.</note> and yet Dauid ſo long as he lyued called him the lordes anoynted. Chriſt called Herode foxe,<note place="margin">Luc. 13. Math. 23. Marc. 12. Luc. 11.</note> and the Scribes and pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies ypocrites: yet did he not impugne their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, or deface their title. VVherfore, though there be ſome faultes to be found in this Theodora, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: yet proueth it not that thei may not reigne, for it is a fallax ab accidente to ſay, ſhe was naught: ergo, ſhe might not rule:<note place="margin">A fallax is a deceitful argument in Logike</note> for that hangeth not vppon the rule, that ſhe was naught, but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the perſone. As if you ſhould ſaye, my L. lubber of London is a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt: ergo he is no by ſſhop. I warrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you, though he graunted you the antecedent whiche he can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denie: yet he would denye the conſequent, or els he would call for wylie VVatſon to helpe him: In Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, tyl of late yeares wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enherited the crown as in Englande, and Scotlande, vntill that they ment by the lawe ſalique, rather to defeate vs of our title, then to condempne the ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as vnlaufull, as you may now ſee by the Frenche king. He neither thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it vnlaufull or vnnaturall to be lorde of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie by that womans tytle. I woulde you coulde perſwade either him or your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey men, to thinke that the quenes title by cauſe ſhe is a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is vnlau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſo do your own countrey good firſt, and let
<pb facs="tcp:466:22"/>vs alone with ours. And as you ſpeede there, you might ꝑchaunce encourage vs to follow when it may be done laufully. Tully ſaith, ne ſis curioſꝰ in aliena rep.<note place="margin">Li. 1. off.</note> The voyce of a ſtraunger, is to be hard in the pulpit ſo long as he ſpeaketh Gods worde: But a ſtraungers voyce is not alowed in foro, in the parliament about pollycie, by cauſe he is not a citezen. This I ſaye not to philip you, as though you ment euill to vs (for I am perſwaded that you loue England aſwell as your own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey) but I meane to moniſh you, that being a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger you diſturbe not our ſtate: leſt you giue oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſion to them that know you not, of ſuſpicion. It is a great enterpriſe (and as they ſay no balle playe) to pulle a quenes crowne of hir head: and ſpecially ſuch a ones, as many ages haue not ſene, nor many coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis enioyed, or many hiſtories recorded the lyke. I would not be wounded in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, with any atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte againſt hir: if I might be lord of al, that Philippe, &amp; the french king haue. VVel, I muſt leaue hir for this tyme, leſt the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of hir vertues make me to forget my matter. And that we may make an ende of our recompt of hiſtories, we wil go forward:<note place="margin">Munſte. Duke of Svveuia.</note> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Duke of Sueuia, ſonne of Fredericꝰ the firſt, called Barbaroſſa, maried the heire of Scicilia, and ſo beca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e king therof &amp; emperour of Rome. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>radꝰ Palatinꝰ,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r. Pala.</note> left behinde him one only doughter Agnes, whiche was Palatineſſe, and after being maried to Henry the duke of Saxo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, made hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Palſgraue: who in like maner died and left a doughter called Gertrude palatineſſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Otto duke of Bauaria maried &amp; beca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e palſgraue &amp; the ſame order of diſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remaineth yet in
<pb facs="tcp:466:23"/>the moſte part of Thempire. Here I myght nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber a gret ſort in Spain, who ſucceded &amp; ruled in the realm But I ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with ſuch as be of late memory, as Ioanna the mother of Charles the fift,<note place="margin">Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na the mother of Charies.</note> who reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and gouerned the countrey not ill, as the Stories report. Mary (the doughter of Charles called Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor) the warrier and wife to Maximilian,<note place="margin">Marie.</note> ſucceded hir father in the Duckdom of Burgundy, and the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of Flaunders. I let pas Mary, Charles ſiſter who ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Flanders in our tyme,<note place="margin">Tillius.</note> And Fraunces the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch kinges mother, who during the terme of her ſonnes captiuitie in Spayne after he had daunſed his pauino at Pauia, ruled the whole dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wherby the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch though they will haue no heires females: yet ſhewe that they condempne not the regiment of women. Other there haue bene, and that not a fewe, whiche haue gouerned and enherited in diuers countreis of Chriſtendome, with muche commendacion. As A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malaſinta the mother of Athalaricus,<note place="margin">Tillius in Chronog. Amala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinta.</note> when ſhe ſawe that the Frenche men, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to all right would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue hir ſonne of Prouince, whiche was his enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce: deliuered it vp to Theodoberto, king of the Mediomatrices, which kept it to thuſe of hir ſonne, Thus was the mother conſtreyned by the purpoſed wrong of the ſubiects, to ſeke remedy for hir ſonnes right, and was a better gouernes to him then he to him ſelfe.<note place="margin">An. 1552. Tillius.</note> Leonora doughter to the king of Aquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, was maryed to Henry Duke of Gaunte, and in ſpite of the Frenche kyngs teethe, brought hir huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande Aquitanie and Poiteaux. Adela mother to the king of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, was made Regent of the countrey in
<pb facs="tcp:466:23"/>thabſence of her ſonne, while he was in the warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sarazens, and gouerned wel. This hir ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne (for his goodneſſe and wiſdome) was called Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus a deo datus ſente of God, and yet thoughte it not amiſſe, to put his mother a wiſe woman in truſt with the whole realme. And according to his expectacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he toke no hurt nor los by it.<note place="margin">Tillius. 1227.</note> In like maner Blanch mother vnto Ludouicꝰ for his vertue named Diuus holie, was twiſe made rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Fraunce, while he was away in the ſame warre. And after his death, ſhe had the gouerning of her ſonne and the realm. It is like that if her gouernment had not ben good at the firſt: the nobles and people wold haue bene lothe to haue had her again the ſecond time. Not longe after that time, gouerned a woman in Flaunders, named coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe Margarite. An. domini. 1247.</p>
            <p>Ioanna the neſe of Diuus Ludouicus was Quene of Nauarre,<note place="margin">Tillius. 1245.</note> and marrying with Philip named Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: made him king of Nauarre, by which meanes, that countrey came to be vnder the Frenche Kinge. And anno. 1415. was a woman gouerneſſe and Quene of Naples, called Ioanna. Not only in Fraunce, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Spaine, and Germany: but alſo in thempire haue women ruled, whiche is more ſtraunge,<note place="margin">Paul. Emi li. Valer. Anſel.</note> becauſe the Emperour is choſen by election, and commeth not to it by enheritance. As anno. 1301. after the death of Henrye the thirde. Hagne his wife for the honor na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Auguſta, gouerned both her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in his nonage and thempire, keping it in good order,<note place="margin">Biſhops buſye bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies.</note> vntil the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Colen (as thoſe men wilbe buſy in pollicies) by certen conſpiracies, pulled the yonge Emperoure
<pb facs="tcp:466:24"/>Henry the .4. from her, after what time grewe much trouble in Thempyre. Hereby we ſee, that in no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, thei thought it a monſtrous Reigne, or againſt nature, for a woman to gouern: which error bringing our auncetors in the reign of Sthephe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be wicked periures cauſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ro conſpire with the ſaid vſurper to kepe Mathilda the daughter of Henry the firſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the title,<note place="margin">Poly. A. li. 19.</note> right, and crown of this realm, but God not ſuffring ſuch an extreme wronge, ſo toſſed him in warres, both extern and ciuil, to the vtter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of the realm: that they wer glad to grow to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grement, and ſuffer her ſon to haue his right, and the vſurper had not only neuer a good day, ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as he reigned: but alſo by the iuſt iudgement of God, firſt was impriſoned, and next loſt his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Euſtachiꝰ, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was all his glory, thinking, he ſhuld haue reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after him: what ſhuld we ſay? God hath not onli ſhewed his diſpleſure and wrath, againſt ſuch as haue ſought, vnder this pretence to defeat true heirs: but alſo hath in this our realme, raiſed vp greate houſes by their menes, as the houſe of York by Philippa a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Anna, which by mariage, brought the title into the houſe of the Morty mares. And King Henry the .7. and all that line,<note place="margin">Poly.</note> colde not claim but by the woman, which was daughter to Henry the .6, and mother to Richard Duke of Richmond. Charles the .8. refuſed Maximilians daughter, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was betrothed, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maried the heir of Britain called Anna, deſpouſed to Maximilian, but ſeduced by certen noble wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of the french King, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by that mariage, became Lord of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, againſt the wils of al the nobles.
<pb facs="tcp:466:24"/>For they thought it better to marrye one, whiche might be their ſeueral Lord, then to ioign Britaine with ſuch a realm, as ſhuld drown the name of it, and bring them (as they be) to ſlauery: Amias was defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, againſt tharmy of Maximilia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Arnoldus</note> it had ben els loſt, as al the french men confeſſed, her name was Catherina licia. A maid defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Orliance,<note place="margin">A vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noble and happye in vvarres.</note> in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, againſt the duke of Burgundie and the Engliſh army, and after with the ſame her army led the yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g king Charls the .7. to Rome, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ther crowned him. Before this maids time, the Engliſh euer proſpered, and the french wer eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the laſt caſt, geuing vp the goſte, but ſhe brought them into that condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that afterwarde, they grewe: and we appaired.<note place="margin">The firſte healpe of the french a vvoman</note> Helena the Quene of the Adiabenits, ruled ſo wiſely and godli: that after her deth, the Iewes erected a monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for her remembrance at the gates of Ieruſalem: She mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to the nede of the pore liberally, in the greate dearth that than was in Iury.<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. 2. cap. 10.</note> Thus thou ſeeſt (good Reader) that if this man take nature ſo generallye, as it may ſtretche to all conntries, all tymes and al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welthes, and then ſaye, it is againſt nature for a woman to rule: That is againſte the generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fente and order, engrafte by nature, in al peoples and mennes mindes: that then it is mooſte vntrue. For I haue proued, that neither the Iewes, nor the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tils, nor yet the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, had that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted bi nature in their harts that it ſtode not with good order of nature that one of that ſex ſhuld rule. But ſhortly I reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus with him, whatſoeuer is natural, the ſame is vniuerſal. But that wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:466:25"/>not rule is not vniuerſall, Ergo, it is not naturall. If to rule in women be vnnaturall: then not to rule, is naturall. But not to rule is not vniuerſall. Ergo it is not natural. That it is not vniuerſal we haue proued by a great number of hiſtories which teſtify that we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in al ages, and all countries, haue gouerned. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain what ſo euer is naturall hath in the mind of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as that there is a God, all menne haue it in their mindes ingrafted by nature, that al ſocieties muſt be ruled and ordered by magiſtrates and lawes: that murder is wicked and againſt nature. &amp;c. which be common opinions in the table of mannes minde, written by the finger of God, with the pen of nature: but of this (that only men muſt rule and not women when it pleaſeth God) there is no ſuch principle vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal in mens mindes. For you ſee that a number of countries, decree the contrary, wherefore it can not be ſaid, that it fighteth with nature: But you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply vpon me thus peraduenture: Nature hathe made her a ſubiect, Ergo, ſhe can not rule. I deny your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, for nature hath made the childe and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſubiects. And yet they may rule as Fabius ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne: and the Kinges ſeruaunt may be my maſter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for you muſt vnderſtand the argument thus, that if nature haue made her a ſubiect: in that ſtate ſhe is a ſubiect, and in reſpect of them to whome ſhe is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: ſhe can not be their ruler. As a thilde in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a childe towarde his father, is his fathers ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect And a ſeruaunt in reſpecte of his maſter and the duty of a ſeruaunt, can not be his maſters heade. But in reſpect of Ciuil pollicie, the ſonne bearing office,
<pb facs="tcp:466:25"/>may be in that functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fathers head, and the kings ſeruaunt an other mans maiſter,<note place="margin">Gen. 39.</note> as Ioſeph was in the houſe of Putiphar. So the woman being eyther as a childe to hir father, or a ſeruaunt to hir maiſter, or a wyfe to her huſband, reſpecting theſe perſones: can not be head ouer them in thoſe offices: that is in the office of a father, a maiſter, or a huſband. But in the office of a ruler and a magiſtrate ſhe may be this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wyfe, that is his ſubiect, and his head, that is his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. So that this argument by deſtinction is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for it is a Fallax, called ignoratio elenchi, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue it, and you ſhal ſee the faulte. VVho ſo euer is one mans ſubiect, can not be another mans ruler, or the ſame mans ruler in an other reſpect. But awyfe is hir huſbandes ſubiect: ergo ſhe can bee none other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>shead, nor his in an other reſpect. This is falſe, for the contradictorie is true: That a wyfe may be this mans wyfe, and that mans maiſtres, and this mans ſubiect in the dutie of matrimony, and the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s head in thauct horite of office. Thus we ſe that al rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons well ſet out, are lyke a wel kempt buſſ he wher neuer a here lyeth amyſſe, ſo longe as he hath a hous to couer him. But when he cummeth into the wynde it is ſone ruffled. Or lyke a paynted madams face, whiche ſo longe as no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bloweth vpon it nor ſweat ryſeth in it: is gay gliſtring, but any of theſe meanes make the wrinkles ſone to appere. So a falſe argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t decked with fayre wordes, ſemeth good: but turne it naked and you ſhall ſone ſee the botches.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde Argument is this that the ſcripture forbiddeth that a woman ſhould rule,<note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> and therfore it
<pb facs="tcp:466:26"/>is not tollerable, the prouſes be out of tholde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">Gen. 2. Eſai. 3.</note> Firſt that after the falſe of Adam through the womans intrcement it was enioyned hir, and hir po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterite as a penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to be at the beck and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2 That Eſai pronouceth as a curſe that the rulers for the peoples vnrulines ſhal be children and women.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 1. Tim. 2.</note> 3. that S. Paule forbiddeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeake in the congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Before that I anſwer particulerly I muſt ſaye this to them all in general, that the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture medleth with no ciuill pollicie further then to teach obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And therfor what ſo euer is brought out of the ſcripture co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning any kynd of regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is without the booke, pulled into the game place by the eares to wraſtle whether it will or no. For Chriſt faith:<note place="margin">Luc. 12.</note> Quis mo conſtituit inter vos iudicem. VVho hath made me be betwixt you a iudge, as though he ſhuld ſaye, myne office is not to determyne matters of pol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licie, of ſucceſſion, and enheritaunce, for that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the ciuill magiſtrates. If he had thought that it had bene within the compaſſe of his function: why and with what conſcience refuſed he to ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at one, whiche were at ſtryfe, and to put that out of doubte which was in ſute. If he ought to do it, and wold not: he lacked charite, and did not his dutie: if it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged not to him, how belonged it to any of his Apoſtles, diſciples, or ſucceſſors? Had not he as large co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he gaue? or could he gyue that he had not? But he knowing his office, as the prophet Eſaie had forſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of him to be, to preache the Goſpel, to heale the broken. &amp;c. would do nothing without warraunt, &amp; therfore being axed if he were a kyng: he aunſwered
<pb facs="tcp:466:26"/>ſimply by a playne negatiue. Regnum meum. &amp;c.<note place="margin">Math. 27. Marc 15. Ioh. 18.</note> my kingdom is not of this world. If his kingdom were not here: neither the ordring of pollicies was his, for remouing from his functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole: he muſt nedes remoue the part, pollicie is a part of a worldly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, yea when they woulde haue taken him vp to make him a kyng,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> as one that refuſed that belonged not to him, he conueyed himſelfe from among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peral iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged to him: why refuſed he his calling? If it did not, where had Paul, Peter, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, any authorite to medle with that he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? Seing he ſaid. Sicut miſit me viue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s pater,<note place="margin">Ioh. 22.</note> ita et ego mit to vos. He gaue them no more ſcope then he had him ſelfe: wherfore it is not like that Paul, or any other, would vſurpe a further authorite, then he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of his father, or they of him, and therfore Paul, ſheweth howe farre he wilbe folowed: Saying. Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores mei eſſote ſicut ego Chriſti: Followe me, and her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to me in thoſe thynges that I followe, and her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to my maiſter in, he teacheth in effect, this part of pollicie whiche he hadde learned of his Lorde. Date Caeſari quae ſunt Caeſaris,<note place="margin">Mar. 12. Math. 22.</note> obey the magiſtrates and thoſe that be in authorite, not only for feare, but for conſcience, he ly miteth no magiſtrates,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> he alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth no polycie, he medleth neither with Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Ariſtocraties, nor monarchies, nor pſcribeth whe ther old or yong, riche or poore, lerned or vnlerned, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhuld reigne. But as he findeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo he leueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, empaireth none, altereth none, diſturbeth none: knowing as Chriſt ſayd.<note place="margin">Math. 20. Luc. 23.</note> Principes gentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domina bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur eis, vos au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſic. It falleth not into a diſciples, an apoſtles,
<pb facs="tcp:466:27"/>or churche mans office, to meddle with ſuche mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: thei haue their princes, guides, and gouernours the churche men be no ſuche:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> For Nemo militans deo implicat ſe mundanis negotijs. It is inough for them to wayte vpon one office,<note place="margin">Prieſtes of fice is ouer the ſoule.</note> to attende as ſoule prieſtes, &amp; not erraunt bay lifes: Thus farre to the whole in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall nowe to eche reaſon in ſpecial where it is ſaid: Et ad virum erit conuerſio vel deſiderium tuum. I myght aunſwer it with the common interpretacion whiche is. Though both in conceauing and brynging forth thy child, thou ſhalt feele throwes and exceding pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues: yet ſhalt thou not be hable to withdrawe the from thy huſbande, but ſhalt gyue occaſion to haue more. The payne of the former ſhall not make the to auoy de the next. This is no euill interpretacion, for it aunſwereth in the maner of the payne, the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite of the offence. As who ſhould ſaye, thou haſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyced thy huſband to turne to thy folly: I ſhal ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make the to turne to him, to thine owne ſmarte. This place thus interpreted maketh no more for this matter then Gloria in exelſis doth proue that S. Peter ſay de maſſe: But by cauſe ſome reiect this interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and we ſeke not to cauil, but to fynd the truth: therfor I wil admyt the other, that it maketh for the wiues obedience toward hir huſbande, that ſhe muſt hange vpon him as vpon hir guide, followe his wyll as the wyſer, obey his commaundement as hir ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, and to be ſhort, to knowe him for hir head, and hir ſelfe for his ſubiect. VVhat? Graunt you this? that is inough. yea I muſt nedes do ſo for the truthe els, and myne owne conſcience, would reproue me.
<pb facs="tcp:466:27"/>How than anſwere you? forſothe as I did before that ſhe muſte do all this and more, but vſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ad aras. So far forthe as he comaundeth like a huſband, like a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and like her head. But if he paſſe his commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as if he commaunde that is vngodlye: then ſhe may anſwer him, as. S. Aug. doth the ruler. Da veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am imperator Tu minaris carcerem, ſed deus gehennam.<note place="margin">Aug. &amp; habetur. 11 q. 4. cap. ita corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris qui reſiſtit.</note> Thou wilt haue me obey thy will for fear of thy pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and ſword: but I muſt obey goddes will, for feare of his eternal fire and damnacion: if her huſband will commaund her in the publike weale, ſhe beinge the magiſtrate, and not he: ſhe may ſay to him as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul ſaid to Fabiꝰ. ſiſte lictor.<note place="margin">Limidec. 3</note> Law make my huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to obey, for heare he is not my hed, but my ſubiect, yea if he breake any lawe, if it were capitall, ſhe myghte ſtrike with the ſword,<note place="margin">A vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye rule as a magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and yet obey as a vvife.</note> and yet be a wife good inough for the dutye that ſhe oweth to him, is not omitted in that ſhe obſerueth, that ſhe oweth to the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale, wherein he is as a member conteyned. But if for her wedlocke dutie to him, ſhe will neglecte the common vvealth: Then is ſhe a louing wife to him, and an euel head to the countrey.<note place="margin">The, ii. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> The .ii. reaſon out of Eſay maketh as muche as for debarringe of yonge Princes rule, as Ioas, Ioſias and our ſwiet kinge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde (as his ſiſter Marye helde) as it dothe againſte women, for they be ioigned together, but in dede it maketh againſte neither.<note place="margin">Eſay the Hebrues Demoſth.</note> For Eſaye beinge worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye called the Demoſth: of the Hebrues, vſeth ſuche goodly figures of ſpeaking, as all the ſcripture hathe not beſide, as in this place, I will take from you your
<pb facs="tcp:466:28"/>honerable Senators, and your wiſe counſelers, and I will geue you boyes and women,<note place="margin">Eſaie.</note> or effeminate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to reigne ouer you, not boyes in age, but in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners (as Ariſtotle ſaithe of yonge men,<note place="margin">Eth. 1.</note> that to heare Philoſophie it maketh no matter for their yeares, but for their maners) not women in ſexe, but in feble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of wit, and not ſuche as ſome women be, wiſer, better learned, diſcreater, conſtanter, then a number of men: but ſuch as women be of the vvurſt ſort, fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, foliſh, wanton, flibbergibbes, tatlers, triflers, waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, witles, without counſell, feable, careles, raſhe, proude, deintie, niſe, tale bearers, eueſdroppers, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inor raiſers, euell tonged, worſe minded, and in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye wiſe, doltefied with the dregges of the Deuils dounge hill, as theſe minions be: ſuch ſhall your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natoures and rulers be, that ſhall be neither hable to rule them ſelfes nor you. No Deborahes, no Iudiths no Heſters, no Ely zabethes. For ſure wher ſuch be: ther is no token of Gods wrath, whiche the Prophet threatneth here: but of gods fauoure, wherof we may be aſſured. Therfor this argumente riſeth of wronge vnderſtandinge, as the Vicar of Trumpenton vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode Eli, Eli, lamah zabatani, when he red the Paſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon Palme Sonday, when he came to that place he ſtopped, and calleing the Churchwardens ſaide. Neighboures this geare muſte be amended, heare is Elitwiſe in the booke, I aſſure you if my L. of Elie come thys waye and ſee it, hee will haue the booke. Therefore by mine aduiſe we ſhall ſcrape it out, and put in oure owne townes name, Trumpington, Tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pington lamah zabactani, they conſented, and he did
<pb facs="tcp:466:28"/>ſo, becauſe he vnderſtode no grewe. So they that vſe this place for a weapon againſt this matter, thei fault in homonymia, not conſidering that words haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſignifications and tranſlations.</p>
            <p>The .iii. reaſon of this argument is oute of Saint Paule, wherby,<note place="margin">The .iii. reaſon.</note> women be forbidden to ſpeake in the congregacion, for it is an vnſemely thinge for them to ſpeake. This is meruelouſlye amplefied and vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as thoughe it were ſo ſounde as no faulte, nor cracke coulde be founde in it. This is the Hercules clubbe that beateth all downe before it. Theeſe bee Sampſons lockes, that make him ſo ſtronge, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there muſte be taken ſome paines in the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge of it: fytſte therefore, I laye this foundacy on whiche I laide before, that Saynt Paule, nor none of the reaſt of Chriſtes garde, meddle not with Cyuill pollycie, no further then to teach obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, nor haue no commiſſion thereunto in all the whole ſcripture. And this beinge a greate matter of pollicie, yea the greateſt (for it conteigneth the whole) it can not be within the compaſſe of Pauls commiſſion, and ſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth it, that Paul either in this place ment no ſuch matter as they gather: or if he did: he did it wythout the compaſſe of his commiſſion, but that is vnlike. For as he ſaide in one thinge, ſo ſurely did he in all. Quod accepi a domino id tradidi vobis Et unitatores hier e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtote ſicut ego Chriſti. VVell what then ment he.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 1. Cor. 4.</note> This he ment. That though he ordemed that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the aſſemblie eccleſiaſtical about the word of God a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d praier, ſhuld haue leaue, orderly a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in his courſe, to ſpeke a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vtter, for thinterpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſcripture, all that was
<pb facs="tcp:466:29"/>reueled him by the ſpirit of God, yet wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (becauſe they be not mete,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14</note> neither by nature nor ſtudy to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che and interprete ſcriptures) he woulde not haue to medle with it there.<note place="margin">Primaſ. in 1. Cor 14 Theoph.</note> And as Primaſius and Theophi: ſaith the chefeſt cauſe that moued Paule to take thys order, was the common faulte that then was in that ſexe. For being ſomwhat inſtructed, by the hearing of thapoſtles in the miſteri of ſaluacion, in the croſſe of Chriſt, they began to thinke ſomethinge of them ſelues, and turned that was taughte to edifye with, to a iangling and tatlinge in the church when thei met, ſo that the congregacion was thereby diſturbed. For the auoydinge whereof, Paule mente to bridle them: as withoute doubte, he wold haue done the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo, if they had prophecied vnorderly, or made it a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of diſcorde: as it hathe bene of late in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacions, where it hathe bene reuiued. And not only he debarred the women from propheſiyng: but alſo from anye publike function in the eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction.<note place="margin">VVhat is requyred in a pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit man.</note> For in ſuch as ſhall occupy the pulpit, is required theſe things, that they be mete to teach, to reproue, and conuince. In teaching is required gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitie, learning, and eloquence. In reprouinge cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and ſounde iudgemente, and in conuincynge Artes, memorye and muche ſcience. And becauſe the bringinge vppe of vvomenne, is commonlye ſuche, as they canne not haue theeſe thynges (for they bee not broughte vppe in learnynge in Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, nor trayned in diſputacions. Or if they were yet becauſe nature hathe made them ſofter and mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then menne. Yet bee they not ſuche as are
<pb facs="tcp:466:29"/>as are mete for that function.) Therfore be they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mete for this calling. For thoſe that be preachers, muſt be no mylke ſoppes,<note place="margin">Preachers muſt be nomilck ſoppes.</note> no white lyuered gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that for the frowning and cloudy countenaunce of euery man in authoritie, will leaue his tackle and crie Peccaui. They muſt be of ſuch nature, as the Poet ſaieth of Crito, in vultu grauitas, in verbis ſides.<note place="margin">Terent.</note> They may not be afrayed to rebuke the proudeſt, no not kynges and quenes ſo farfurth as the two tables rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth. As we ſee in Samuel, Nathan, Elie, Ihon Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, and many other. They may not ſtoupe to euery mans becke, and ſtudy to pleaſe man more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God. If hereſies ariſe, they muſt haue their tooles ready to mete with thaduerſary and to ouerthrowe hym: whiche he can not haue, onles he haue trauay led in many ſciences, harde and redde much, which thinges becauſe they be huſwyues) women can not haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, and therfore they be vnmete hereunto. Yea God knoweth ſo be many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to: for it is not inough for a man to tell a fayre tale in the pulpit, and when he commeth downe is not able to defende it. If prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and ſpirituall miniſters be ſuche: where be we when we come to handgripes, (They muſt not only floriſhe, but they muſt know their quarter ſtrookes, and the waye how to defende their head, their head Chriſte I ſaye, and his croſſe. And ſpecially in theſe dayes, wherin Sathan ſpiting the happy grouthe and grenes of Gods field, ſoweth tares and fytches of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and ſectes continually, to choke or to empayre the good corne if it may be. VVhat ennemies haue we of the Papiſtes? vnlearned thinke you? nay, who
<pb facs="tcp:466:30"/>ſo encountreth with them, had nede haue his harnes wel bucked to hym, or he may chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to take a wipe: I would they were aſwel mynded, as they be learned. VVhat ſaye you nowe to the Arrians? whiche ſuer, are lyke to enfect the beſt heads in Europe (I meane the Italyans) if God prouide not remedy. Shall it be eaſy thynke you for euery man to ioyne with them? I can not tell howe ſimple they be. But one man of that ſect ſo diſtourbed a whole vniuerſitie in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, that all the learned men there, and the Prince him ſelf,<note place="margin">Tubinga in Sueuia.</note> was not hable to ſcrape out that he had wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly grauen. The Swingfieldians, the Maioranes, the Pelagians, the froward freewyll men, the Adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſtes, the Oſdrianiſtes, thenewe Marcioniſtes, the Anabaptiſtes, with infinite other ſwarmes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſtes, do you thinke that euery pulpit man wyll be hable to aunſwer them. I pray God there be many that can. I ſaye therfore becauſe there is ſo muche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a ſpirituall miniſter: that all men bee not mete for the office. And therfore that with good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon women bee debarred from it. Albeit, at ſome tymes it pleaſeth God to vſe their miniſtrie euen in this poynt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note> as the woman of Samaria, whiche was the fyrſt preacher to hir cytezens of the Meſſias, and the women,<note place="margin">Math. 28. Marc. 16. Ioh. 20. Ruff. li. 10 cap. 10. Theo li. 1. cap. 23.</note> the fyrſt Apoſtles and meſſengers of the reſurrection. And as we reade in the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call hiſtorie, A certen woman vnder Conſt. Mag. was the Apoſtle of the Iberians, whiche turned firſt the Kynge and Quene, and then the whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to the fayth of Chriſte. This coulde not bee
<pb facs="tcp:466:30"/>done without ſome talke in thaſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies, nor without a kynde of preachyng. Yea, Theodoretus ſayeth, that ſhe dyd preache to them: wherfore me thinke euen in this poynte wee muſte vſe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a certen moderacion, not abſolutelie and in euerye wyſe to debarre them, herein (as it ſhall pleaſe GOD) to ſerue Chriſte. Are there not in Englande women thynke you, that for their learnynge and wyſdome, coulde tell their houſholde and neighbours, as good a tale as the beſt Sir Ihon there? And what if by occaſion, not by common office, they ſhoulde ſumtyme make their neighbours partakers of their giftes: were it ſo heinous a matter?<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> I pray you what more vehemencye vſeth Paule, in the forbiddynge of women to preache, then inforbydding them to vncouer their heads. He ſayeth of the one,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> it is euyll fauoured, and of the other: that it is againſt nature.<note place="margin">As vvome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ache, ſo be they to go bare hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> And yet you knowe that in the beſt reformed chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of all Germany: all the maides be bare headed, whiche the preachers and learned men, make noo greate accompte of. This I ſaye, not becauſe I allowe either (for I aſſure you I dooe not.) But that wee ſhould not in ſuche pointes, grate vpon the woordes to ſore, as though in no reſpecte a woman may ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir mouth to edifie. But if this be vtterly taken from them in this place: what maketh it againſt their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment in a politike weale, where neither the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man nor the man ruleth. If there be no tyraunts, but the lawes. For as Plato ſaith.<note place="margin">Plato de leg. lib.</note> Illi ciuitatiparatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt exitiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vbi magiſtratꝰ legibus inperat, et no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leges magiſtratui That cytie is at the pits brinke, wherin the magiſtrate ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:466:31"/>the lawes, and not the lawes, the magiſtrate: VVhat could any kyng in Iſraell do in that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, beſides the pollycie appoynted by Moyſes? They be but miniſters, obeyed for the lawes ſake, and not for their owne. Nowe what vnhablenes is in a woman for the miniſtring of lawes? She knoweth not the lawes, no more doth your kyng. She ſitteth not in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, howe oft doth your kyng? Onles you call de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining matters in his priuie chamber, iudging. She is not mete to go to the warres, ſhe hath that bee mete,<note place="margin">Tillius Arnoldus Iuſt. Herodot.</note> and ſome wemen haue gonne and ſped wel. She is not of ſo ſound iudgement, peraduenture beter, &amp; of more lerning then your kyng, as it happeneth at this tyme, that you can neuer ſhewe in al Englande ſynce the conqueſt, ſo learned a kyng, as we haue now a Quene. Men will not ſtande in aweſo muche of a woman as of a man: that is their faulte and not hirs. No more will they of a childe, and yet be they tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours that do diſobey him.<note place="margin">Solin. 43. cap.</note> Solinus writeth that the neighbours of Sambri haue a dogge to their kynge, and by his beckes and fawnings they geſſe what they muſt do. But thei were foles in obeying a brute beaſt, and you bee Traytours in not obeying a reaſonable creature.<note place="margin">It is leſſe daunger to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by a vvoman then any vvhere els</note> They are to obedient (a ſhrewed faulte) and you to diſobedient, that is no faulte. VVell a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not reigne in Englande. Better in England, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any where, as it ſhall wel appere to him that without affection; will conſider the kinde of regiment. whyle I conferre ours with other as it is in it ſelfe, and not may med by vſurpacion: I can fyndenone either ſo good or ſo indifferent. The regiment of Englande is
<pb facs="tcp:466:31"/>not a mere Monarchie, as ſome for lacke of conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion thinke, nor a meere Oligarchie, nor Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratie,<note place="margin">The kind of gouern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment in England. Amonar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie is vvher one alone rule An Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchie vvhere a fevv rule. A Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratie vvher the people rule. Architas de leg. &amp; iuſtit.</note> but a rule mixte of all theſe, wherein ech one of theſe haue or ſhoulde haue like authoritie. Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage whereof, and not the image, but the thinge in dede, is to be ſene in the parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hous, wherin you ſhal find theſe .3. eſtats. The King or Quene, which repreſenteth the Monarche. The noble men, which be the Ariſtocratie. And the Burgeſſes and Knights the Democratie. The verye ſame had Lacedemonia the nobleſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d beſt city gouerned that euer was, thei had their kings, their ſenate a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Hippagretes, which wer for the people. As in Lacedemonia none of theſe could make or breake lawes, order for warre or peax, or do any thing without thother, the king nothinge without the Senate and commons, nor either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or both withoute the kinge (Albeit the Senate and the Ephori had greater authoritie then the Kinge had) In like maner, if the parliament vſe their priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges: the King can ordein nothing without them. If he do. it is his fault in vſurping it, and their follye in permitting it: wherefore in my iudgement thoſe that in King Henry the .viii dais,<note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in Kinge Henry .8. daie.</note> would not graunt him, that his proclamacions ſhuld haue the force of a ſtatute, were good fathers of the countri, and wur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacion in defending their liberty. Vvold God that that court of late daies, had feared no more the fearcenes of a woman, then they did the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſuch a man. Then ſhould they not haue ſtou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped contrary to their othes and alledgiaunce to the crowne, againſte the preuilege of that houſe, vppon
<pb facs="tcp:466:32"/>their marye bones to receiue the Deuels bleſſinge,<note place="margin">The recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Popes abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Parliament.</note> brought vnto them by ſatans Apoſtle the Cardinal, God forgeue him for the doing, and them for obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But to what purpoſe is all this? To declare, that it is not in England ſo daungerous a matter, to haue a woman ruler, as men take it to be. For firſt it is not ſhe that ruleth but the lawes, the executors whereof be her iudges, appoynted bi her, her iuſtices of peace and ſuch other officers: but ſhe may erre in chuſing ſuch: ſo may a Kinge: and therfore they haue theyr counſel at their elbow, which by trauail abrod, know men howe fit or vnfit they be for ſuche offices. 2. ſhe maketh no ſtatutes or lawes, but the honerable court of Parliament: ſhe breaketh none, but it muſt be ſhe and they together or els not. 3. If ſhe ſhuld iudge in capitall crimes: what daunger were there in her wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manniſhe nature? none at all. For the veredict is the 12. mennes, whiche paſſe vppon life and deathe, and not hers: Onlye this belongeth to her myniſterie, that when they haue founde treaſon, murdre, or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie, ſhe vtter the paine limited in the lawe for that kind of treſpaſſe. Yea but this ſhe can not do becauſe a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not learned in the lawes, No more is your kinge, and therefore haue they their miniſters, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che can ſkill if they be cruell, wicked, handmakers, and bribers, it is their faulte, and not the Princes, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les he know them to be ſuch and winke at it. VVhat maye ſhe doe alone wherein is pearill? She maye graunte pardon to an offender, that is her preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, wherein if ſhe erre: it is a tollerable and pityfull error to ſaue life. She maye miſpende the reuenues
<pb facs="tcp:466:32"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>f the crowne wantonlye, ſo can kings do to,<note place="margin">VVhere mistreies be, vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment cannot be dangerus.</note> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlye do, and yet may they be kings: if on thother part, the regiment were ſuch, as all hanged vppon the Kinges or Quenes wil, and not vpon the lawes wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: if ſhe might decre and make lawes alone, without her ſenate. If ſhe iudged offences accordinge to her wiſdome, and not by limitation of ſtatutes and laws: if ſhe might diſpoſe alone of war and peace: if to be ſhort ſhe wer a mere monark, and not a mixte ruler, you might peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tute make me to feare the matter the more, and the les to defend the cauſe. But the ſtate being as it is or ought to be (if men wer wurth theyr eares) I can ſe no cauſe of feare, nor good reaſon why Saint Paule forbiddinge her to preache, ſhoulde be thoughte to forbidde her to rule, nether Saint Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt.<note place="margin">Amb. li. q vet &amp; no. teſt. &amp; he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tr. 33. q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Amb. Theoph. or Primaſſius writinge vppon that place gather anye ſuche thinge as you ſtrain out of it. I knowe verye well that Ambroſe ſaithe, they maye not teache, be witneſſes nor iudge, and Aug. in li. 2. gen: et hab. 23. q. s. Eſt ordo ſaith he. It is a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall order in men that the women ſhuld obey theyr huſbandes, and children their parents. Saint Hierom thought them vnmete to iudge alone by their diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Ergo, to beare rule and conſerre in pollitike matters with other. Nay it is a fallax adicto ſecundum quid ad ſimpliciter: for he forbiddeth them to iudge in a reſpect, neither hauinge rule by enheritaunce nor iudging and conferring with other, and you therfore gather that ſimplie they are forbidden Deborah iudged and that lawfully, which cam not to it by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce, but by extraordinarye callinge. Muche
<pb facs="tcp:466:33"/>more may ſhe that to Gods callinge hathe ioygned thordinarie meanes of enheritaunce, her commons conſent,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſvvere to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> and confirmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lawes. To Saynt Auſten and all the reſt, which wolde haue women in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of their huſbandes, is to be anſwered as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: that their meaning and ſpeaking was, of euery priuate woman in the bonds of mariage: And not of thoſe which God by birth hath called to the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of realmes. Neither is it to be thought that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thold fathers wold be ſo iniurious to any heirs female: as to take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fathers patrimony, or that wold that al other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s daughters ſhuld haue a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d enioy their right: and kings daughters ſhuld be put fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their righte. Either ſo ſeuer thinheritaunce from the dominion,<note place="margin">Vvomans inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce linked vvith the dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nu. 27.</note> that they maye haue thone withoute the other, (whiche wilbe harde for you to do) or els graunt them both as you oughte to do. The daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Silphad by the iudgement of God and not of man were enhabled to their enheritaunce: And ſhall we take vppon vs to iudge in our pollicie otherwiſe then God did in his? Againe, Saint Auguſtine, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, the Cannon law, and Ariſt: meddle not wyth thoſe rules and gouernmentes, whiche come by ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall diſcentes, coincydent and linked with the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaunce: but with ſuch as ſtand in election. VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is to be noted,<note place="margin">Thediuer ſities of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</note> that there be .iii. maner of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates. One choſen by lotte, as was the houſe of Saul. A nother by Suffrages and election, as in Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, Polonia, the fre Cities of Germany, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. And the thirde prouided of God by lineall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, as in Fraunce, England, and other Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.
<pb facs="tcp:466:33"/>if any were to be choſen by lotte, or ſuffrage: I would not in dede that any woman ſhould ſtand in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but men only: for I ſay with Ariſtotle, that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the male is by all ly kelihod meter to rule, then the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in many reſpectes. And vndoubtedly in the whole number of men, might be founde ſome one that ſhoulde in all reſpectes, paſſe the beſte among women in wiſdome, grauite, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, vnderſtanding, ſobrietie, temperauncie, hable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to take paines, warly kenes, iuſtice, fortitude. &amp;c. But when it ſtandeth in no mans election, but in his hande that ſhapeth male or female, in the wombe of the mother, at his pleaſure:<note place="margin">In Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d God hath al the voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in his ovvn ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> Then hath mans voyce no authoritie, by cauſe he hath gyuen ouer his right in chuſing, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon conſent vnto God. That he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his inſcrutable wyſdome, may chuſe and diſpoſe, as he pleaſeth. This being doone, ſhall man pull back his graunt, or call God to accompt and ſay, Nay when we agreed, the matter ſhould be referred to your iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: we ment not that you ſhould ſend vs a woman to rule ouer vs: or we had forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to put that in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions, and therfote you muſt geue vs leaue to reuoke our grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for we can prouide better then thus, our ſelfes. VVere not this a foly ſhe plea (thinke you) and a mad enterpriſe? wold he not ſone aunſwer vs. Oh you preſumptuous fooles,<note place="margin">Gods aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvver to mens ſoly</note> that haue ſuche opinion of your own wyt: who made empires and kyngdomes, dominions and rules? who preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and mainteineth them? whoſe be they? yours or myne? muſt you haue the orderyng or I? If they bee myne: why let you me not alone with them? If they
<pb facs="tcp:466:34"/>be yours: ſhewe your euidence howe you came by them:<note place="margin">Math. 20.</note> ſhall not I do with myne what I liſte? Is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eye ill becauſe I am good? Murmur ye at myne anoynted, becauſe ſhe is a woman? who made man and woman, you, or I? yf I made hir to lyue: may I not make hir to reigne? If I apoynt hir to the office? can I not adourne hir, and make hir hable to diſcharge it? VVhy then (you of litle faithe) eyther feare you my good wil: or miſtruſt you my power? you are muche worſe then Saule in this poynte, whome I reiectyd for diſobedience. For when I ſent my ſeruaunt Dauid,<note place="margin">1. Samu.</note> yonge of age, and no Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ante inſtature, with his ſhepe hoke and his ſlynge: Saule woulde haue armed hym wyth hys owne armoure? But when Dauid threwe it of and wente his waye naked againſt his enemy, a great hyghe monſtre, in compariſon of hym: Saule myſtruſted not as you do: murmured not as you doo, ſayinge, ah this poore boye is not hable to be our champion, and to defende our libertie: but he prayed for him, and wyſhed him well in the name of Iehouah the lorde of hoſtes. It is I tell you all one to me, to ſaue with many or few, with armour or without, by a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or by a man.<note place="margin">The maic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of god repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by a vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no les then by a man.</note> VVhat letteth, that ſhe may not as well repreſent my maieſtie, as any of you all? If I be beſt repreſented by the ſhining ornamentes of the mynde, and not the outwarde ſturdines of the body: why may not ſhe haue at my hande that any of you haue? wiſdom to gouerne, iuſtice to puniſh, cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie to pardon,<note place="margin">Dansel. 13. Num. 22.</note> diſcreſcion to iudge. I that coulde make Daniel a ſucking babe, to iudge better then the wiſeſt
<pb facs="tcp:466:34"/>of the lawyers: A brute beaſte to reprehende the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of a Prophet: and poore fiſſhers, to confound the great clarkes of the worlde: can not I make a woman to be a good ruler ouer you, and a mete miniſter for me? VVhat vnly kelihod ſe you in hir? are your eyes ſo dulle? or your myndes ſo malycious? that you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not or wyll not ſee thoſe Iewelles, wherwith I haue decked hir? is that rare learning, that ſingulare mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, that heauenly clemencie, that chriſtiane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, that loue of religion, that excellent wyſdom with many more of my graces, nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in your ſight? I ſhewed you the lyke towarde in a man of late: but for your owne vnworthines, I toke him from you: And wil you nowe, I haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you this: make your ſelues vnworthy to enioye hir? Leaue of, leaue of, your owne pollycie, which is but folly, and embrace my ordinaunce, as it is your dutie. For I pulle down whome I will, and ſet vp whome I wil. Though God ſpeaketh not thus to vs audibely: yet ſuer, he nedes muſt thus ſpeake in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience inwardly. VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs leaue of to diſpute, and beginne to praye,<note place="margin">Vve muſt praye for the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes eſtate and not diſpute of hir right.</note> that it maye pleaſe hym to ſtably ſhe hir ſeate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge vs, and to ſende hir longe lyfe and quiet reigne, to defende hir and vs from inuaſions abrode and conſpiracies at home, to geue hir grace to ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke his honour, and maynteine the truthe, to guide hir harte in the choiſe of hir huſbande, and to make hir frutefull, and the mother of manye chyldren, that thys Realme maye haue the graftes of ſo good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a tree, That oure chyldren and poſterite maye ſee hirs occupying hir throne, with honour, ioye, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:466:35"/>quietnes. The remembraunce of hir vertues carieth me awaye from my matter: wherfore I return. And becaus Ari. is thought to be of ſuch authorite in this matter,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſvver to Ariſto.</note> let vs a litle examine his woordes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is the male is moore mete to rule then the female, well, what inferre you? ergo the woman vnmete. I denie that argument, you ſhould rather ſaye the woman is not ſo mete, that we could graunt you, and not a whyt hurt our cauſe: for otherwyſe no man will reaſon, as to ſay this man is better learned then the other: ergo thother is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned. Chalke is whyter then cheeſe: ergo cheeſe is black. No man that knoweth what compariſon is, wyll bryng two contraries in one compariſon, as to ſaye pitche is blacker then ſnowe, or fyer is whotter then water. But if they compare two thynges toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they muſt be ſuche as they haue in one qualite or propertie maius et minus. As I ſaye right. A man is more mete to rule then a childe. That is not by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmacion and negacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as becauſe thone is apt, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thother is not, and euen ſo of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is more mete: therfore it foloweth not that ſhe is vtterly vnmete. And therfore Plato Ariſt. maſter not a whit wurſe learned then his ſcholer,<note place="margin">Plat. in Ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meo.</note> ſaith: Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus vtriuſque Sexus preficimus nuptijs, our maner is to make officers of both ſexes to ordre mariage. And ſaint Paule as we haue declared, gyueth them a kynd of gouernment <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to gouerne the houſe. And lykewyſe Ariſto,<note place="margin">Ariſt. in Eth. lib. 8. Cap. 10.</note> him ſelfe in the Ethikes. So that neither Philoſopher, nor Apoſtle, dealeth with them ſo hardly as you do. But Ariſt. 3. polit: ſaieth,
<pb facs="tcp:466:35"/>that cities be euil gouerned by women. Vvhat, by al or by ſome? if he ſaye by all, we can reproue him by many inſtances: if he ſaye by ſome: we can ſaye the ſame of men. So that you ſe: that theſe be no oracles which you bring in out of Ariſtotle, wherby (if you haue no better authoritie then this) you can not put them out of poſſeſſion. In this poynte I can not but think you much blame wurthy, not that maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as many do) you peruert the ſayinges of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: But for that negligently, you paſſe them ouer without waying and vnderſtandinge their ſayinges, without conferring and matching place with place, and ſaying with ſaying. For if in the citinge of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle you had ioigned the Ethikes with the Polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, I ſurely beleue, that you wold haue made him none of your iury in this matter.<note place="margin">Lib. 8. ca. 10. Vt ſupra.</note> For in the Ethikes handlinge the kindes of rule, what is a Monarchie, what an Ariſtocratie, and what a Democratie, ſaithe of the rule of the man and the wife thus: Viro cum vxore ius id intercedit, quod eſt in optimorum poteſtate. Nam pro dignitate ijs in rebus imperat, quae dignae ſunt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro. Quae autem feminam decent: eas ei tribuit. Qu od ſi in omnibus preſit vir ac dominetur: in paucorum poteſtatem fit mutatio, quoniam contra dignitatem facit, non qui eſt praeſtantior. Interdum etiam mulieres praeſunt cum amplu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patrimonium conſecutae ſunt. The rule and kind of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment betwixt the man and the wife ſaithe Ariſt:<note place="margin">A Senate vvher ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni rule to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</note> is like the gouernment of the chiefe, or of a Senate. For the man accordinge to his wurthines, ruleth in ſuch thinges as becommeth him, and the wife in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as is meete for her. If ſo be the man will rule and
<pb facs="tcp:466:36"/>beare the ſwaye in all: Then is the rule chaunged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Oligarchie, that is, where a fewe beare the ſtroke,<note place="margin">An Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchie is vvhere a ſevv beare the ſtroke</note> and herein he dothe otherwiſe then becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth him. Sometime women alſo hauing great and large patrimony beare the ſway. In the which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des I noote firſt, that the Philoſopher leaueth a kind of rule to the woman, whiche is hers ſo muche by nature, as the huſbande pullinge it from her, entreth into a kinde of tirannie and violateth the moſte na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and beſt ordre. As thoſe do which turne an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocratie to an Oligarchie that is the better into the worſe. Secondly if I woulde grate vpon the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and take the aduauntage of the compariſon: I mighte neare gather an equall authoritie betwixte the wife and the huſbande. For euery man knoweth that in the rule of the chefe, whiche is called Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratie (whereunro he likeneth that in Mariage) there is equalitie and none vſurpeth vpon an other. But I will not ſo followe the aduauntage of mine argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente: that I will confounde goddes apoyntmente. Thirdlye it appeareth plaine by this place of Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: that in his time it was a common order that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men enheritoures, ſhoulde rule their landes, houſes, and poſſeſſions (VVhiche is oure caſe) and yet not be thoughte to do againe nature in ſo doinge: Theſe things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, you muſt nedes not only be thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to deale to ſtraightly with this ſexe by plucking from them all, when your Philoſopher geueth them ſome, but alſo to be much ouerſene in ouerſeing and peruſing your authors. But leaſte Ariſtotle ſhoulde kepe vs to long from matter of more weight and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,
<pb facs="tcp:466:36"/>I wil return again from the Philoſopher to the Apoſtle. If you reaſon in this place of S. Paule.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> permitto mulieri loqui. I ſuffer not a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeke in the congregacion. Ergo, not to rule, thinking that it is formall, a minore ad maius from the leſſe to the more: your logike a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diuinitie both do fail you. For it is not to be taken thus, Paul forbiddeth her the les for her vnaptnes, Ergo, he debarreth her of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But in dede it is contrary wiſe, he forbiddeth her the greater and more chargeable function whiche is the ſpirituall miniſterie and preaching: therefore it followeth not that he ſhutteth her from the les, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is extern pollicy. No man I think doubteth but that the Eccleſiaſticall function is greater and more chargeable then the other,<note place="margin">The chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che mans office of more char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the temporall rulers.</note> for thone concerneth the bodye, and the other the ſoule. The one reacheth no further then outwarde actes, but the other pearceth to the harte and thoughtes That binedeth in earthe the bodye, thys fettereth boothe in heauen and in earthe, the ſoule: The one as Sainte Auguſt: ſaithe, threatneth priſones, the other eternall damnacy on.<note place="margin">Aug. &amp; he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tr. n.q. ca. ita corp.</note> The one maye be executed by deputies: the other muſte execute him ſelfe de manu tua. &amp;c. To the one is required iuſtice and no great learning: thother can not be without great lerning and knowledge.<note place="margin">Ezech. 3. &amp;. 33.</note> Thone treteth of the world, thother of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thone of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges temporall, thother of thinges eternall, and to be ſhorte, the one belongeth to this life, and the other to lyfe euerlaſtinge. VVherefore what wyll ſerue the one: wyll not ſerue the other. For they bee not
<pb facs="tcp:466:37"/>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> A good churchman mighte be a good ruler as Samuel was: but euery good ruler ran not be a good churchman. Thus we ſee that Sainte Paule thruſtinge that Sexe from the greater function and office: dothe not alſo diſable it to execute the other which is leſſe. But you wil ſay in England ſhe muſte haue both. How can ſhe diſcharge both, if you make thone ſo hard? I anſwer that in dede both belonge to her but not in one maner. For in thone (as pollicye) ſhe hath a function,<note place="margin">Hovv the Quene may ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the churche, and yet be no prieſt. Exod. 32.</note> that is ſhe muſt be a doer: in the other ſhe hath thauthority and ouerſight but not the function and practiſe as we ſe in the common welth of the Iewes. Firſt betwixt Aaron and Moiſes. Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes comptrolled Aaron, but yet he executed not Ara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons office, he offred no incenſe nor ſacrifice ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely, he medled not with tharke, nor any ſuch thing as belonged to the prieſthode, he ware not the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he miniſtred not the ſacraments, and yet had he authoritie to redreſſe his faults, as it appeareth in the matter about the calf,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.</note> and by the commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he receiued at Gods hand Tu eris illi in deum &amp; il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le erit os tuum. Thou ſhalt be his God and he thy ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che man. VVell but Moiſes aucthority (ſaye ſome) was not ouer the prieſts, becauſe he was a prince, but in that he was a prieſt, and ſo was it lawful for him to meddle with church matters, becauſe he was a chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che man. This hold they, that wold haue prieſtes to be kinges: and not kinges ouerſcers of prieſtes. Ther grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to proue him a prieſt: be theſe. Firſt that the pſalme calleth him ſo.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 98.</note> Moiſes &amp; Aaron inter ſacerdotes eius. &amp;c. Moiſes and Aaron amonge his prieſtes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarely,
<pb facs="tcp:466:37"/>that ſaint Auguſt. vpon the ſame pſalme ſaith ſo. And .3. that to the Hebrewes, and in Exodus he is ſaid to ſprinkle bloud vpon the aultar. Laſt of al, that a prince can not geue to an other, that he hath not him ſelfe: and therfore if he be not a prieſt he can not electe, nominate, ordeine, or correcte prieſtes. To theſe I aunſwere ſhortly, and firſt to the firſt. In the Pſalme howe ſo euer the old interpreters gaue it, we rede in the Hebrewe Cohanim, whiche is a worde indifferent to the chief prieſtes, or thechief princes, wherfore ſuche as doo beſt vnderſtande that tongue, geue it thus. Moiſes &amp; Aaron inter miniſtros eius. Moiſes and Aaron among his miniſters, and to proue that it may be ſo, the ſcripture calleth Dauid his ſonnes Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanim. miniſters. For no man is ſo fond to ſaie,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 8.</note> that a kinges ſonnes were prieſtes. Yea the beſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Hebrewes interpreting this woorde, giue it in Chorei ſheino. Moiſes &amp; Aaron inter eos qui inuocant nomen eius. Moiſes and Aaron among thoſe, that called vpon his name. Thus we ſee that this place truly vnderſtande maketh no whyt to proue Moiſes prieſthod. To the expoſition of S. Aug. whoſe wordes be theſe. Aperte enim in illis literis Aaron nominatur ſacerdos: de Moiſe non ibi dicitur quod ſacerdoserat, ſed ſi hoc non erat quid erat? Nunquid ſacerdote maior eſſe poterat? Exproprat Pſalmus quia et ipſe ſacerdos erat. Moiſes et Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. In that place Aaron is plainly called a prieſt: but of Moiſes it is not ſaid that he was a prieſt. If he were not that, what was he than? Could he be greater then a prieſt. The Pſalme doth vtter it that he was a prieſt. To this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, I ſaye myne anſwere, is that ſaint Auguſt.
<pb facs="tcp:466:38"/>Not vnderſtanding the Hebrewe, was eaſely decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and being wrapped in theſe two places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, wherin there ſemed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leaueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at a iarre as he found the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the one to ſay he was: and the other he was not: whiche maner of interpretacion, &amp; reconciliation of ſcriptures, howe it is to be lyked: I leaue to the learned reader to iudge.<note place="margin">24. Exod. Heb. 9.</note> 3. That whiche Moiſes is reported in Exodus, and the Hebrewes to haue done as a prieſt, it hurteth vs nothing. For he might do ſometimes that extraordinarely, which be longed to the prieſt, as we read that kinges readde the boke of the law, and yet were no prieſtes. Yea, al the children of Iſrael, at their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming out of Egipt, dyd as much as this came to, for euery one ſpri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kled bloud vpon theit dore poſtes in the paſſeouer, and yet they could not all be priſtes. And this ſprincling of bloud vpon the aultar, was but a ſolempne ceremony, for the time done, and not ſuche a function, as than was proprely appointed to the prieſtes. But to put the matter out of doubt. If Moiſes were a prieſte, than were there two highe prieſtes at ones, whiche coulde not be, by the lawe, and alſo Moiſes muſt nedes be in feriour to Aaron, becauſe Aaron, and not he: is there called the highe prieſt. Thus we ſe how lightly, light argumentes may be aunſwered, and I would wyſhe, that as eaſely, obſtinate men could be ſatiſfied. The laſt is of as litle force as the reſt, and therfor I ſay to it ſhortly, that it is grounded vpon a falſe principle, or maxima, whiche is that none can giue to another that it hath not it ſelfe. VVe ſee that as the phiſicions ſay, the braine being the origine of the ſenewes: giueth to
<pb facs="tcp:466:38"/>the whole body, ſenſum &amp; motu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſenſe and mouing, and yet by their opinion lacketh it ſelfe. Againe, the earth giueth to all frutes, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> whiche Ariſt. ſaith: is ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s motus, that is, that they ſhould growe and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue to a greater quantitie, and yet the earthe it ſelfe, neither moueth toward bygnes nor increaceth one way nor other. And if a prince may geue to a lawyer, authoritie to plead lawe, though he can not pleade him ſelfe and preſcribe a Tanner how he ſhall tanne, though he tanne not him ſelf, being neither a lawyer nor a tanner, why may he not I pray you in lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, conſtitute, apoint, correct, and ouerſe the church men, though he be no churche man him ſelf. But the meaning of theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is to driue pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouerſeing them, that they might in the meane time liue out of ſubiection. And now the name being odious, becauſe theire diſſolute lyfe, hath purchaſed them an euell name, they thinke (when no ſhifte els will ſerue) that princes will not medle with the authoritie, les they ſhould be combred with the prieſtes infamie. VVhat the Princes authorite was ouer the byſſhoppes and prieſtes aperith in the .2. of the kinges,<note place="margin">2. Re. ca. 12</note> where Ioas checketh the byſſhop and prieſtes for not beſtowing the offeringes vpon the reparation of the the temple, and enioyneth them to do it. If the prince hadd not this authorite ouer his biſſhoppes and prieſtes, why ſhould S. Paul haue ſaid omnis anima. Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher power:<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> he ſaith not al te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral ſoules, or al ſaue prieſts: This authorite kept the pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; emperours after chriſts time, vntil the beaſt of Rome made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſts: as apearith by Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus
<pb facs="tcp:466:39"/>Magnus, who was the moderator of the great counſell of Nece. And by Iuſtiniane whiche writeth to Peter the maiſter of his chappel matters,<note place="margin">Neceph. lib 8. Tripart. hiſt. cap. 5</note> where he ſaieth Iuuemus, we commaunde that all Byſſhops and Prieſtes do not from henceforth whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper thir Seruice, but ſo pronounce it with an audible voyce, that the people may heare &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c.<note place="margin">In nouell conſti 123.</note> This Emperour, euen in matters of the churche, toke vpon him thauthoritie to appoint them an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in their Seruice, howe dare then our proude pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates (very fooles in deede to them that were then) wraſtle with the Prince in this matter? But to oure matter we ſee by theſe examples, that the Princes hadde authorite in ſpiritualties to ouerſee them and order them: but meddled not with the function in executing, for that belonged only to the Prieſtes: Lo, I truſte you nowe perceaue, howe the functions doo differ. But thautorite ouer both may lawfully be in one. And that maketh not the Prince beynge a woman, vtterlye vnmete to gouerne, becauſe ſhe hath in ſomme repect to doo in bothe. This I haue ſayde by the waye leſt our aduerſaries the Papiſtes, ſhould ſnatche this at my hande whyle I thus ſeuer thoffices that I meane (as they doo) to pull from the Prince the ouerſight and gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the churche. I may not tary longer in that matter at this tyme. A tyme ſhall come peraduenture when it ſhall be more largly handeled. In the meane tyme, I retourne to my purpoſed argument: Furthermore where it is ſayde thou ſhalt chuſe a Kynge amonge thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and not among thy ſyſters.<note place="margin">Deut. 17.</note> And thereuppon
<pb facs="tcp:466:39"/>is inferred, that we may haue no Quene. It is the like reaſon as if a man ſhuld ſay.<note place="margin">Mar. 2.</note> Chriſt ſaid Veni ad vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum peccatores ad penitentiam, that is I am come to cal men ſinners, and not women ſinners. Therfor, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no ſinners: or if they be, they ſhal not bee ſaued: or as one reſoned examinet ſe ipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> homo, let a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> examin him ſelf: and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate, ergo,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not. And Chriſt ſhal at the latter day ſaye, Venite benedicte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not Benedicte. Therfore the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal not com in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or nearer to this our purpoſe,<note place="margin">Math. 18 Luk. 18</note> ſi peccauerit in te frater tuus. If thi brother offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo oft. forgeue him: hereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I gather, that I nede not to forgeue mi ſiſter. In al to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hath a ſinguler good grace, and ſpeciallye in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue tonge wher Ach which ſignifieth a brother do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the not only comprehend alſo a ſiſter but a nephewe to.<note place="margin">Ach. ſignifieth, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſiſter and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phevv.</note> And through out the whole ſcripture the maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line comprehendeth the feminin, or els ſure we muſt ſay with the phrenitik poſtellus: that women be not yet redemed, but men and that they muſt haue a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to dye for them, aſwell as men hadde Chriſte.<note place="margin">Poſtellus phrenſy.</note> That place of Scripture, which commaundeth a bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to be a king emong the Iewes, had no relacion to a ſiſter, as theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make it, but to ſtraungers. For it followeth non conſtituus regem alterius gentis. Thou ſhalt not make the a kinge of a ſtraunge nation. For the people of God, hauing no neighbours that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the true God as thei did: could not haue cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen any ſtraunger to be their kinge, but they ſhoulde haue bene in daunger of ſwaruing from God, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to Idolatrie. And therfore was it neceſſary, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:466:40"/>great coate to Englande, no more than you wolde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the Engliſh law, which is the litle cote to Rome our lawe muſte direct vs, becauſe it beſt agreeth with our country, we haue no further to do with the ciuil law then in arch matters, that is for teſtaments, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages and ſuch other, as for landes, and enheritance, pains for offences and many other poynts touching the law: ours doth meruelouſly iarre with the ciuill law, as we ſhall in ſome poyntes declare. VVherfore to burden vs with the ciuil lawe? is aſmuch as if you ſhoulde perſwade the Scottes to vſe the Garamantes law, to kil men at .50. and women at .40. becauſe the countrey being ſomwhat barren, can not wel noriſh ſuch, as by their age can do no greate good. But that you may ſee, that the ciuill lawe, and oures, agreeth like harpe and harrowe: we wil confer them in a fewe poyntes. And becauſe this matter wherof we treate, concerneth enheritaunce: we wil firſt ſpeake of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. In England the Eldeſt ſonne inheriteth, the ſathers landes only, ſauing in Gauel kind. And in mi opinion it is good pollicie, for the continuaunce of houſes. For nothing ſoner deſtroieth greate houſes, then the deuiſion of then heritance, as it appeareth in Germany,<note place="margin">The deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heritance, deſtroyeth noble hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes.</note> and wil more hereafter to our poſterity, when the yong brothern ſhall not be made abbottes biſhops, and cardinals as they haue hitherto bene. In the Ciuil law, the children ſuccede indifferentlye in their fathers patrimony, in fendis the ſonnes, and in other both ſonnes and daughters l. max. vit. ff. ſancimus C. de lib. praet. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Autent. de hered. ab inteſt in princ. et in. ff. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. et ff. cum filius. Iuſt. de hered. VVhere you ſee not
<pb facs="tcp:466:40"/>only our lawe farre to diſagree with this: But alſo that the ciuil lawe graunteth enheritaunce to the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males, whiche, you would plucke away. The cyuill lawe, geueth the father power ouer his childe in lyſe and death, ſpecially, that whiche is called Ius vetus, as it aperith Le. 2. C. de par. qui fil dict et le. in ſuis Edelib. et poſth. C. de pat: ptate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But in England if any father ſhould kill his ſonne: he ſhould be try ſed vp for his labor. The cyuill lawe maketh the children of tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Infames, but committeth them not to perpetual priſon, as they do in Englande. In the cyuil lawe, the king, or lorde of the ſoile,<note place="margin">Tit de leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute. ff &amp; lo. &amp; Ti. Iuſt. de le. app. tut.</note> hath nothinge to do with wardes or tutorſhippes, but the next of kynne, if the father in his lyfe tyme apoynte none: but in our law, the kyng hath the wardeſhip of all that holde of him in capite or knightes ſeruice. And as it was graunted to the crowne, vpon a neceſſary reſpect: So muſt it not be pulled away,<note place="margin">VVarde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips are not raſhly to be pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the prince</note> ſo longe as the ſame cauſe remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. It was geuen him at the firſt, in conſideration of the great charges in warre, and the ſmale reuenues that belonged to the crowne. And though ſuche or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſeme hard, thorough thabuſing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by ſome gredy guttes: Yet the realme, hauing alwaies, almoſt contynuall warres, with the Frenche, or Scottes, or both: who ſo euer goeth about to pul from the crown ſuche helpes: vnwittingly, maketh a breache for the enemy to inuade vs. VVherfore I would wiſhe, that ſuche as out of gods boke will comptroll the kinges exchequer, ſhould well vnderſtand the matter, befor he brought it into the pulpit. In the ciuill lawe,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt. Iuſt. l. fin. C. qu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d tut. velcur eſſe deſinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> the tutorſhippe endith in the males at .14. yeares of age,
<pb facs="tcp:466:41"/>and in the females, at. 12. But our lawe kepeth him in nonage vntill. 21. yeres. The cyuil lawe by ndeth not him to marry, by the force of his wardſhip, where his Tutor wyll:<note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nec ſil. Cde nup. I ſiſil. fami<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le ſi puel tut l. in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> uict. C de nup.</note> C. de nup. Marriage muſt be free and in his own choiſe, and may not be compelled by his father, muche leſſe by this tutor. But in England, he tutor hath his mariage, or maketh him to paye tor his libertie, how that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, and how in different it is, let the lawyers anſwer. I medle no ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her, but to ſhe we that it is ſo. The cyuill lawe ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoreth lyfe: that it graunteth a traitour his aduocate to defend his innocencie,<note place="margin">L. ſeruu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ff publ. vi caſtr. nu. 5 Bart.</note> but in our lawe he can haue none to ſpeake for him, but him ſelf. For the fault is cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted (and that iuſtly) ſo heynous, that it taketh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, all maner of helpe, to put other in feare. Againe, the cyuill lawe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempneth no man, onles he either confeſſe the faulte, or be openly conuicte by witnes ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But our lawe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteth it to the veredict of 12. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, indwellers in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, wher the treſpas is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted,<note place="margin">The triall of capitall crimes by 12. men.</note> who pronounceth giltie if they thinke ſo, whether he confeſſeth it or no, and oft tymes rather vpon their own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, then ani great witnes or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. This order as it was in it ſelf at the firſt without corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: was maruelous concionable and godly, and in my iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t much better then the cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil order. For they to wring out the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of the fault co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, are driuen to vſe tormentes, and to puny ſhe before they haue tried the faulte, wherein they are ofte ty mes deceaued, by rackynge thoſe whiche haue not offended, and dryuinge them for paynes of tormentes to ſaye that they neuer did, as I haue harde, happened at Tubinga, in the wirtenberg
<pb facs="tcp:466:41"/>lande,<note place="margin">Againſt racking.</note> that a man was broken vpon the whele for murdring an other, which after was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a liue, the ſmarts of the tormentes made him to confeſſe it, and lye of him ſelf. In monument wherof his image ſtandeth yet in a glaſſe wyndowe of the churche, euen as he was vpon the whele. Agayne there was in Englande, an Italian, not longe agoo, who (as they ſaye) paſſed thorowe all the tormentes in Venice, and eſcaped without confeſſing the faulte, whiche in deede he hadde committed. On the other ſyde our.<note place="margin">The queſt mongers.</note> 12. men the queſtmongers, being indwellers in the countrey, and men of ſkyll, ſhall learne by the circumſtannces, as by the life of the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fame of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or their own ſearch in the matter: whether he be ſuche a one or no, and ſo without racking, wreſting, and tormenting, the deede maye be founde. But in deede at theſe dayes it is growen to great corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that thorow one ſpeciall meanes, or two which be theſe. If there be any noble man dwellinge in the countrey either a Duke, a Marques, an Earle, or Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron:<note place="margin">The iuries and queſts corrupted</note> He ſhall lyghtlye haue in his retynewe all the cobbes in the countrey, whiche be the queſtmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, and if any matter be touchinge him, his man, or his frende, whether it bee a cryme capitall, or Niſi prius, ſent downe for landes: the caſe ſhal wey as he wil.<note place="margin">The fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teinours to great men</note> For his deteynors muſt nedes haue an eye to my lorde, though they ſhould go to the deuill for it: and ſo be ſome innocentes knyt vp, and ſome offenders dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, ſome titles of inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce loſt, agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt al iuſtice and right. Another is, if my lord wyll not offend the Statute of retynewe: then muſt the hyghe Shrife be
<pb facs="tcp:466:42"/>his frende: And the vnder thefe (vnderſhriſe I ſhould ſaye) his man. He empaneleth the queſt either ſuche as dare not diſpleaſe my lorde, or for good will, will not. And ſo that way betwixt the highe theſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertheſe, my L. and the curſtmongers,<note place="margin">The cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the Sherifs</note> poore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are out weyed. This corruption if it be not loked to: wil not make this order (whiche was the beſt that could be) to be the wickedſt that can be. But as I ſayde, in it ſelfe (me thinke) it hath much more iuſtice, equytie, and indifferencie, then the cyuill or rather cruel rack hath. If I ſhould peruſe and compare all poyntes wherein ours differ from the cyuill: and ſhewe that for our countrey it is muche meeter, I ſhould neuer make an ende. VVherfore theſe ſhalbe ſufficient, to ſhewe that you muſt brynge our owne weyghtes, to weye our matters by, and not ſtraungers, or els we muſt take you for an euell Clarke of the markett. Therfore if you will iudge well of our municipall matters: you muſte let vs alone with our own coate, and geue the great boye his. Nowe I paſſe to certen inconueniences whiche are thought to come of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens rule.<note place="margin">The inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovve vvo mens rule. The firſt.</note> Many inconueniences do commonly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the rule of women and their enheritinge of kyngdomes, as the loſſe of holdes, and auncient poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions as experience teacheth of late daies, by the departing from Hams, Guiſnes, and Calyce, with all that we hadde in Fraunce, beſides the daungeringe of the realme to be gouerned by ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, which thing of late was muche feared, and not vnlyke to happen. For the firſt, it is to trewe: that in that woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s reigne Englande was put to a ſore plunge through hir wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes:
<pb facs="tcp:466:42"/>which wold moue warre, when ſhe might haue bene at peax, vpon no iuſt cauſe, but becauſe (as you wold haue her) ſhe wold ſhew her a louing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and an obediente wife, rather then a catefull go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes. That follye was accidente to her perſon,<note place="margin">England hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loſſe by mens rule then by vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens.</note> and not proper to her ſexe. But admit it to be throughe the fault of a woman: haue we not had as greate, and greater by men? who loſte olde Brytaine to Iulius and the Romaines? men. Vvho loſte it againe to the Saxons? men. Of whom wone it VVilliam conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour? of men: who loſt it to the Danes? me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who loſt Normandie, Brytanie, Gaſcoigne, and Guine, and al our right in Fraunce? men, who loſt Bulloigne, Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenois and all the reſt? a man. VVho killed the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh King, when Henry. 8. was in Fraunce? a woman or at the leaſt her army? who brought in the light of gods worde into Englande? a woman, who lighteth now again the candle after it was put oute? a woman, whereby it is euident that we haue, not yet ſo muche cauſe to complaine of loſſe by them, as by men. And in oure hiſtories whiche we haue before cited: wee maye ſee manye common welthes by women enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, or at the leaſte well preſerued, but fewe ey ther muche weakened, or vtterlye deſtroyed. Onles you tell me of the deſtruction of Troye, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge, was rather thorowe the follie of Paris, then anye rule of Helena, and as for thys loſſe we haue nowe, I doubte not, but as the olde fathers are wonte to ſaye, that as by a woman came death: ſo by a woman was broughte fourthe life. In like manner
<pb facs="tcp:466:43"/>as bi a womans (whether negligence, or miſfortune, I wote not we haue taken this wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (ſo bi anothers diligence and felicitie, we ſhal haue it againe healed. If euerye man coulde perſwade him ſelfe of as good ſucceſſe by her as I do my ſelfe: I doubte not but the Frenche, and the Scottes bothe, ſhoulde haue theyr handes full, I praye God oure vnthanckfulnes make vs not to fare the worſe.<note place="margin">The .2. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> The next and greateſt inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience and daunger to be feared is, that if a woman inherit: the realm by mariage ſhall be tranſſerred to ſtraungers. A greate matter I confeſſe if it ſo bee, yet GOD maye do with his owne what he liſte. Scitote (ſaith the Prophet) quia deus eſt dominator in regno ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, et ipſius regnum eſt, &amp; cuicun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vult dabit illud: if he will tranſlate it,<note place="margin">Eccleſi. 10.</note> who can let it? Yea in another King Henries daies. And ſome tranſlation and ioig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of realmes maye turne to muche good, and the wealth and tranquilitie of many. As if we had had a Kinge for your Quene, or you a King for oures, it had bene a goodly tranſlacion: to haue vnited bothe realmes in dominion, regiment and law, as thei be in nature, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maners. I ſuppoſe a great dele bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter for your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it is now, thus to be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, yea ſubiected and ſlaued to the proudeſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trueſt and the mooſte tirannicall nacion,<note place="margin">The heny yokes of the french</note> vnder the ſonne. I except not the Spaniardes, whoſe dominion the Italians in Millane, Naples, Scicilie, and elſſe where: can muche better brouke and abide, then the light and inconſtant French,<note place="margin">Caeſar. in comment.</note> as Ceſar calleth them. If you and we had ioigned together: it had made no
<pb facs="tcp:466:43"/>great matter, on which ſide the kinge had bene, ſo he had bene religious. I graunte if all thinges anſwer, it is better ioignynge at home, then chuſing abrode. As if he be no verye baſe or meane perſon, if he loue and feare God, if he be of the ſame religion,<note place="margin">The orna mentes of an honie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borie ma.</note> indued with good and commendable qualities of wiſdome, Iuſtice, Manhode, Temperaunce, giftes of languages knowledge of Countries, pitifull, mercifull, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunte, ſobre, no hearer of flatterers, continent, not prodigal, but liberal, no extorcioner, &amp;c. Such a one if God ſhoulde lot any Quene, were to be preſerred, to any abrode. Onles all theſe, myght be found in a ſtraunger, and therto iouned nobilitie and auncient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of lynage, and the nation beyng ſuch, as vſe not to rule cruelly, but rather fatherly, then lordly. For by ſuche a one coulde come no great harme, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye muche good. As for example, if your Quene, ſhoulde haue founde oute ſome Germaine, or ſome ſuche other, whoſe Gouernmente is not rygorous (as in deede theirs is not) theyr hartes not amby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, the ſame Religion, good bryngynge vppe, a manne of actiuitie, whoſe auncetoures haue bene religious, lyncked wyth manye Prynces, eyther by Conſanguinitie, Affinitie, or ſure Societie, and league, of whome there coulde be no doubte of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueying the treaſure to any other nacion, or bringing in of hys owne countrye men to oppreſſe the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes (as vndoubtedly the Spanyardes and Frenche woulde). Suche a one I ſaye, if God appoynted: I ſee not why the name of a ſtraunger, ſhuld be odiouſe, it
<pb facs="tcp:466:44"/>is religion and likenes of maners, that ioigne men together,<note place="margin">Such as be of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me faithe be no ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers.</note> or at the leaſt ſhoulde ſo couple them: that agreing therin, we ſhuld not much ſtick in the reſt, In the kingdom of heauen, is nother Iew nor gentile man nor woman. A ſtranger if he be a goodman, is as deare in the fight of God, as he that is born in the middeſt of Edenbrough. This I ſpeake, not becauſe I ſhute at any one, for that were not onlye malapart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but madneſſe. But to anſwer mi obiection, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is, that tealmes be vndone by the matchinge of Quenes with ſtraungers.<note place="margin">Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſterus in Tab.</note> Scicilia, as the hiſtories re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, was quietly and happely gouerned, ſo longe as the Duke of Sueuia marrying the heir, had it in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et poſſeſſion. But after a Pope of Rome, as the duke paſſed thorowe Italie, to ſet order in Scicilie, had bi conſpiracy murdred him, it fel euery daye more and more to decay. So that it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not ſo much in the chuſing of a ſtraunger, as what he is that you chuſe. He is one of our brethren, if he be a faithfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, it is maners, faith, and behauior, and not nacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that make men ſtrangers one to an other. A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his own country, at home, if he be not of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith: is a ſtraunger. And contrary wiſe, wher there is one faith, one baptiſine, and one Chriſt: ther is narrower fraternite then, if they came out of one wombe: But to conclude, we muſt commit all this to God,<note place="margin">Subiectes mai vviſh but not vvringe Quenes to mariage.</note> who hath the hartes of rulers in his handes, as the flouds of waters, and wil ſo diſpoſe them as ſhal be moſt to their peax, to the realmes good, and hys honor, let vs not meddle with bridelinge of Quenes in mariage this way or that wai, we are none of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:466:44"/>to whome it ſhalbe ſaide, who ſhal geue this woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now thus thou ſeeſt good reader, that al this wynde ſhaketh no corne, that this bolde bluſtering blaſte, though it puffeth, and bloweth neuer ſo muche: Yet can it not moue, or ones ſtirre the ſuer grouded rock of verite. And though it be the propertie of Northre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blaſtes to coole and freeſe: yet in the hartes of good chriſtians, faithfull ſubiectes, and true Engly ſhmen, well warmed with natuall loue, and defended with the walles of wyſdome, obedience, and dutie: it can do nothing. It may peraduenture make a ſewe weake redes to wagge, whiche wil ſtyrre at euery litle puffe of wynde: But the ſtronge and harde Ookes ſure ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in loialtie, and growen to a iuſt perfection in the diſcipline of dutie: will neuer ſtirre a leafe for it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that this blaſte is ſent out of Aeolus at the requeſt of dame diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to hindre good Aeneas, ſay ling to the porte and hauen of quietnes and loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Though thou warte not diſpoſed of thy ſelfe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for opinion of thauthor, or for the noueltie of the matter, to ſtande to thy tackle againſt this ſtorm: yet I doubt not, but now by me rather put in mynde of that thou knoweſt, then taught that thou wart ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in: thou wilt ſone conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne this gale of wynd,<note place="margin">A recapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulacion.</note> and take it to be nothinge, but as it is named verye wynde indede. Thou ſeeſt it euy dently proued, that it ſtandeth well inoughe with nature and all good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, with iuſtice and equitie, with lawe and reaſon, with Gods and mans ordinaunce, with cuſtome and antiquitie: that a woman leafte by hir progenitors, true heire of a realme, hauing the conſent of hir peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:466:45"/>the ſtabliſhment of lawe, auncient cuſtome, and Gods callyng, to confyrme the ſame: may vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly, ſuccede her auncettors lawfullye reignyng, in lawful ſucceſſion, both to enheritance and regiment. Thou ſeeſt no ſcripture is agaynſte it, truelye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſt ande, but rather both in example and practiſe, and alſo in expreſſe word and meaninge, altogether with it. Thou ſeeſt no lawe wherto we be bounde, to debarre this ſexe of this right: but in euerye wyſe to graunte it them, as it ſhal come to their courſe. And that the rule beyng ioyned to thinheritaunce, can no more be plucked from it, ſauynge iuſtice inviolated, then thy ſoule from thy body, and thou yet alyue. Thou ſeeſt laſt of all, that thinconueniences that be feared, be rather bugges to feare babes, then matter to moue men and ſpecially chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which loke not ſo much to tharme of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as to the helpe of God for their ſafetie: which truſt not in horſſe and harnes, glayues and gunnes, and ſuch other worldly meanes but in inuocation and faith, and in the mightie arme of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 147.</note> VVho delighteth no more in the legges of a goodly made man, then in the lamenes of a creeple, Nor in the rugged lookes of a deſperate warry our: then in the mylde countenaunce of a wyſe VVoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. VVherfore the matter ſtandyng ſo, that whoſoeuer rule, man or chyld, male or female, God muſt be our ſhilde, fortreſſe, and bulwarke: Let vs do our dutie bi truſting him,<note place="margin">Vve muſt caſt our care vpon God.</note> and he wyl do his, by helpyng vs, and ſo much the rather, becauſe that now, it is more like the glory ſhalbe his, if the victorie be ours, Then if we had ſome great Goliah, ſome luſtie champion, to
<pb facs="tcp:466:45"/>take the matter in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. For the next way is, to make him ſhrink from vs, to put ether our whole truſt in a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny other, or ſo to parte the prayſe with him: that his maieſtie ſhal haue one pece, &amp; our pollicie another.<note place="margin">Vve may not part vvith god</note> How oft crieth he to the Iſraelites. Nay, go to now, cal vpon your gods to helpe you, let me ſe what thei can do for you. Runne to your leaguefellowe the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptian and kynge of Aſſiria, in whom you haue put your truſt. Let them ſhyld you, agaynſt thoſe euyls that ſhal come vpon you. VVherfore let vs ſay with Dauid, Hii in curribus, Hii in equis, nos autem in nomine domini inuocabimus. Truſt who wyl in their ſtout kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> we call vpon our God to help our good Quene. Now thou art perſwaded, thou true Engly ſhe heart, that thou maiſt and oughteſt to take, eſteme, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour one of this Sexe appointed of God to rule ouer the, for thie naturall, and lawful ſoueraigne: it is thy part to know and learne, and after to do and performe all maner of dutie to her, which occupieth by mooſt iuſt title, thimperial throne of this Realme. And that thou maiſt the rather, the willinglier, and gladlier do it: I mynd by Gods grace, to treat a lytle of the dutie thou ougheſt her, of the good hope thou mayſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of her, and the fruit of doyng or balkynge thy dutie towardes her. VVhiche. iii. thynges, whyle I runne ouer: thynke it not longe, for I mynde not to make any long diſcourſe. There is no man ether of wyt ſo dull, of vnderſtandyng ſo ſſender, or of malice ſo obſtinate: but wyl and muſt confeſſe, that God by nature, haue ſo ordained all thinges: that mankinde ſhoulde not onelye rule, and haue the dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer other creatures, which be not of nature ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb facs="tcp:466:46"/>as he is, but alſo, one man ouer an other: that ſome ruling and ſome obeing, concorde and ttanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue. For if al ſhould ruie: there ſhuld be none to obey. Or if all ſhould obey: there ſhould be none to rule.<note place="margin">Some be made to rule and ſome to obeye.</note> VVherfore, God hath ſo diſpoſed his creatures in this world: that ſuche as he wyl deck and beautifie, with his ſingular giftes, ſhould by ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng other, that lacke them, be meanes to ayde and helpe them. For God ſo careth for the preſeruacion of this godly and comly frame of his, the world: that he will not leaue it without meanes of order, where by it may contynew. And though it be his peculiar propertie, to haue dominion and rule, as the onely kyng and monarke: yet becauſe our dulnes can not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaue his bryghtnes, nor our infirmitie his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie (as the people of Iſrael ſay de to Moiſes,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> let not the Lorde ſpeake to vs but thou) therfore he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth not only his power,<note place="margin">Deu. 20. Exod. 22.</note> rule, honour, and maieſtie to men: but alſo his owne name, callynge them Gods: that by their manhod, they myght con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre with men, as men, and by their name and office, repreſent a dyuine maieſtie as God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 81. Pſal. 28.</note> Ego dixi dij eſtis, ſay eth he. I ſaye you be Goddes. Agayne. Deus ſtetit in ſinagoga deorum. God ſtode emong the aſſemble of Gods, that is magiſtrates. Thus it pleaſed God to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dourne his anoynted with ſo noble a name: that we whiche be of nature rebellious, ſhuld beholde in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not only fleſh and bloud, whiche they haue commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with vs, but alſo a dyuine and godly maieſtie, which they haue geuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God. So that we ſhuld rather fixe our eyes vpon their office, whiche is gods: then
<pb facs="tcp:466:46"/>vpon their perſon whiche is mans. If this order were not in nature, al thynges woulde growe to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, while euerye man, as he were of greater power: ſo coulde and woulde oppreſſe ſuche as were of leſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> (as Theodoret ſaithe) the greate fiſhes eate vp the ſmall, and the weaker beaſtes, be the ſtrongers pray. Therefore, it is not ſaide withoute great cauſe of the apoſtle: that the Magiſtrate is for our good. For he defendeth oure bodies from the murderers, oure goodes from the rauenoure, and oure landes from the oppreſſour. Seing then that God by nature,<note place="margin">Ro. 13.</note> hath thus placed Magiſtrates in deede to be watchmen to kepe our cities, to preſerue our lande from thenemy abrode, and conſpirator and oppreſſor at home: we ſhuld be to much ingrate: if we ſhulde not loue hym or her, that careth for vs, and to obſtinat if we ſhould not obey them that rule not for their own pleaſure, but for our commoditie. Hereto we be exhorted by many places of ſcripture, wherunto, if we herke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not: we prouoke gods vengaunce to guſh out againſt vs: out of whoſe moſte holye mouth, they come. Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye ſoule (ſaithe Paul) obey the higher power, as ordeined of God: for who reſiſteth the power,<note place="margin">Ro. 13.</note> reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth Gods ordinaunce. In whiche woordes is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined both a precept and a pain. A precepte, in that he commaundeth all to obey, exceptinge none, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prieſt nor Monke ſaithe Chriſoſt.<note place="margin">Chryſ. 10. hom. 23</note> which muſte aſwell obey, as the lay itie. A pain, in that he vttreth them to be gods rebels and aduerſaries, which do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte the power ordeined of God. For who violateth the ordinaunce: violateth the ordeiner, whiche was
<pb facs="tcp:466:47"/>God. But becauſe almoſte none doubte of this, that they muſt obey (onles it be a few diſſolute Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes) and many be ignoraunt, wherin they ſhoulde obey: therfore did Paule him ſelf not omit to teach, that they muſte be obeyed in honor and paimentes. Cui vectigal,<note place="margin">Obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce conſiſteth of. ii. thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> vectigal, cui honor, honorem. For it is not inough to paye them their due, as a man payeth his hirelinge, or his miller for grindinge his corne: but he muſte alſo yelde him his due honoure, why che muſte firſte come from the harte, and then be vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in outwarde humblenes. The Perſians thoughte ther kinges and rulers to repreſent ſuch a diuine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye:<note place="margin">Hovv the perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured their kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> that they fell flat on their faces before theyr ſouereigne. And the ſame we read to be vſed among the kinges of Iury. The like wherof, the hiſtories do reporte of the Turkes, that they haue not onlye as muche honor geuen them as the kings of Perſia had: but alſo who ſo euer ſpeaketh to him, at his goinge from him,<note place="margin">Hovv the Turkes honoure theirking.</note> neuer turneth his backe vppon hym, but goeth backwarde ſo longe as he is in the ſame place wyth him. Fewe I thincke will allowe thys, yet muſte they learne hereby, that greate honour is due to that eſtate, and thincke it no Idolatrye as ſome men vſe to terme it, either to bare thy head or bowe thy knee to the chiefeſt miniſter of God, yea if thou doeſt it not thou makeſt an idoll of thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">To knele to a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is no I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry.</note> whyle thou lifteſt vppe thy baſeneſſe to that heighte, that thou wylte not ſtoupe, where thou oughteſt, nor geue honoure where thou ſhouldeſt. VVhat is els to make an Idoll of thy ſelfe, but to honour thy ſelf, where thou oughteſt not, and pull downe Goddes
<pb facs="tcp:466:47"/>Maieſtye, where thou ſhouldeſt not: Ah we bee all Adams children, yea and the deuels to, if we goe no further: But Adams children, be diſtincte in degres,<note place="margin">Degrees of men.</note> euen by the ordinaunce of God. As we rede through oute the Bible:<note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> and Chriſte in the newe Teſtamente confirmeth it, ſayinge: geue to Cefar that is his. And the apoſtle: go before one another in honoure.<note place="margin">Ro. 12.</note> So that they may rightlye chalendge it, and we be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to yelde it. But this will not be onles we firſte bow at home in oure heartes, and learne to ſtoupe, ſay inge in oure ſelfes. VVhat? thou arte a ſubiecte not called to honoure, Therefore thou muſte not pearche vp, before thou beiſt called: And couldeſt thou, if thou warte in the ſame place ſuffer (if it were not for thine owne ſake, yet for the dignities and office ſake) to be withoute honoure? If we can thus reaſon wyth oure owne proude ſtomackes: we ſhall ſoone leaue of to be Adames children, and become Goddes and the Quenes obedient ſubiectes. The hart (I ſay) muſt be framed and brought into the circle of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce:<note place="margin">Obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſpryngeth from the hart.</note> and then wyll all the reaſte followe. Thy knee ſhall bowe, thy Cap ſhall of, thy tonge ſhall reuerently ſpeake of thy ſoueraign, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wher thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. For lyke as the fountain being clear, or trobled the water that goeth from it, muſt be good or bad: ſo the hearte beynge in order, the reaſte canne not bee out of order. Thy tong muſt be dedicated to God, to ſpeke wel and reuerently of his miniſter, for els as Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lomon ſaith: he will make the birdes of the ayre to vtter thy rebellion. Furthermore, it is thy bounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duti
<pb facs="tcp:466:48"/>to geue her,<note place="margin">The .2. part of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedyence. Dein. 1. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lymth.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe calleth for part of thi goods that as Demoſth. ſaith, by parting with a little: thou maiſt keepe the whole. Is it not better to healpe the mother and miſtres of thy country, with thy goods and body: then by withholding thy hande, and nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, to make her not hable to kepe out thine enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my? haddeſt thou rather that thy auncient ennemy, the proud french man, or vntruſty ſcot, ſhould come to ranſake thy coffers, to deflour thy wife, to rauiſh thy daughters, to beat thy childrens brains vpon the walles, to fire thy houſe, to ſpoile thy goodes, driue away thy cattle, enioy thine enheritaunce, cut thine own throte, and bring thy country to naughte: then that the Quenes officer ſhould take the .20. parte of thy poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for thy defence? If thou wilt not haue theſe miſchiefes to happen thou muſt do thy dutye in paying with a franke and free hart, without grut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching or groning, ſpecially, ſeing thou gathereſt all that thou haſt, in her peax. Shuldeſt thou that arte a huſbandman follow thy tillage, reape thy corn, and enioy it: if thou wart not defended by her diligence? Shouldeſt thou that arte a graſier kepe thy fat Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lockes and flockes of ſhepe, til they were fatte: if ſhe were not thy ſhephearde? Shouldeſt thou that arte a marchant cary out, and fetch home, to thy exceding gain, thy merchaundiſe: onles ſhe were thine Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall? Could the Lord or gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enioy his rents, if ſhe defended not the tenauntes? Coulde the biſhops ruffle in their robes, kepe their great houſes, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d haue their thouſands yerely, withal the reſt of ther ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie: if ſhe wer not their bulwarke, and tooke care
<pb facs="tcp:466:48"/>for them, while thei care not for her? And to be ſhort there is none that ſhould enioy his owne: if her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection were not. If thou myſtruſt the my ſpendyng of that thou geueſt, and ſhe taketh: thou art to foliſh. For could ſhe that in al her lyſe, hath liued vpon her owne, ſo humbly without pride, ſo moderately with out prodigalitie, ſo may denly without pompe: now find in her heart, in vnneceſſary charges to laſhe out thine? VVilt thou haue a taſt, how prodigal or pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous ſhe is? I pray the then marke theſe two poynts which I know to be true (although in that Sexe they be ſtraunge) vii. yeres after her fathers death,<note place="margin">The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel.</note> ſhe had ſo proud a ſtomake, and ſo much delighted in gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng gaſes of the world, in gay apparell, riche atty re and precious iewels: that in all that tyme, ſhe neuer loked vpon thoſe that her father left her but ones, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that agaynſt her wyll. And after ſo gloried in them: that there came neuer gold nor ſtone vpon her head, tyl her ſiſter enforced her, to lay of her former ſobre nes, and bear her company in her gliſteryng gaynes. Yea, and than ſhe ſo ware it, as euery man myght ſe, that her bodie caried that, which her heart miſliked. I am ſure, that her maidenly apparel, which ſhe vſed in Kyng Edwardes tyme,<note place="margin">The po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe of engliſh ladies aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the quenes ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample.</note> made the noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters and wyues, to be aſhamed, to be dreſt and payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lyke pecockes, being more moued with hir moſt vertuous example: then with all that euer Paule and Peter wrote, touchyng that matter. Yea this I know that a great mans daughter, receaiuinge from Ladye Marie before ſhe was Quene, goodly apparel of tyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyll, cloth of golde, and veluet, layd on with parche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:466:49"/>lace of gold: when ſhe ſawe it, ſayde, what ſhal I doo with it? mary ſaide a gentle woman weare it. Nay quod ſhe, that were a ſhame to followe my lady Mary againſt Gods woorde,<note place="margin">A yonge ladies an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvere.</note> and leaue my lady Ely zabeth, whiche foloweth Gods woorde. See that good example, is ofte tymes muche better, then a great deale of preachinge. And this all men knowe, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the ladies hent vp thattire of the Scottiſh ſkyttes, at the commyng in of the Scottiſhe Quene, to go vnbrydled, and with their heares frownſed and curled and double curled: ſhe altered nothinge, but to the ſhame of them all, kepte hir olde may denly ſhamefaſtneſſe. &amp;c. An other thyng to declare, how lytle ſhe ſetteth by this worldlye pompe, is this. That in all hir tyme, ſhe neuer medled with monye but agaynſt hir wyll, but ſemed to ſet ſo lytle by it: that ſhe thought, to touche it, was to defile hir pure handes conſecrated to turne ouer good bookes, to lyfte vp vnto God in prayer, and to deale almes to the pore. Are not theſe argumentes ſufficient to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the thynke of hir: that ſhe wyll neyther call to the before ſhe hath nede, nor miſpend it vaynely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhe hath it?<note place="margin">An exhor tacion to liberalitie.</note> VVherfore if thou beareſt the hart of a chriſtian: thou wylt miniſtre to chriſtes lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt willinglye, and gladly. If thou baſt the mynde of a trewe ſubiect: thou wylt not ſee thy ſouereigne lacke. If thou haſte the forcaſte of a wyſe man, thou wylt be content with a lytle, to purchaſe ſafetie of the whole. If thou haſt the ſtomack of a good engliſh man, thou wylt with body and goodes, keepe out the forren ennemy, whiche would be glad, through thy
<pb facs="tcp:466:49"/>diſobedience, to ſalute thee at thy gate: wherfore be not couetous, where thou ſhouldeſt be lyberall, nor vnkynde, where thou ſhouldeſt be thanckfull, nor waywarde, where thou ſhouldeſt be forwarde. Take to thee, the ſtomacke of a free palfraye, and not the froward touches of a reſtie iade.<note place="margin">Li. demori</note> It is the propertie of thone, ſaieth Seneca, to goo forwarde luſtelye with the Shadowe of a wande, and of the other, to renne backwarde, put you neuer ſo muche the ſpurres to hym. Nowe by cauſe our nature is ſo dull, that it can not be ſtirred vp withoute ſome hope of benefytte: Therfore I wyll briefly ſhewe what good hope there is, by all lykely hode, of this godly gouerneſſe. And to the intent, I myght appeare to ſaye of hir for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, what I thinke and knowe, withoute ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion of flatterie, or hope of benefyt: Therefore I haue ſuppreſſed my name: that my penne might be the freer. VVherfor if thou thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſt that either I ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke more then I thynke, or do that I do for any hope of benefite: thou doeſt me wrong in miſiudging: and hir great iniury in not beleuing. If I ſhould reherſe al thynges which myght put vs in hope of hir good, godly, and vertuous reigne: I ſhoulde peruſe hir wholle lyfe paſte: But that were to longe and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perteyneth to the Storie to be wrytten of hir,<note place="margin">The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vp.</note> then to this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wherfore I wil only touch one or. 2. things to giue goodme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to geſſe at the reſt. It is knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> howe vertuoſly and vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginly keſhe hath bene brought vp what wiſe, honeſt, diſcrete, ſober, and godly women ſhe hath had about
<pb facs="tcp:466:50"/>her, howe ſhe hath bene trained in learning, and that not vulgare and common, but the pureſt and the beſt which is moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended at theſe dais, as the tonges, artes, and gods word, wherin ſhe ſo excedingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited, as I my ſelfe can wytnes, that. vii. year paſt, ſhe was not in the beſt kind of learning inferior to thoſe that al theyr lyſe tyme had ben brought vp in the vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſities, and were counted iolly felowes. So that it is lyke, that nowe, ſhe is not meanlye inſtructed and armed with good letters. If then learnyng and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſation with ſuch as be wyſe and honeſt, faſhioneth and frameth the mynde (as Plato ſayth) and maketh it tractable as waxe, to prynt in good images of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and modeſt maners: And commonly, wel tilled land bryngeth forth good frutes: we muſt nedes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue great hope, yea in a manner be aſſured: that as ſhe hath paſſed many of our kynges, and alour Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in theſe good ſtudies and Sciences: ſo ſhe muſt nedes exceede them in the reſt of her lyfe and gouern ment. And that you may vnderſtand that there hath not bene, nor is in her, learnyng without nature, and knowledge without towardnes, to practiſe: I wyl tel you, what I haue credebly hearde, and aſſuredly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue of her. For I woulde wyſhe of God, that all men knew by her aſmuch as I do: that thei might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue of her the ſame opinion that I haue.</p>
            <p>Her firſt ſcholemaſter with whome I was familiar, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very honeſt and learned,<note place="margin">The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſchole maiſters anſvver.</note> emongſt other talke, which we had of her (for I was curious in queſtioni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and he gentle in anſweringe) tolde me once, that he learned eueri day more other, then ſhe of him. It ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:466:50"/>to me a miſtery, as in dede it was, but becauſe he wold not kepe me in doubt, he thus expounded it. I teach her wordes (quod he) and ſhe me things. I tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che her the tongues to ſpeake: and her modeſt and maidenly life, teacheth me workes to do. For (ſaith he) I think ſhe is the beſt inclined and diſpoſed of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in all Europe. It ſemed to me a goodly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion of her, and a witty ſaying of him, and therfor not to be forgotten: In like maner, an Italian,<note place="margin">An Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſayinge of the Quene</note> which taught her his tonge (thoughe that nacion lightlye praiſe not out of their own country) ſaid once to me that he founde in her. ii. qualities, whiche are neuer lightly yock fellowes in one woman, whiche were a ſinguler witte, and a meruelous meeke ſtomacke, I would haue thoughte that theſe men had thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended her, becauſe ſhe was their miſtreſſe: but by certaine knowledge other waies I vnderſtode: that it was true, and that they might haue ſaid much more, and not haue lied. This diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and godly toward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes being in her then, can not now be but muche en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by continuaunce of ſtudy, hauing about her ſuch as feare God, increaſing in yeares, and taught bi affliction, which as (Dauid ſaith) bringeth vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and in a nother place.<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.</note> Bonum mihi domine quod humiliaſti me It is my great profite Lorde that thou haſt brought me lowe,<note place="margin">The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie.</note> for hereby I haue learned thy law, and of this I think no Engliſh man is ignorant: that her affliction hath ben far aboue the condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a kings daughter. For there was no more behind, to make a very Iphigenia of her, but her offring vp, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the altare of the Scaffolde. How ſhe behaued her
<pb facs="tcp:466:51"/>ſelfe in thoſe ſtormes and tempeſtes, let them wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who beyng hir aduerſaries: hadde the muynge of her. I wyll ſaye nothynge, though I coulde ſaye muche: But this I ſee, and therefore muſte ſaye, that than ſhe muſte nedes be in hir affliction maruelous pacient: whiche ſheweth hir ſelfe now in this proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to be vtterly without deſyre of reuenge: or els ſhe would haue geuen ſome token or this daye of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, howe ſhe was handled. It was no ſmal iniurie that ſhe ſuffered in the protectors dayes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certen venymous vipers ſpued oute their poyſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hir to dymyniſhe hir honour:<note place="margin">The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aſſlic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the protectors daies.</note> But God hir father and defender, made hir ſo muche the more to enter in to the hartes of good people: howe muche the earneſtlyer they wente aboute to harme hir. VVas it no wrong think you that ſhe ſuſteyned of late dayes, to be firſt a pryſoner in her owne houſe, and garded with a ſorte of cutthrotes whiche euer gaped for the ſpoyle of hir houſe, that they myght haue bene fyngeryng of ſum what? Then with great ſolempniti,<note place="margin">The Quene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted to the Tour.</note> with bandes of harneſſed hangeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie was he that might haue the carying of hir) to be ſetched vp, as the greateſt traytour in the worlde, hoiſted into the tower, there kept not lyke a kynges doughter and a Quenes ſiſter: but as one that hadde come out of Turkey to betraye Englande. VVhat aſſemblies and counſelles? VVhat examinacions and rackynges, of poore men was there, to fynde out the knyfe that ſhoulde cutte hir throte? what gaping
<pb facs="tcp:466:51"/>among my Lordes of the clargie, to ſee the daye wherein they myght waſhe their goodly whyte rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chettes in her innocent bloude? thinckinge that then none ſhoulde be ſpared, for they ſawe the bloude of the father waſh of the Scaffold, the daughters bloud, the huſbandes, the wifes, the yonger brothers, the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſo one after an other, tyll the hangemanne was wearye. VVhen they ſawe that ſo much woode was ſpente in Smith fielde about holy Martirs ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to the God in the boxe: that poore folckes for lacke died for colde in London: when they ſawe the ſtreates of London ſo decked and adourned wyth Gallowes, and behanged with gentlemens carcaſes: that my L. of London coulde not haue place to goo a proceſſion: when they ſawe all theſe notable trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies wherein no reſpecte was hadde, neither of ſexe nor kynred, neither of age nor innocency, neither of noble nor vnnoble: had not theſe ratchetters good cauſe to hope: that this bleſſed woman ſhoulde haue followed, and ſo they haue bene out of feare of thys daye, whiche is come vppon them?</p>
            <p>VVhat mente thoſe charitable Churchemenne thincke you towardes her? whan they coulde not bee contente, to ſuffer Sir Thomas VViat vpon the ſcaffolde (euen at the houre of his deathe, betwixte the axe and the block, when it is like men wil not lie) to diſcharge her, of that was laid againſt her, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden hys owne conſcience of that, he thoughte at that time hee ſtoode giltie in, for hurtynge her
<pb facs="tcp:466:52"/>to ſaue himſelfe, when he teſtified to the people that ſhe was cleare. Cried not weſton, beleue him not, be leue him not? For the racke hath wrounge out other maner of matter. Oh tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, and rake helles. VVas he rather to be beleued vpon your cruel racke, than nowe, vpon the ſcaffolde. when he feared the tearyng of his fleſhe, then when he myght loke for helles tor mentes? whan it ſtode vpon the loſſe of hys carcaſſe, than whan he muſt daunger his ſoule? Dyd you not here, vtter your miſcheuous mindes, and meanings, that you cared not, though he went to the deuyll, ſo you myght haue bene ryd of her. Theſe be the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable gooſtly fathers, which muſt be at a mans cl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe, when he is redy to dye. VVhoſe regard of the Soule is ſuche: as thei muſt nedes haue their ghoſtly chyld, euen with the laſt breath, laſh out moſt ſhame ful lyes, to maintaine their malice, &amp; murder. Theſe fellowes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe Confeſſion to ſerue their tourne, for the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch, as they would haue out of the way. If their Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion ſerued not to ſuch purpoſes, I warrant you, thei would not ſet a blewe point by it. Thus had ſhe the whole worlde agaynſt her, with all the ſpyte and malyce that could be deuiſed: And yet ſhe is ſo far offro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſekyng reueng: that I am ſurely per ſwaded, that ſhe prayeth for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Are not theſe great tokens thou good ſubiect, of much mercy to follow? Marke her comming in, and compare it with others She commeth in lyke a lambe, and not lyke a Lyon, lyke a mother, and not lyke a ſtepdam. She rusſheth not in at the fyrſt chop, to violate and breake former lawes, to ſtirre her people to chaunge what they liſt,
<pb facs="tcp:466:52"/>before order be taken by lawe. She hangeth no man, ſhe behedeth none. She burneth none, ſpoileth none. I wiſſe if my L. Cardinal had known her cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy: he would not haue made ſo much haſt in dying ſo ſone to follow his miſtres,<note place="margin">My L. of London vviſer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> and to be out of the daunger of this. I like my L. of London better: for thoughe he haue deſerued a great deale more: yet he neither ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth away, nor hangeth him ſelfe, nor nothinge, but truſteth to find grace, which neuer deſerued any. But you wil ſay that this Quene hath no ſuch aduantage againſt men, as thother had, and therfore is merciful whether ſhe wil or no: you ſay wel but not al, is ther no aduauntage to be taken, thinke you? I wil not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, becauſe I am no lawyer. But I wil axe thys for my learning of the lawyers, whether it be a faulte by ſtatute to take away the title or any part of it which belongeth to the king or Quenes ſtile? as to take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it by no order of law, but by priuate authoritie, thys part ſupreame head of the church of England. If it be a faulte, of what force were the writtes, whereby the Parliament was called, that tooke awaye the ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, if the writtes for lacke of wordes of form, wer not good in the law: by what authoritie did that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament repeale. K. H. and K E. lawes or make anye newe? by what authoritie, if they were not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called, receiued they the biſhop of Rome? And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by his authoritie, broiled, and murdred ſo many martirs? Surely if the firſt were vnlawful, the laſte can haue no warraunte, if the lawyers finde this to be ſo: hath then the Quene none aduauntage againſte men thincke you? if it be ſo: then muſt you confeſſe, that
<pb facs="tcp:466:53"/>there is a meruelous mercy and no rigour, an exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding pacience, and no deſire of reueng in her. If it be not ſo: yet might ſhe fynde good quarels els to deale more hardly with ſom then ſhe doth. In Quene Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries firſt daies the biſſhoppes that were maryed were thruſte out of the parliament houſe before any lawe, and all maryed deanes and archedeacons oute of the conuocation, many putte out of their lyuinges and other reſtored withoute force of lawe. If that were lawfull for hir: why is it not lawful for this? Yea ſome noble men and Gentlemen were depryued of thoſe landes whiche the kynge had genen them withoute tarying for any lawe: leſt my Lord of VVincheſter, ſhould haue loſt his quarters rent. Many churches were chaunged, many altares ſet vp, many maſſes ſayde, many dredges ſunge, before the lawe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, all was done in poſt haſte. Some for feare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture that they ſhoulde not els haue hadde the bleſtered maſſe, whole fyue yeares in the worſhip of the fyue Gaudees of the bleſſed virgin Mary. Nowe we ſee that thinges be doone with more aduiſement and leſſe haſte, although there be a better warraunte for this then for that. For ſhe knoweth that to bee trewe whiche Seneca ſayeth, Velox conſilium ſequitur penitentia. But the deuil is a diligent felowe, he beſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him in his matters, for he euer miſtruſteth he ſhuld come to late.<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> Contrariwyſe God is longanimus of great pacience, and maketh his to be the lyke, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to loke for amendement: then by and by to ſeke deſtruction and reuenge. VVherfore ſhe being gods choſen inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to repreſent here amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie:
<pb facs="tcp:466:53"/>walketh wiſely in the ſteps of him that hath cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led hir, and ſtudieth diligently to repreſent a lyuely image in hir mortalite of his incomparable and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice maieſtie, by vſing correction without ſeueritie, by ſekyng the loſte with cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, by gouerning wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely without fury, with weying and iudging without raſhenes, with purging il rumors with deliberacion, and to conclude, in doing hir dutie without affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Beſides furth it is not the leſt toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all to perſwade vs of hir happy and godly procedinges, that ſhe pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out ſome ſuch couſelors to ſerue hir (and I truſt will do more) as be neither of common wytte nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, of whom ſome by trauaile in ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge countreis, ſom by learning, ſome by practiſe and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke authoritie in other rulers daies, ſome by afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either one waye or other: for their giſtes and graces whiche they haue receiued at Gods hande, bee men mete to be called to ſuche roumes. And if any man thinkes there be inter azimos fermentum let them leaue that to God and tyme, and deſcant not to farre of it. Herein ſhe well putteth in practiſe that is counſelled by Eccleſiaſticus, ſaying conſiliarius ſit tibi vnus de mille.<note place="margin">Eccl. 6.</note> Culle out of a thouſand a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellour, for it is no mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of ſmall waight to chuſe counſellors as it aperith by the counſell and ſucceſſe of Roboam whiche was of two ſortes.<note place="margin">1. Reg 12.</note> Thauncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t men &amp; Senators gaue him cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel &amp; aduiſe to kepe the people in order by loue, gentlenes, and cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy, thother aduiſed hym not to ſpare but to lay about him to chop of their heades, to towre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, burne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, awai with them, dead me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do no harme, and to make his litle finger heauier vpon
<pb facs="tcp:466:54"/>his people the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was his fathers body. Theſe ware luſty laddes theſe were ſuche: as would wyne all our loſe all. But they founde at the laſt as other that haue fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them very Hieroboamites as wriſſles, VVyn cheſters and ſome other their ſcholers yet aliue, that as Horatius ſaieth vis conſilij expers,<note place="margin">Horat. in od. s.</note> mole ruit ſua. fearſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes without wiſdome, and counſel, cummeth to a ſo liſhe ende. I doubt not but hir maieſtie if ſhe could, woulde chuſe hir counſell of the nobilyte, ſhe being her ſelfe the head of that order and patroneſſe: but if ſhe ſhal eſpie out meaner men of greater experience, farther reache, and more ſcyence, then they be: it is not to be feared, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nobles both for their owne ſafetie, and the Quenes, would gladly lotte to them ſelfes (though ſhe woulde not require it) ſuche as myght put them in mynde of thynges they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not, either becauſe they haue not exerciſed and beaten their heads about it: or by lookyng to their lordſhips haue not had leiſure to ſtuddy for polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. But wiſe men by ſtudy and noble men by birth, wyll make ſuche an harmony in the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth: as neyther Frenche nor Scotte, ſhalbe hable to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupte the concorde: and it to be hoped that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one parte in reſpect of their nobilitie, wyll contempne the other for their baſenes nor enuie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their wiſdom: nor thother part through thadmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion of their own giftes, ſet light by the honour &amp; au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tnes of the peres.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> Learne a ſimilitude ſaith Paul of the body of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how eche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber is not the head, &amp; yet hath his neceſſary vſe in the bodye, wherefore if
<pb facs="tcp:466:54"/>ſome be wiſer, and ſome nobler, ſom richer, and ſom porer: I doubt not but like good marmers they will all conſider, that they muſt all trauaile to bringe the ſhip of the common welth, the Church of Chriſte, and the Quenes realm, to a quiet port, which wil not be: if they ſtriue, who ſhall tend the ſail, and who the helm, who ſhall ſounde, and who clenſe the Pumpe, who ſhal do this, and who ſhal do that. Ioſephe with King Pharao kept by his counſel al the kings people from ſtaruinge, a meane man and a ſtraunger, pulled out of Priſon, wher he lay for a great crime.<note place="margin">Gen. 41.</note> And Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell gouerned Chaldea better then all the Princes ther, and his ſeruice was more acceptable to the king then all the reſt: Mardocheus by the help of Heſter,<note place="margin">Heſter. 8.</note> kept Aſſuerus from the fouleſt murdre, that euer was deuiſed. And yet he was but a meane man to be of a kinges counſell, being not onlye a ſtraunger, but alſo ſuche an abiecte, as ſatte at the kinges gate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out office, dignitie, countenaunce, or anye eſtimaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea and of ſuche a ſtomacke, as he woulde not ſtoupe to the proudeſt of all the reaſte. M. Haman, who was, domine fac totum, Vvhiche had like to haue coſt him the beſt ioynte he caried aboute. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if meane men be called to that honoure: lette no manne repine at it. For ſometime vnder a homelye coate, lieth hidden muche treaſure, and pure golde is founde among muche droſſe.<note place="margin">Pro. 21.</note> A wiſe man ſaithe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon climeth vp into the cities, of the ſtronge and mightye, and deſtroieth all the ſtrengthe that he truſteth to: if I had but. 10. Neſtors, ſaid Agamenon Troy could not ſtand longe. Conſideringe then that
<pb facs="tcp:466:55"/>aſwell in the choiſe of counſelloures as in all other thynges oure mooſte deare ſoueraigne taketh that waye: as all godlye wiſe men muſte needes accompte the beſt: and geueth vs by theſe buddes and floures, ſo greate hoope of ſingulare frute: we maye if we bee nor ſtoones in ſence, and monſters in malice, cheare and feede our ſelues with the good ſucceſſe, we hope to haue by her. One thinge there is that maketh my harte to blede in my belly for her: That when al her progenitoures commonly haue founde their realm in quiet: She good Lady receiueth it at the hande of her ſiſter intangled (I will not ſaye oppreſſed) wyth forren warres, the french on thone ſide, and the ſcots on thother, which ſucking oute of their auncettors, poiſoned breaſts, immortal and dedly hatred againſt this realme, lie in waite like theues, to inuade and to ſpoil it. In token wherof the french freke, as it is ſaid after truce was taken: VVhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hard of .Q. M. death kept ſtil his Germains about him, vpon hope that if there had ben any ſtir in England, he might haue ſet in a fote. And for that purpoſe, had willed the cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of lotharing, to confer with our churchmen, to ſe what mighte be done, whether he did ſo or no God knoweth: but it is certain that the cardnall had ſuche commiſſion: but God hath diſpatched their deuiſes. And beſides that ſhe is thus lefte: who ſeeth not the realme not Philipped, but fleſed for Philips ſake, by mainteining all the laſt ſommer, ſuch a nauy on the ſeas, and an army on the land, beſides ſom tokens of loue that paſſed (I am ſure) from the Quene to her ſpouſe, to ſhew that ſhe was a louing wife: Alas what
<pb facs="tcp:466:55"/>remeadye? it is a miſerable caſe:<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.</note> but this will be the help, firſt to flee to God, and ſay on euery ſide. In do, mino confido, quomodo dicitis animae mae tranſmigra in montem ſicut paſſer. Our truſt is in God, thoughe the French and ſcots, and the deuil him ſelfe had conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt our ſouerein, whiche is anima noſtra, oure life and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort. Shal not we with God and pollicy, be hable to do aſmuch for the preſeruation of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as Philip of Macedonie did with pollicy alone?<note place="margin">Gemiſtus. Princes of il begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninges, oft mak good endinges.</note> who comming to his kingdom in as il caſe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d worſe, then this vertuous Lady doth to hers, hauing the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyrians, the Paenyans, the Theſſalonyans, the Boeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and the Atheniens, in his neck: ſo vſed the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by making peax with ſome, by leaguinge with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and by war with the reſt, one after another, that within .iii. yeres ſpace, he gatte again that his ancet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors had loſt, and made al his enemies to ſtoupe, and not long after became themperor of al Grece.<note place="margin">2. Samu. 3.</note> In like maner Dauid entred into his kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins had made a meruelus ſlaughter in Iſrael, and killed king Saul a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes in the field, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yet with in a while, he recouered the loſſes, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d had the better of al his enemies round about him: So I doubt not, but God ſhal ſend this Iudith grace and power, to cut of Holophernes hed, and this Deborah to ſaue her peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d knock out Siceras brains, com he either out of fraunce, or out of ſcotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. But ſo much the ſoner: if al men like true ſubiectes, put to their helping hande, knowinge that it is theyr quarrell aſwell as hers. Come of you biſhoppes, away with your ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<note place="margin">Aduiſe to the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</note> yeld vp your thouſands, be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreds
<pb facs="tcp:466:56"/>as they be in other reformed Churches, where be as greate learned men as you are. Let your portion be prieſtlike and not princelike. Let the Quene haue the reſt of your temporalties and other la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain theſe warres which you procured,<note place="margin">Biſhoppes landes.</note> and your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe left her, and with the reſt to builde and founde ſcholes thorow oute the realme: that euerye pariſhe church may haue his preacher, euery City his ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendent to liue honeſtly and not pompouſly, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wil neuer be, onles your landes be diſperſed and beſtowed vpon many, which now feadeth and fatteth but one. Remember that Abimeleck, when Dauid in his baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wold haue dined with him,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 21</note> kept ſuch hoſpitaliti: that he had no bread in his houſe to geue him, but the Shew bred. wher was all his ſuperfluity to keepe your pretenſed hoſpitalitie? for that is the cauſe that you alledge, why you muſt haue thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds as though you were commaunded to kepe hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, rather with a thouſande, then with a hundreth: I would our country man VVicliefes boke whych he wrote deeccleſia, were in print, and there ſhoulde you ſee that your wrinches and cauillations, be nothing worthe. It was my chaunce to happen of it in ones hand that brought it out of Bohemia. Lay to youre handes,<note place="margin">Aduiſe to the noble men.</note> you noble men, and rather ſel a pece of your enheritance to help the Quene, then by a little back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes to ventre all, and to ſe a proud French man, your heir, or a Scot, the ſteward of your landes, learn you of thauncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſenators of Rome, and let your wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, take example by theirs, to ſette more by youre Prince, then your pomp, by your country, then by
<pb facs="tcp:466:56"/>your curioſitie and vnſitting ſuperfluitie in apparel, dyet, and other vnneceſſaries.<note place="margin">Liui. 3 de.</note> Theſe Romaines of whome I ſpeake being ſtreſſed and almoſte brought to the laſt caſt, by the long and daungerous warres of Hanibal, and the Frenche, did not only lyke louing fathers to their countrey, bring in their mony and goodes, without hinching or pinching, to reliefe the charges of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth: But alſo partly by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and partly by their good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked the noble matrones their wiues, to bringe in their ouches, ringes, chaines, bracelettes, and other iewelles, to be beſtowed in the neceſſary defenſe of their countrey. Oh you Engliſhe ladies, learne here rather to weare Romain hartes, then Spaniſh knaks,<note place="margin">Aduiſe to the ladies.</note> rather to helpe youre countrey, then hinder youre huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, to make your quene ryche for your defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe then your huſbandes poore for your gariſh gaineſſe. If euery one of you would but imploy your ringes and chaines, or the price of your ſuperfluous ruffes, furres, fringes, and ſuche other trinkettes, vpon the neceſſary defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey: I thinke you ſhuld make the quene much richer, &amp; habler to mete with your enemies, and your ſelfes much the honeſter, &amp; reddier to withſtande Satan whiche this waye goeth about to ſift you. leaue of your pride &amp; leaue a good example as the Romain ladies did to your poſterite, of loue to your countrey, loyaltie to your quene,<note place="margin">To the Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> &amp; honeſtie towardes God and man. Be liberal you Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; thinke it not inough to ſerue the quene with your bodies, but helpe alſo with your goodes. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not the Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Fraunce to make you their
<pb facs="tcp:466:57"/>ſlaues. Some of you knowe what natured men they be, beware that the reſt feele not. It wilbe a ſhame and to great a vilanie for you, which in al ages haue bene hable to holde their noſe to the grindſtone, nowe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſparing of your goodes, which is niggardie, or feare of your liues, which is cowardiſe, to be their pezantes, whoſe lordes your Auncettors were. Loke to this geare you. Lawyers, whiche for a lyttle ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of your breath in chatering in the Chancery, and common place: become the Lordes of your cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis, and leaue your ſonnes ſo great liuelodes as thei be noble mens matches. Some in ſport cal you drud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and not iudges, but I thinke in god earneſt that it is contrary that you make you and your lordes and al other drudges. In this your ſo gret gain forget not what you owe to your prince, by whoſe protection you haue had leaſure to ſtudy, &amp; now time to plead. If your countrie be not kept in peax, your law wilbe litle worth, neither your copes nor coifes wil ſerue to any vſe. I would you could al finde in your hartes to be as liberal toward your prince as ſome of you haue bene of late to the orders of Friers. Be no niggardes you marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of your gaines to releue the quene,<note place="margin">To the marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</note> for if you be: the vengeaunce of God wil come vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your hurdes and ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes, the tratling Scot ſhal knocke out your cheſtes botoms,<note place="margin">Iacob. 5.</note> ſhal enioy your machaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, meete out your veluets and ſilkes, carry awaye your clothes, brenne your fayre houſes, and rule in your citie of London, which the lord forbyd: In like maner you Farmers and Franklins, you yomen and riche Cobbes, abroad with your ruſty ryals &amp; your
<pb facs="tcp:466:57"/>old Angels, which you hourd vp: for the ruſte of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe to your conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe you couetouſly kepe Gods creatures fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their true vſe, wherfore thei were made. They are called currau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; not ſlepaunt. Helpe your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let the quene haue part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that you may peaceably enioy the reſt. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hourd you them vp, and for whome?<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note> Theſaurizas neſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s cui co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregas. I am ſure your meaning is thereby to leaue your ſonnes and heires, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, paſtures wel ſtored, houſes wel furniſhed, and honeſt ſoms of money to marrv your doughters. But if thou beſt not liberal towardes the defence of thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try: who ſhal be thine heire? The pocky frenche man and the ſcoruy Scot: thyne olde gold ſhalbe caried away into Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, thy ſonne and thou ſhalt be made gally ſlaues. And where thou thinkeſt to marry thy daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter richelye: thou ſhalt ſee both hir and hir mother defiled before thy face miſerably. Thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhalbe chaines in the gally, wherwith he ſhalbe fettered, a whippe vpon his bare ſkinne, if he row not to the death, and an horſe lofe and water for his dayly dyet. Oh thynke vppon this, thynke vppon it, you hourders and hyders of Gods creatures. Lette not that mucke of the molde, thoſe ruſtye Royalles be dearer to you, then your countrey, your Quene, your wyfe, and children, your owne bodies and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. VVhat a ſpyte were it, that you ſhoulde be the Treaſurers of your mortall foes, that you ſhoulde keepe for them to carry awaye,<note place="margin">To the huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> and hyde from your Quene to enryche the robber. And you huſbande men whiche haue Gods plenty, aboundaunce of his
<pb facs="tcp:466:58"/>bleſſinges. Sticke not to helpe your natural cuntrey ſo muche as you can. God is benificiall vnto you, be not vnthankfull to his chefe miniſter. For like as the ſpringes and brookes renne into the ſea: ſo muſt all mens trauail tourne to the defence of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey. If the ſpringes ſhould withholde their water: at the laſt the ſea ſhuld lacke So if euery one of you hold back your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: what ſhal become of your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey &amp; next of your ſelues? The Philoſophers ſay that the ſonne draweth vp the moiſtnes of the water in the ſea, and therof maketh the cloudes whiche after according to the wil of God, be caried ouer al the face of thearth to water it, &amp; of that water, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, riſeth the ſpringes and ryuers, ſo that neither the ſea can be without the ſpringes, nor the ſprings with out the cloudes, nor the cloudes without the ſea. Lo what a mutuall contributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here is in helping one an other. In like maner if you yelde not to the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie, parte of your frutes: it ſhalbe ouerru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne for lacke of helpe with your enemies, and what ſhall then become of you? If you yelde liberallie to your head, ſhe ſhalbe hable by Gods grace to defend you with her ſouldiars, ſo that you may eare in hope, ſow in ſuertie, reape with ioye, and eate with ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty. Is not this ſea of yours, your countey and quene, by many meanes ſucked drie thynke you? Is it a Small charge to maynteyne a nomber of ſhyppes againſt the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che that they haue no leaſure to lande in Englande, and inuade you? To maynteyne an armie in the borders, to keepe the countrey from burnynge and ſpoylynge? VVhat ſaye you to the buyldynge of
<pb facs="tcp:466:58"/>block houſes by the ſeas ſide, the prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of harnes, gunnes, and weapons for the warre, to the kepinge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her, a great cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of wiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to debate for your welth and ſafegard, to the ſendinge embaſſadors hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thither, with a thouſand more charges whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wer to long to recken: From whence muſt thys come? but from the frutes of the earth, which by qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes you gather: and without her defence you muſt loſe. Oh you count it a great matter, to geue. 3. or. 4 ſhillings in the pound. Oh England, England, thou knoweſt not thine own welth: becauſe thou ſeeſt not other countries penury. Oh if thou ſaweſt the pezan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Fraunce, howe they are ſcraped to the bones, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what extremities they ſuffer: thou woldeſt think thy ſelf bleſſed (as in dede thou art) whiche haſte ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fathers and mothers to thy gouernoures, then Kinges or Quenes. The huſbandman in Fraunce, al that he hath gotten in his whole life, louſeth it vpon one day. For when ſo euer they haue warre (as they are neuer without it) the kings ſouldiers enter into the poore mans houſe, eateth and drinketh vp al that euer he hath, geueth their horſe his corn, ſo longe as it laſteth, without paying a farthinge, and neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth ſo long as there is any thing left in the hous. This was the maner:<note place="margin">Hovv the french pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zantes bee handled.</note> but this king hathe amended it with the wurſe, for his ſouldiours come not thither, but his rakehels thofficers, which pare them euen to the bones, the pore man neuer goeth to the market, to ſel any thing: but he paieth a tolle, almoſt the half of that he ſelleth: he eateth neither pigge, goſe, capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor hen: but he muſt pay as much for the tribute of
<pb facs="tcp:466:59"/>it there, as it might be bought for here: h. Ovnhappy and miſerable men that liue vnder this yocke. In I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly they ſay it is not much better,<note place="margin">The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtate in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talie.</note> the huſband men be there ſo rich: that the beſt coate he weareth is ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, his nether ſtockes of his hoſe, be his own ſkin, his diet and fare not very coſtly, for he commeth to the market with a henne or two in one hande, and a doſen egges in a nette in the other, whiche beynge ſolde and tolde, he bieth and carrieth home vvyth him, no Biefe or Mutton, Veale or ſea fiſhe, as you do: but a quarte of oyle to make ſallettes of hearbes, wherewith he liueth all the weke followinge. And in Germanie thoughe they be in ſome better caſe then thother:<note place="margin">The coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimen in Germani.</note> yet eat thei more rotes then fleſh. For what cheare ſo euer they haue beſide, they are ſure of ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ſtinckinge hearbes, whiche they call crowte. Thus theſe men liue and thinke them ſelues happy: if thei may haue inough of this. Now compare them with thee: and thou ſhalt ſee howe happye thou arte. They eat hearbes: and thou Beefe and Mutton. Thei rotes:<note place="margin">A compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Engliſh ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvith other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men.</note> and thou butter, cheſe, and egges. Thei drinck commonly water: and thou good ale and beare. Thei go from the market with a ſallet: a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thou with good fleſhe fill thy wallet. They lightlye neuer ſee anye ſea fiſh: and thou haſt thy belly full of it. They paye till their bones rattle in their ſkin: and thou layeſt vp for thy ſonne and heir. Thou art twiſe or thriſe in thy life time called vppon to healpe thy Countrye, with a ſubſidie or contribution: and they daily pay and neuer ceaſe. Thou liueſt like a Lorde, and they like dogges. God defende vs from the feling of their
<pb facs="tcp:466:59"/>miſery. I am a fraid our grutching and groning, will make vs to taſte of this whip, as it muſt nedes come to paſſe, if thy heade haue not wherewith to defende the: theſe wil be the frutes of thy diſobedience VVe liue in paradiſe. England is the paradiſe and not Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as commonlye they call it. For they haue figges,<note place="margin">The fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land and Italy.</note> Orenges, Pomgranates, Grapes, Pepons, Oyle, and herbes: and we haue Shepe, Oxen, Kie, Calues, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Fiſh, woll, Leade, Clothe, Tinne, Leather, and infinite treaſures more, which they lacke. VVe haue plenty of all thinges: and they ſcarceſitie of all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Oh if thou kneweſt thou Engliſhe man in what welth thou liueſt, and in how plentifull a Countrye: Thou wouldeſt .vii. times of the day fall flat on thy face before God, and geue him tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks, that thou wart born an Engliſh man, and not a french pezant, nor an Italy an, nor Almane.<note place="margin">VVhat vvill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv oure grutching.</note> If thou beiſte not thanckfull to God, and liberall to thy Quene and Country: the poore pezante of Fraunce, ſhall enioye thy wealthe: and feele howe happye thou arte, and thou ſhalt taſte of his miſerye to knowe howe vnhappye he is. The Frenche ſhall teache thee to eate rotes and Acornes: ſeinge thou canſte not fynde in thy harte to doe thy dutie, to them that mainetaine thys thy vvealthe, Thou muſte learne to drincke water, if thou comeſt vnder his yocke, and ſpare thy Barly and Ootes, for his greate horſes. The Scottes in ſpite of vs,<note place="margin">The folye of the Scottes.</note> haue made him their heade: but they ſhall tell me or it be long, how wiſely they haue dealte, hauer cakes will be good manchet with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within a while.<note place="margin">Ioſua.</note> God that defended his children of Iſrael from the Amalechits
<pb facs="tcp:466:60"/>the Paleſtines, the Iebuſites, the Ammonites, the Moabites, and all the reſt of their enemies defend vs from the ſlauery and miſery of that proude nacy on, that cruel people, and tirannous rulers. Furthermor for the ſauegard of your country, if you be called to the warres, grutche not nor grone not at it: go with good willes and luſty courages,<note place="margin">An exhor tacion to manlines in the vvarres.</note> rather to mete them in the field, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to tarry til they come home to you, and hang you at your own gates. Play not the milk ſoppes in making curtſy, who ſhal go firſt: but ſhew your ſelues true Engliſhe men in readines, courage, and boldnes: and be aſhamed to be the laſt, feare nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther french, nor Scot. For firſt you haue God, and al his army of angels on your ſide: you haue right and trouth,<note place="margin">God is Engliſh.</note> and ſeeke not to do them wronge, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend your own right. Think not that God wil ſuffer you to be foyled at their handes, for your fall is hys diſhonour, if you loſe the victory: he muſt loſe the glory. For you fight not only in the quarel of your country: but alſo and chieflye in the defence of hys true religion, and of his deare ſonne Chriſte, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt men of the ſame religion, whiche might make theuent doubtfull, but againſte his ennemies, Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes frendes, the Turkes confederates, ethnikes, Idolaters, and very helhounds. If there wer nothing els to prouoke gods fury and extreme vengaunce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that turkiſh Valeſius the french tiraunte:<note place="margin">The fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Turke.</note> but that he roigneth him ſelfe in league wyth Chriſtes ſworn enemy the Turke: were it not inough to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, yea to enflame the wrath of God againſte him? is he a king or a deuel, a chriſtian or a lucifer, that bi his
<pb facs="tcp:466:60"/>curſed confederacie ſo encourageth the Turke, that he nowe dare be bolde to venter vppon Polonia, a Chriſtian realme, whiche hath receiued the goſpel. And that way to come into Germany. Oh wicked catiſe, and fierbrand of hell, which for thincreaſing of his pompe and vayn glory (whiche he ſhall not long enioye) wil betray Chriſt and his croſſe,<note place="margin">The fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch is Chriſtes enemy &amp; the Turks Friende.</note> to his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall enemy. Oh foliſh Germains which ſe not their owne vndoing. VVhiche conſpire not together with the reſt of chriſten Princes, to pull out ſuche a tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour to God and his kyngdome by the eares oute of Fraunce, and hange hym againſt the ſonne a drying: The deuill hath none other of his ſyde nowe, but him to mainteyne bothe the ſpirituall and the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Antechriſte, the Pope and the Turke: GOD can not longe ſuffer this, though he wynke a whyle at his wretchednes, and ſuffer him to ſcourge vs and other, vntil we knowe our ſelues: And after vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly he will pull his feathers, he wyll coole his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, as he did Nabucadnezer, and others whoſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple he followeth: wherfore ſeynge he hath forſaken God lyke an Apoſtata, and ſolde him ſelfe to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: let vs not doubte but God wilbe with vs againſt him: when ſo euer he ſhall ſeeke to wrong vs, and I truſt wyll nowe in the latter age of the worlde ſhewe his myght in cuttynge of this proude Holophernes head, by the hande of our Iudith: Oh bleſſed is that man that loſeth his lyfe againſt ſuch a Termagaunt: yea more bleſſed ſhall they be that ſpende their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues againſt hym, then againſt his great maiſter the Turke: for the Turke neuer vnderſtode the croſſe
<pb facs="tcp:466:61"/>of Chriſte, but this Iulian Apoſtata, is named a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelles name: Chriſtianiſſimus. And is in the verye harte of Chriſtendome: and lyke a traitorous Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene is Chriſtes enemy.<note place="margin">The fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch manhod is not to be feared.</note> Secondarely what people be they with whome we ſhall matche: are they Giaunts, are they conquerours, or monarks of the world? No good Engliſhe man they be effeminate Frenchmen: Stoute in bragge, but nothing in dede. They be ſuch as you haue alwayes made to take their heles. They be your ſlaues and tributaries: whoſe Caſtels, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and townes, you haue poſſeſſed, whoſe armies you haue not ones but .500. tymes diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fited, whoſe noble men you haue manfully killed, ſpoyled their countrey, brent their cities, taken their kynges, and crowned your owne, in the chiefeſt cytie of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, as their owne hiſtories do teſtifie.<note place="margin">Tillius in Chrono. Cuminius de bello Burgund. Pol. Virg.</note> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our auncettors victories at Crauantum, at Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolium, about Amias, in the borders of Normandy, at Creſſiacum, at Dagincourt, when ſome tyme they killed. 2000. ſome tyme. 3000. VVhen they had in the fiielde againſt vs to helpe them the king of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heme, the kyng of Scottes, the kyng of Nauare, the Duke of Lotharinge, the Duke of Flaunders, and 26. ſtraunge earles.<note place="margin">Till. an. 1339.</note> Yea their hiſtories doo confeſſe that we haue ſorer handled them: then euer the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains wereable to doo. At this daye the Germaines that come home out of their warres ſaye: That the Franſois are more afraied of the Engly ſhe then of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nacion:<note place="margin">The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fault.</note> And it is no maruaile, for we haue tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Gods help euer had the better of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Only this was our faulte, whiche was alſo Hanniballes, that we
<pb facs="tcp:466:61"/>coulde conquere them when we lyſte: but we coulde not vſe the victorye, in kepynge that we hadde got, whiche was oure negligence and not lacke of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode. In oure tyme what good forune haue we had agaiſt them? Howe dyd Kynge Henry the eyght Scourge them? In his youthe, wanne Turwyne and Turney, and in his age Bulloigne, Blackneſte, Newe hauen, Tholde man, and all that countrey. VVhen durſt theſe meacockes mete vs in the field? or if they did: went they not weepynge awaye? This courage was in our Auncettors, that they thought it a ſport to warre with the Frenche men: They contempned them as diſhe cloutes: and ſhall we feare them as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors? They inuaded them in their owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: and ſhall we ſuffer them to bragge vs at oure own gates? Thei haue left vs this glory for our enhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaunce:<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> report of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe.</note> and ſhal not we leaue it to our poſteritie? It hath ben alwayes ſayd of Thengliſhe and yet is (as of the Ombri) that either they will wynne or they will die. Oh ſhall we ſuffer this honour to be taken from vs in our dayes? Shall not we leaue it aſwell to oure children: as our progenitors left it to vs? Tuſſhe feare neither their horſe nor their gunnes: For when they haue the ſeas at their backes, in ſteade of their foxe holes, wherinto they always crepe, and the black byll at their noſes, our arrowes in their ſides, and Engliſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lokes in their eies: they wilbe ſo perplexed that they can not tel where to wynde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Then reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that for this .110. yeares our au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cettors haue ſcourged the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; kept this noble yle ſpite of the deuil &amp; them. Sauing that VVilliam of Norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy crept in among
<pb facs="tcp:466:62"/>vs through the cyuill warre of twoo brethren, He rald and Toſton.<note place="margin">Tillius polyd.</note> And yet what did he? He leſte his poſteritie to reigne, which were rather by tyme tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be Englyſhe: then the noble Englyſhe, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comme Frenche, as oure tongue and maners at this daye declareth, whiche differeth very lytle from our Auncettors the valy aunt Saxones.<note place="margin">VVe be the Saxo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s poſteritie.</note> VVe haue a fewe hunting termes and pedlars Erenche in the louſye lawe, brought in by the Normanes, yet remayning: But the language and cuſtomes bee Englyſhe and Saxonyſhe. I can not tell what Frenche bloude is left. But if there be any Frenche hartes, I woulde they hadde to it the Mall Francois, whiche is their countrey mens enheritaunce: Beſydes this you haue the pidlyng Scottes, whiche are alwayes Frenche for their lyues. So we haue had them alwayes, we neuer had to doo with the one, but we hadde the other bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy againſt vs. For they haue bene and are to vs as the Philiſtines, Iebuſites, Amalechites. &amp;c. were to Gods people prickes and thornes in oure ſydes, to keepe vs from pryde, or as the Samnites, were to the Romaines rather to exerciſe vs in warres, then that they were euer hable to doo vs any diſpleaſure: how ofte haue we inuaded them, euen to the harte of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, made notable ſlaughters, killed their kings, take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their nobles, and did in maner what we liſt: our victories of late days as Flodo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> field, Muſſelborough field, Saint Catherines daye and other, declare that our borders nede more to ſeare the ſtealyng of their cattel: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any inuadig of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie. And that wher to they truſt moſt: ſhalbe theyr greateſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and
<pb facs="tcp:466:62"/>greateſt helpe, I mean the commyng in of the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch men into theyr countrie. For nether the begerlines of the land, wilbe able to fede the fine mouthed fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor the nature of the Scotts can long ſuffer their yocke, and ſo wyll they together by the eares. Thus haue we nothing to diſmay vs, but al thyng to enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs. God to fyght for vs, the ſtrength of our land the courage of our men, the goodnes of the ſoyle, to geue vs to maintaine warre, the wekenes of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ouer whom we haue rained, and triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phed, the ryght of the quarrel. And to conclude all likelihode of victory to make vs rather to conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then fear them. VVherefore, if thou beiſt a man: ſhrinke not. If thou beiſt a good Subiect, ſeke no excuſes. As one did, when a Noble man muſtred his men towardes Bolloigne. One, among the reſt, which deſired to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at home, ether becauſe thei hadd ſome diſeaſe, or wer in ſome part lame, or had ſome ſuch impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeing that diuers wer excuſed, deſired that he might tari at home alſo. Nay ſaith the noble man, thou art a tall fellowe, young and luſty, hable to the King ſet uice, thou muſt nedes go. Alas ſyr quod he, I haue an impediment, I cannot go. Vvhat is that ſayd the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man. Mary my hart faileth me ſyr, quod he. Yea ſaith the noble man, is that thy impediment, in dede thou canſt not haue a wurſſe. But I wyll remedie the of that with an halfepeny halter, if there be no other helpe. Suche whyte liuered mylke ſoppes be no true Englyſh, for thei lacke tholde Engliſhe hartes.</p>
            <p>¶ Nowe therfore, it is all our duties, to be in euery wiſe be obedient to gods liuetenaunt our ſouereign,
<pb facs="tcp:466:63"/>in forwardnes, and helping her both with our goods londes,<note place="margin">Our duty of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> and bodies, when nede is, euerye man in hys callyng. If we do not: we fyrſt prouoke Gods wrath agaynſt vs, to poure downe his vengeaunce vppon vs, either by ſicknes and plagues, or by openinge the mouthe of the earth, and hell to ſwallowe vs, to the dongeon of damnation,<note place="margin">Nu. 16.</note> as Corah, Dathan and Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, or to ſend vs a tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in ſtead of a louiug Quene and mother to raigne ouer vs: or by turning the hart of the prince through our vnkindnes, churliſhnes, &amp; rebellion, from vs. That where as ſhe loued vs, and truſted vs: ſhe muſt be greeued and ſuſpecte vs. And what prouoketh Princes to be lyons, and ſeuere, yea maketh them tyrants? but the frowardnes, the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes, the kicking and diſobedience of the vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſubiectes, as Thucy dides ſayth of Harmodius, and Ariſtogeiton,<note place="margin">Thueyd. li. 6.</note> which by the cowarde kyllinge of Hipperchus made Hippias to be a fraied, thei would do the lyke to him. And therupon gat hym a garde about hym, cut his ſubiects ſhorter, gaue them leſſe libertie, ſhewed them the leſſe loue, ioyned himſelfe with other kinges, to make him ſtrong, made harder lawes. VVhere as before he ruled curteouſlye, brake no olde lawes, nor vexed them not. The frowardnes of the people is a great matter to alienate the princes mynde from them: wherefore, if thou wylt haue a good kyng or Quene: playe thou the good ſubiect. And if thei be of nature enclined to clemencie: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke them not to fury. If thei be not: rather ſtudy to wynne them by obedience, then to exaſpetate them by Rebellion. It is for the ſynnes of the people that
<pb facs="tcp:466:63"/>God ſuffereth tirantes to raign. For if the people did their dutie: God would rewarde them with mercy.<note place="margin">The gain of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note> By diſobedience to thy head, what gaineſt thou? but fyrſt as I ſay, Gods wrath, next thi rulers diſpleaſure which as Salomon ſaith: is death. 3. Trouble of thine owne mynd, while thou kickeſt agaynſt the pricke.<note place="margin">Pro. 16</note> Then the daunger of thi country, in that by thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, thou openeſt agate, to let in thy common enemy, both to thy countries and thine owne vndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Thou prouokeſt thi prince to hedge the in, with many lawes, which is fyrſt thy deſerte, and after thy hurt. For as Arceſilaus ſayd,<note place="margin">Arceſilaus</note> where there be manye Phiſicians and Poticaries: it is a ſigne there be many diſeaſes: So wher be many lawes:<note place="margin">Then ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvhat vve bee in England.</note> it is a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of much diſobedience. Laſt of al, thou art ſure, if God puniſh the not here: yet ſhalte thou not go ſcott free in the world to come. Loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iewes at this day, who for their rebellious and vnquiet nature, are ſcattered abrode in the world, theircities deſtroied,<note place="margin">Ioſeph de capt. The rebel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>l on of the Ievves.</note> their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie deſolate, and their name abhorred. And who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Ioſephus ſhal ſe, that it could not be otherwiſe. For there was neuer vnder the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſuch a rebellious people. I graunt that the chefe cauſe was, the refuſall of Chriſt, but God puniſhed that ſinne with a nother by ſending them vnbuxome hartes, wherbi thei mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght purchaſſe their owne deſtruction. As it came to paſſe at the laſt, to the terror of all rebellious and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious nacions.<note place="margin">Thucyd, Polyb. Lin.</note> VVhat made Scicilia that noble ile to be ſo toſſed and turmoiled, as it was? Firſt betwixt the olde Atheniences the Lacedemonians and after that betwixt the Romains and Carthagiens: but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord
<pb facs="tcp:466:64"/>among them ſelues, and diobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to their rulers?<note place="margin">Scic lia.</note> what made the romains ſo ſone to ouerthrow Grece: but that manye cities refuſed to be gouerned by the Atheniens and ſome other by the Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and others by other,<note place="margin">Thucyd.</note> ſo that it was an eaſy matter to win thoſe countries, that by ciuill warre and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience had loſt and vndon them ſelues: what made either Dane or Normand to ſette his fote in this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble realm:<note place="margin">Englande co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered by diſcord</note> but werines in the ſubiectes of their own naturall rulers, and malicious deſire to haue innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions? This hath ben the vndoing of all countries to be loth to obey, and readye to rebell. Contrariwiſe where good concorde, and brotherlye vnitie, where loyaltie and obedience is: there muſte neades bee a ſure ſtate,<note place="margin">vvhat pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerueth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monvvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</note> as Solon being aſked what preſerued a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthe, anſwered when the ſubiectes obey the magiſtrates, and the magiſtrates the lawes. This ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the kept the Venetians common welth ſo longe, and ſo many hundreth yeres in tranquilitie and honor, in that they haue ſought to reuerence good lawes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d obey their maieſtrats, not becauſe their Ariſtocratie is the beſt kynd of Gouernment (as by no meanes it is nether by reaſon, experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, nor iudgement of Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loſophers. Let vs therfore contende wyth them, in that preſerueth them, whiche is humble obedience, faythfulnes,<note place="margin">The calof the ſedici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</note> and true ſeruice to our countrie, and the head therof. And thinke that it is the call of Sathan, that moueth vs to the contrary, to entangle vs lyke a cunnyng fouler, vſinge ſuch a voyce as we lyke, in the net of deſtruction, both of body and ſoule. If we obey, and do our dutie: all the bleſſinges of God ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:466:64"/>be poured vpon vs. VVe ſhall lyue in peace bothe of bodie and mynde, with leyſure and libertie to ſerue God freely, without feare of thennemie to encombre vs in our poſſeſſions,<note place="margin">All good things fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovve obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience.</note> ordrede of Antechriſte to vexe our conſcience. Our land ſhall haue Raine and ſunne ſhine in dewe ſeaſon, our cornes and frutes ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, our cattell and goodes ſhall encreace, oure bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhalbe without diſeaſes, our myndes quiet with out croſſes, our wiues ſhall not be barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, our childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no vnthriftes, our ſeruauntes no loyterours, nor pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, our neighbours not enuious but louinge, oure counſellours wyſe and prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, our men of warre cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ragious, our preachers faithful and not lordlyke, our lawyers not couetous, our iuſtices no bribares, oure lordes and noble men no fooles, our officers no ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, and our gouernors no tyrauntes. For where as God ſaieth elles Dabo vobis regem in ira inea.<note place="margin">Oſe. 13.</note> I will geue them a kyng when I am angry, to anger them: He ſhall then ſaye to the contrary, Conſtituam ſuper illos vnctum meum qui regnabit inter illos in aeternum. I wyll apoint them a prince that they ſhall neuer bee wery of, nor that ſhal deale with them vncurteouſly. Do you not heare how lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tably your natural mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your countrey of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,<note place="margin">Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des voyce to hir cluldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> calleth vpon you for obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces ſaying. Oh, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber my dear chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren in what caſe you ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, your enemies be rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, lyke vnſaciable rauenours to pluck me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, to caſt you out of my lap where I haue this. 110 yeres lyke a faithful mother nouriſhed you, a tyme ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for me I trow to know you, &amp; you me. I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue bene and am glad of you, I delight and reioyce in
<pb facs="tcp:466:65"/>you, aboue all other peoples. In declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof I haue always ſpued out &amp; caſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me Danes, Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che, Norwegia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and Scottes. I could brooke none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the tender loue that I bare vnto you, of whome I haue my name. I neuer denyed to miniſter to you my ſingular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, which God hath lent me for you, as corne and cattell, lande and paſture, wull and cloth,<note place="margin">Englandes liberalitie toward hir children.</note> lead and tynne, fleſhe &amp; fiſhe, gold and ſiluer, and all my other treaſures: I haue poured them out among you, and enriched you aboue all your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours about you: which make them to enuie you, &amp; couet me. Beſides this God hathe brought forthe in me, the greateſt and excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſt treaſure that he hath, for your comfort and al the worldes. He would that out of my wombe ſhould come that ſeruaunt of his your brother Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> VVyclefe, who begate Huſſe, who begat Luther, who begat truth. VVhat greter honor could you or I haue,<note place="margin">Chriſtes ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cond birth in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> then that it pleaſed Chriſt as it were in a ſecond birth to be borne again of me amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you? And will you now ſuffer me, or rather by your diſobedience purchaſe me, to be a mother withoute my childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to be made the nurſe of a ſorte of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fideles Idolaters and Turkes? Can I abide to be with out you, or can you be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to be without me? Oh God graunt that I neuer ſe the day that the baſterdly brode of ambytious frenche men, eate and enioy the frutes whiche I prepare for you my deare chyldren: Lette me rather ſatiſfie my thirſte with their effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate bloud, then they ſhould pluck from you my motherly breaſtes: Sticke to youre mother, as ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:466:65"/>ſticketh to you. Let me keepe in quiet and feede as I haue done your wyues, your children, and your kinſfolkes: Obey your miſtres and mine which God hath made lady ouer vs, bothe by nature and lawe. You can not be my children, if you be not her ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes: I wyll none of you, if you will none of hir. If you loue me you can not hate hir, as my hope is you doo not: if you obey her, honour hir, and loue hir, be you aſſured that I wyll not fayle you at your neede, with any of my good frutes that you can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre: I wyll fill your boſomes and your mouthes, your wyues, and your children, with plentie. And if your enemies come againſt you, I will ſound ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible againſt them, that their hartes ſhall fayle them to come of the Seas and treade vpon me. I wyll not ſuffer ſo vyle a nacion to remayne quietly, or to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue any fotinge in me: wherfore as a friende I exhorte you, and as a mother require you (my dere Englyſh chyldren,) to knyt your ſelues together with bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue, and with vnfained obedience, to defende me and my gouerneſſe agaynſt thoſe your auncient enemies, whiche euer were in feare of you and yet be. If they attempte any thinge againſte me, playe the men, and honour me with the ſacrifice of their heads and carcaſes. Then ſhall I thynke that you bee no mungrelles but the trewe poſteritie of my auncient childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the olde Engliſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which by their valiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe made me lady of Fraunce, and gouerneſſe of al their chefe cyties, follow your fathers ſteps, &amp; dele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d your mothers honour. Be no ſlaues wher you haue bene
<pb facs="tcp:466:66"/>lordes, nor ſubiectes, where you haue bene rulers.</p>
            <p>¶ Thus good trew harted Engliſhe men, ſpeaketh your countrey vnto you, not in worde but in deede. VVherfore geue no dulle eare to hir, nor harken not to any vayne blaſtes or voyces whiche maye drawe you from the loue of your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, from the ſauing of your ſelues, and &amp; the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of your ſouereigne. You ſhall finde loue for your obedience, faithe for your truthe, care and ſtudy to kepe you, for your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy good will to obey hir. Let no enchauntment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witche you. Let no ſpiririte deceaue you. Let no ſtraunger make you ſtraungers to your ſelues. You ſee their reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be triſles &amp; their wordes but wynde, whiche goo aboute by their bluſterynge blaſtes to blowe you, fyrſt from youre dutie to God, whiche commaundeth you to obeye youre Rulars, next from your faith whiche you owe to your prince, for that care and loue whiche ſhe beareth toward you. And laſt of all from your quiet and countrey: which you can not enioye, but by doing your dutie in obey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing. Let vs therfore good brethren I beſcche you in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der mercies of God, in the bowelles of Chriſte, ſtoppe our eares from hearing, ſtaye our myndes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conceauing, and ſhut vp our mouthes from vttering any ſuche venyme or poyſon: whiche theſe mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bankes brynge out of our enemies lande, to inſecte, poyſon, and corrupt vs, vnder the pretence of play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to ſalue vs.</p>
            <p>¶ Let vs heare God rather then man, which crieth and commaundeth vpon payne of dampnacion, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his lieutenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſupreme officer: Againſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:466:66"/>we can not kicke, but we muſt be Gods enemies, falſe ſubiectes, and Satans ſeruantes.</p>
            <p>¶ Let vs ſeke to requite her with thankfulnes, which ſtudieth to kepe vs in quietnes. Let vs daylye call to God with lifted vp heartes and handes, for her preſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation and long lyfe: that ſhe may many yeares cary the ſworde of our defence, and there with cutt of the head of that Hidra, the Antichriſt of Rome, in ſuche ſort, as it neuer growe againe in this realme of England: that Gods glory maye flory ſhe, good mens conſcience may beat reſt, this noble Realme in honor, &amp; the Quenes Maieſtie in long ſeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, which God grauut. Amen⁂</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:466:67"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>pseudonymous printer's device of John Day, featuring a hand holding a birch twig emerging from a cloud above a globe or orb (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <q>Who ſo knoweth the Lordes Will and doth it not ſhalbe beaten w<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many ſtripes <bibl>Luke XII</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:466:67"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
